hello today we're going to be looking at
running the esp32 code
on an emulator the technology that we
use to do this is called qemu or quick
emulator
and we can go to a google search and we
can look for
qemu
and here we will find some information
about
kwema or qemu
and you can see over here under user
mode it tells you you can run various
different types of architectures
including
the esp32 architecture extension which
is pretty cool now if you're looking for
what's going on behind the scenes we can
go through to the github repository
of espressif
[Music]
and if we have a look at this
and under this repositories over here we
can search for qemu
and we can see that there is a fork of
the original qemu that has especially
been designed to run esp32 chips we can
also go through to the wiki over here
and get much more information if you
read this over here it'll basically tell
you that you need to compile it on your
machine i have a windows machine and
there's quite a few prerequisites that
you'll need to basically install
and becomes a bit of a pain in the butt
because there's quite a bit of work
involved however if you're using the
espresso vs code extension we have a
docker container that we can use so
if you're brand new to this stuff
there's a couple of things you're going
to need firstly just very quickly head
over to my course
learn esp32.com go to the course and
look at the free videos specifically the
environment setup and go ahead and
actually install your environment then
you're gonna have to head over to
docker
and you're gonna need to go ahead and
read up and how to actually install
docker on your machine so if i look over
here i'll notice that i have docker
started
okay
so let's get cracking with this thing
here i have vs code opened a brand new
vs code instance and i'm just going to
hit f1 and i'm going to say esp-idf new
project if you don't see it you can just
go esp idf
call on new project
let's go ahead and select that and we'll
give it a name this is going to be
qemu
test
one
and i'll put it into a temporary
directory somewhere
see projects my spike directory that's
where i have all my play code now i'm
going to just go ahead and say choose
this template and i'm going to hit this
extension over here i'm going to choose
the esp-idf and i'm going to go ahead
and say sample project and create
project and it's going to ask me
this has been created do you want to
open it up in a new window
yes i do
okay brilliant
so here i have a brand new project
notice that we've got this dev container
over here that is the docker file that
we need in order to run our qmu instance
but for now what i'm going to be doing
is i'm just going to be writing a little
bit of code okay and the question is do
we have some intellisense so let's have
a look so hash include
esp underscore log dot h
the pso that's great so
so let's go ahead here and create a
while loop
so while true
so let's go ahead and print out a log
we'll say
esp underscore
log
i
for log informational
and we have the option the first thing
tells me that we can put a tag in there
so we'll just uh put something like qemu
in there and then essentially we can put
in some sort of message we say running
q emu
count
percent d
we haven't got something there just yet
so let's go ahead and create something
there
we'll see over here into count
is equal to zero
over here we'll basically say count
plus plus
then i'd like to add in a short delay so
to do that i'll need to add the free
rtos libraries
hashing code free r toss
free artist.h
as well as hash include
prioritis
task.h
then over here
we can say the task delay
and then we can use the macropdms2tx
and over here we can put in the miller
seconds we want to delay i'll just put
in 1000.
okay so that is our code written done
now before we even try to compile this
thing what i'd like to do is actually
open it up in my docker container as you
know it is as it does have this doc this
dev container so what i'm going to do is
i'm going to hit f1 and i'm going to say
open in remote location so remote
container reopening container that's
what i want so make sure everything's
saved and let's go ahead and do that and
we can see that it's starting the dev
container
all right so it looks like it's now
started up which is great so let's go
ahead and open up our main again and we
can see our code that we've just written
and at this point we can go ahead and
build it that's the first thing that we
will need to do for running it in an
emulator is actually build it
so over here you can see that you can
just press that esp-idf build that's one
way to do it
my preference is to actually open up a
terminal and then write the commands
which is idf dot py
build
and uh as this is the first time it's
actually building this it might take a
minute or two
okay so it has now built successfully
you might notice that the intellisense
have got has gone a bit wonky
um if we have a look at what's happening
inside our vs code file we'll notice
that the c plus plus properties is all
pointing to my c drive and obviously my
docker container doesn't know where my c
drive is so if you wanted to fix that
you could go ahead and actually find
where the
gcc extension or gcc
compiler is and essentially add that
here and then go through to the settings
and change all these parts
correctly but that's not the point of
what we're trying to do here so let's
not worry about that too much right now
uh what i am going to do is i'm going to
create a new file here let's put it on
the root and i'm just going to call this
commands
and i'll just make it a text file
so
i'm just going to put the commands that
i'm going to be running inside here just
so that we can actually see what we need
to do so the very first step of actually
getting qemu up and running is we need
to actually combine all our bin files if
we have a look at the build folder we'll
notice that there's actually a couple of
different bin files the primary being
this one over here qme test one bin
that's the bin file that was just
generated by building this project
however if we have a look at the
flasherogs.json
we'll notice actually at this point in
time there's actually three
bin files and it'll actually tell us
where they are
there's the partition table boom there
is the bootloader bin
and then there's this one over here
also interestingly is notice the offset
of where they are this is essentially
where they would
be written to within the actual flash so
what we need to do is we need to
actually create a single file that
represents what our flash is going to
look just to uh be clear as to what it
is that we're trying to do what we'll
need to do is we need to create a file
and this file will need to be four
megabytes large because that is the size
of my flash then starting at about 1000
wherever that is over here we'll need to
basically start writing in the
bootloader
and that's going to happen at
and that's going to happen at 0x1000
of this file then a little bit later we
need to write
the partition table
at 0x
8000 i believe it is
and then a little bit later at 10 000 we
need to write our app
so we can go ahead and actually get some
python 2 or some javascript to actually
put together a file like that for us
luckily we don't need to do that there's
actually a command that will do it for
us and what i'll do is i'll just go
ahead and paste this in here and then
we'll walk through what it actually does
so what this is doing is it's basically
launching this
esptool.py which is essentially a
very common tool that we use with the
chip and you'll notice it's forward
slash dot forward slash which basically
means i want to execute this thing and
over here we basically specify which
chip is we want the esp32 but it could
also be the s2 or the c3 or whatever it
is then we've got this command called
merge bin which is what we want to do we
want to merge all these bin files
together um the output will be
results.bin that's essentially the new
bin file that it's going to create with
all the mergers all right full flash
size is gonna be four megabytes because
that's how big my flash is then starting
at 1000 hex we're gonna go ahead and get
the bolt bootloader bootloader bin which
is build bootloader
bootloader bin over there then starting
at 8 000 we're gonna go build partition
table partition table the bin partition
table partition table type bin and then
finally at ten thousand we're going to
go to build commute test two which is
essentially on here except for it's not
queuing test two qme
test dash one
qme test dash one bin yep that looks
good and then flash mode dio and then
flash frequency and flash size so if we
go ahead and
put that in here
and i press enter it says that it's
written it so let's go to the root of
the project and we'll notice over here
i've got this resulted bin so that's my
combined bin file
okay cool so that's the first thing we
needed to do the next thing we needed to
do is we need to basically run qemu
and to do that we're just basically
going to look at this command over here
so we're going to run qemu system
extension so this particular executable
is actually
recognized by this environment so
there's actually this is part of my
environment variables already so i don't
need to go ahead and look for it it's
already there which is quite nice
because of this docker the way because
of the way this docker container has
been set up right uh we're going to run
no graphic machine is esp32 the drive is
going to be this result.bin which is
essentially what we generated over here
and there's some sort of other options
as to how it should actually recognize
this particular flash file so i'm just
going to copy that
and i'm going to paste this in here and
if we did it right we can see yeah it's
starting and we can see i'll count one
two three and so on okay interestingly i
find it very hot i don't know how to
basically exit out of this so i'm just
going to go ahead and kill it and
there's essentially two more options
that are of interest to us the minus s
lower case we'll put it into debug mode
so that we can actually debug it and
minus capital s means
hold the execution don't start it until
you actually have a breakpoint on there
so let's go ahead and run this one now
so i'll just go ahead and create a new
instance for a new shell
and run this and we should see it's we
should see it start but then it should
just stop
so there it is it's waiting for us and
it says your application is running on
port 1234 is available okay cool now our
debugger is waiting on a port we need a
way to actually hook up a debug port or
debug remotely on this particular port
unfortunately the espressive launch.js
doesn't allow us to do that at least not
that i've been able to see so if i go
ahead and launch this nothing happens
oh we just get this error so what i'm
going to do is i'm going to go to the
extensions i'm going to put in here gdb
and the one that we want is this thing
called gdb lldb this one works quite
well so this native debug so go ahead
and install it and once that's installed
let's go back to our launch.json and
we're going to add a configuration and
now that we've actually got that
extension we'll see these gdb
entries come up and what we want to do
is we want to connect to a gdb server
and we're going to be modifying this a
bit so you'll notice over here that
we've got some intellisense for some
additional stuff the thing that we need
to do is actually get the gdb path
and
this is essentially going to be the
extension gdb debugger so let's go ahead
and actually open up a new terminal and
we'll just go ahead and find it quickly
so i'll just go cd
to the root and then i'll say find
look everywhere with a name and this is
where it gets tricky is extinct
extension
esp32 dash elf
dash g
d b so let's go ahead and find that guy
and there it is so that's the full path
so let's go ahead and copy that
and that'll be our gdb path
the request is going to be attached the
name let's go attach to
q e m u
our executable will be the elf file
inside our build so that'll be if we
have a look for the l file here it'll be
this one cumin test one elf
so let's go ahead and grab that name so
we can use the dollar
workspace
variable forward slash build
for the build directory forward slash
qm test one elf the target is going to
be colon one two three four so that's
essentially the default port for qmu
current working directory is definitely
this uh workspace route that's good and
we'll try it with this pretty print on
let's see what happens so i'm gonna go
ahead and save that now just one thing
before we end up here is this dot
forward slash needs to change to just
forward slash
because it's not relative
it's essentially from the beginning of
the route so now that we've got that
right um let's go ahead and save it well
we don't need this terminal so we'll
basically go ahead and close that
and we're sitting over here and it's
waiting for us to attach
so with that let's go ahead and make
sure we've got the attach to qmu
selected and let's go ahead and press
the play button
and we can see that we're hitting a
breakpoint and essentially we can f10
through that and we can mouse over the
count we can play and it'll come back
and we can go to our terminal and we can
still see the output over there and we
can see the local variables over here
and a little bit of the stack trace over
here step over all right and that's it
so now we've seen how to set up qemu
with the breakpoint and run some esp32
code
as an emulator i hope this video was
useful to you and it potentially saved
you some time and if it has please
consider subscribing to my channel and
liking my video
other than that please also consider
supporting my patreon account as it will
enable me to produce high quality videos
like this thank you again for watching
and see you later