you're here to learn about Lua so let's
just go ahead and get started we're
going to cover all the basic syntax
we're going to cover comments we're
going to cover all the primary types of
variables that you're going to use
inside of Lua how to define them and how
to use them we're going to talk about
control flow we'll talk a little bit
about modules then we'll talk about some
more advanced function features
following up with some meta tables and
then a little bit of bonus for uh for
those of you who make to the end of the
video before we do that though we need
to get a little bit of background sorted
out Lua is elegant it's a beautiful
language and if you think it's not
because it has one-based indexing I've
got a video for you in the description
but that's not what we're going to talk
about today Lua a primary idea inside of
it is mechanisms over policies which
means that instead of having special
keywords for things like classes Lua
allows you to use its simple building
blocks to compose more complicated ideas
so this is it Lua gives you the
mechanisms to implement them instead of
special keywords or special things built
into the language what's beautiful about
this is that lets us explain all of the
Practical things you need to know to get
started with Lua in one video it's very
easy to pick up and very easy to get
started it's also designed to be
embedded in this case right here you're
actually going to see me inside of my
neovim program execute Lua live and see
the results it's embedded inside of
neovim you might also be here because
you want to know because you're modding
in WoW or something like that I don't
know L is embedded in a bunch of
different places and I just think it's
really cool I think it really executes
well on its design principles and really
targets those it knows how to say no
which is very important for a language
C++
anyways first thing comments it's really
simple they start with a dash dash it's
a comment it ends at the end of the line
you want to do multi-line comments you
got to do Dash Dash and then these
little bracket guys we're going to see
them again in a moment simple literals
look like this numbers just type the
number guys I don't think you really
need me to tell you this but basically
you can sort of think of this as local
that says hey don't make this a global
variable and then this establishes a new
name within the current scope then
you've got number equals five okay right
so that sets the number equal to five we
have strings with double quotes with
single quotes and once again we got the
little double bracket guys and once
again this makes something that was
before a single line kind of construct
into something that can stretch over
multiple lines we've got booleans you
know truth is true and lies is false you
can set multiple values in one line like
this we're going to be returning there
later and last but not Le well actually
last and least is nothing or the nil
value right so it's nil and you can use
that as a proper value and there's a few
tricks with that later but we'll come
back to that too functions are first
class in Lu which pretty much just means
hey you can make them as values right uh
there's two primary ways we Define them
one one is like this where we say a
local function name of the function and
then any arguments inside we have the
body and then it ends with end Lua
doesn't use a lot of brackets for
denoting scope it usually uses words I
think it's kind of pretty I really think
you won't notice it after you write it
for a little while uh the other way that
you can Define functions is doing
something like this local greet and then
since functions can be values this
section right here defines a new value
of a function and assigns it to greet
just like we did for these other simp Le
values here in this example we've got a
higher order function which is just a
function that returns another function
and in this case this function takes in
a value and then we use that in our sum
that we're going to do later so in this
case we have add one we we sort of get
that value from this higher order one
right we which binds value right here
those are called up values you don't
need to know about that today you can
just think about ah it saves off that
value so if we execute this we'll see
that the output is add one of
two that's three okay hopefully you're
following along right hopefully that
part wasn't too crazy okay and so that's
sort of the output of doing that in Lua
we basically only have one way to store
data and that's tables tables are like
lists where you can have you know a
sequential index of values and you can
iterate over them and store them but
they're also like Maps or dictionaries
from python land where you can store
different different things inside their
keys and map from one value to another
so the first thing is we can use tables
like a list so this is like we have the
first value is first and then two and
then false and then a function Lu's
lists can be heterogeneous right they
can have different values Lua doesn't
care it'll put all of them in a list for
you so if we get the first
value Yes you heard me write the first
value we're going to get first
hey nice right nice that's what you'd
expect is because first is the first
thing anyways so now we get fourth is
four and we print this value uh and we
call this function before we do so it
prints right here but that's beside the
point right so we get a function out of
the fourth spot so that's tables as
lists but we also have tables as Maps
there's a few different ways you can
write values here you can do a literal
key uh this basically just translates to
the same thing as if you did uh a string
here except if it doesn't have special
characters like spaces or like pluses or
ATS or all this other stuff you can just
write it without the additional quotes
and then sets it equal to a value the
other thing you can do is inside of
brackets right here like this you can
put any expression you want and then
that's a key and then you can set a
value to
here you can even do functions now pause
here and
think pause here and think what is going
to get printed here so so this one
probably you can guess t. literal key
right that's kind of the same thing as
indexing with a string what do you think
is going to get printed for this last
one pause right okay and now execute and
you'll see nothing nothing gets printed
here because this function is a
different function than this Lou doesn't
know what's inside of the functions
right it's just sort of like uh by not
just like uh whether they're
referentially trans it doesn't really
matter right these two different things
are two different functions because we
made them two different times so they're
like different pointers it's not a huge
deal right now but it's just something I
wanted to point out because it might be
confusing if you expected those to be
the same because they're the same
function no they point to different Lua
functions it's okay if you don't get it
just skip that
part we are not going to cover threads
and user data mostly because you're not
going to encounter these that often
threads are from the co-routine
librarian Lua which is a very cool
Cooperative sort of scheduling thing
that you can do but most of the time
you're not going to run into those or at
least not directly and user data is when
you have some C library that's going to
interact with Lua and you probably won't
interact with that at the beginning
either but those are the only other two
types of variables that we didn't cover
so control flow the first kind of for
Loop we have here is if we have
something like a list of something we
want to iterate over those items we can
say four and then we have a variable
equals and then this is start and stop
this hashtag favorite accounts isn't
actually a #that's an Octor and it is
the length operator so it gets the
length of 1 two three and so when we run
this we'll see one two 3 right that's
the index one two 3 and then we can
index into our list to print out those
values of tgtv the Prime and terminal.
Shop by the way the other way that we
can do this is we can use what's called
I pairs right and this is sort of like
um in in index pairs the iterative pair
here right and this returns two values
the index and the value at that index
notice how in this version we didn't
have to sort of index back into the
array this just returns it directly and
those two things are basically the same
but what's going to happen here what's
going to happen here if we try and do
the same idea over a map it's not going
to do anything that's because this
length operator for tables operates on
sort of the idea of I can only give you
the length of an array that's or of a
table that acts like an array right so
I'm looking for sequential things that
aren't nil so when we execute this
literally nothing's going to happen
because this is going to this is
essentially saying for index equals 1 to
zero okay well I'm done skip to the end
we need a new function to help us out
here that function is pairs so I pairs
is I like to think of it in my head
integer pairs cuz it's the integer
numbers that we have and then pairs is
just for all the values so if we print
this off we'll see that hey the reading
scores for thdv is 9.5 that's the key in
value and for the primagen it's not
applicable notice that we can store
different values in the in the values
itself different types of things it
doesn't matter that this one's a number
this one's a string Lua doesn't care
about that next thing if so in this case
it's very similar to how you're probably
expecting most ifs things to work in
languages the only thing is it's not
there's no like parentheses required
around here and there's no curly braces
so you just write if you know loves
coffee then you should check out SSH
terminal. shop it's cool else they
should still check out SSH terminal do
shop it's still cool so if we execute
this we'll see um we'll see those values
here and the only thing to note here
that we haven't talked about yet is the
only falsy values are nil and false
everything else is true so zero empty
table a function with no return whatever
it doesn't matter only nil and false are
the false values everything else will uh
sort of evaluate to a truthy value and
go down this path so that's for if
statements there's also else if you can
figure that out I I know you you if
you're this far in the video you can
figure out how to do else if anyways
modules this is once again we're going
back to this idea of mechanisms over
over policies Lua doesn't have a special
thing that's magical about a particular
block of code to make it a module
instead files are just big Lua functions
effect effectively and so if I had a
file like fu. Lua you might see it start
off with something like local m equals a
table that capital M once again nothing
magic it's just kind of convention that
people use to stand for module so I can
set values on my table just the same way
that we were during doing earlier and
return that we don't have to return a
table it's just usually good to return a
table because you might want to add
other functions later or do other things
like that so it gives you a little bit
more flexibility but if we're in another
file bar. Lua and assuming Foo is like
on a runtime path and all this other
stuff we can do local fu is require Foo
this name could be anything we want
usually it's good to name it a name that
sort of reflects the thing that you're
importing here or requiring and then can
call food. cool function right which was
defined on this original table so
modules are just basically the result of
whatever is returned from a file if we
removed this return here then this would
break because nothing gets returned from
the file so that's like returning
nil okay few more things about functions
functions can have multiple return
values which means in this case this one
returns four values 1 2 3 4 and when we
sort of receive those values or try and
and place them into something we get
first second last in this case so what's
going to happen here is the first value
gets put in so that's this one that goes
here second goes here third goes here
into last and we discard any additional
values if you have something here
basically Lua is going to let you uh
unpack those values until it notices
something that's going to take its place
now that probably doesn't make any sense
but let's give an example here this
function takes a variable amount of
arguments which is denoted by a nice
Ellipsis or ellipse I guess is sort of
the single ellipse I actually don't
remember um and you can place this
inside of some table like this to put
all of the values inside so this is
going to say hey take all of the things
that you put right here right you
because like you're literally replacing
the text so take all the arguments that
you passed here put them here so it's
like writing hello world and exclamation
right and that puts it in a table now
you can see do our ey Pairs and we're
printing those and then we're end and
then we return the arguments back so
that's not that exciting you know it's
not a very cool example but in this case
because there's nothing following the
call to this variable arguments function
it's going to return all of those back
to print since print can take multiple
values it's going to print all of those
for the second one though notice this is
kind of like there's only one slot to
put the result of variable arguments so
take a guess at what's going to happen
based on how we did this before when we
run this for ourselves you'll see that
the output here looks like we're going
to print all the arguments one hello two
world three bang right so that's the
same between each but notice how in this
number two we lost the rest of the
arguments that's because we only have
one slot if you want to call it that to
place the uh the value okay so that
means we just discarded the rest of the
arguments that's kind of a thing it's
just going to let you discard stuff
that's totally
fine and the another thing that we need
to talk about for functions is how you
can call them obviously you can call
them with parenthesis we've already done
this the parentheses go here not like a
list where they go beforehand but if
there's only one argument that you're
passing and it's a string literal you
can actually drop the parentheses and
just go something like this single
string high and if you run this you'll
see that these two values are exactly
the same no errors so sometimes you'll
see this um dropped with the parentheses
when there's one string I don't do it as
often for Strings but I do it very often
for this scenario which you can do the
same thing for tables I usually do this
most often when I want to sort of
emulate um like optional or default
default arguments Lua doesn't have those
once again doesn't have a policy for how
you would Define uh what are optional
arguments or default arguments or how
you would say it's required but it has
this doesn't have that idea instead what
you can do is sort of emulate this by
directly passing a table with no
parentheses and it looks like you're
calling it with something like oh
default is 12 and others false right and
in this case we can check inside of this
function oh did we pass a default value
right so if we didn't pass one it'll be
nil okay then we'll set ops. default
equal 17 and then we can print these two
not the most exciting function but when
we do this sorry for smashing the
microphone you'll see that 12 and false
right so that's our default 12 and
others false or right for our second
option other is true we didn't pass def
fault so we get 17 true so that's the
two other ways that you might see people
calling functions which is definitely
surprising the first time that you see
these parentheses dropped and it just
looks like people are coming up with
their own magic stuff this only works
for literal strings and literal tables
those are the only times that works so
we have one other sort of uh Edge
scenario to consider for functions which
is when we Define a function on a table
so let's say we have some table like
this if we do a DOT right then we have a
list of arguments here so we can write
function uh you know like the table name
dot something else and then these two
things are actually equivalent so this
colon sort of magically creates this is
like the only syntax sugar that Lua has
and usually people use this to Define
like some sort of object system or
inheritance or to use something about
the table itself um but if you see this
coal in here all that does is it's
translating this idea into this idea
okay and and really it's just saying uh
I'm going to call something on my table
where the first argument is going to be
like inserted as self and it will be the
table that I'm calling we'll see an
example of this shortly in metat table
so if that didn't make sense just uh
just keep that in mind that this colon
is just syntax sugar for DOT and self
okay all right so metat tables metat
tables
are you know like it's a thing about
tables right that's the meta and the
tables they describe or change the
behavior of tables uh this is really
similar to like thunder methods in
python or like how you would Implement
different traits maybe in Rust right
which is that basically what we can do
is we can say hey I will give you a
table and it will describe what you
should do under various scenarios uh
within the language the first one we'll
do which is the really simplest one is
ADD so right down here we're going to
add two tables normally that would be
bad you can't just do like Lua table
plus table that's not good okay if we
just like try and add these it says hey
you just tried to perform arithmetic on
table values no no no don't do that so
instead we need to define a way for how
we could add two tables and in this case
we sort of have an idea of a vector you
know like some Vector three and each of
them has three values right and we're
going to tell it hey here's what I want
you to do when I add these two items
right so it's like left and right so
this V3 is the result of V1 + V2 and if
we execute this you'll see that hey V3
V3 right here 1 two 3 right so if we add
these two values these are going to
cancel out that's the zero and we have
one and two that's three and then five
and two that's seven and then if we
added V3 to itself that should work just
fine too if we print the whole table
we'll see 0 6 and 14 right which is
basically doubling all of these and L
knows that this has a meta table with an
add function inside of it that's how it
determines that this little plus guy
here needs to do something besides the
normal thing that it does when you try
and add two tables which is throw an
error there's a bunch of different these
are usually called meta methods because
they're things on a table that we can do
the other one that's kind of cool in
this scenario that I wanted to go over
is called index so index is called
whenever you try try to get a value from
a table that does not exist so in this
case we create an empty table and we set
its metat table to this Fibonacci metat
table we just made and this key is the
value that we're looking for right so
when I call FIB five this doesn't have
FIB five right it's not it's not around
there's nothing set inside of the table
already so it's going to call this
function it will then check these and it
says the key is not less than two okay
so I'm not going to return and then what
it's going to do it's going to update
the table and it's going to call these
functions and funny enough in this case
we're actually showing how this can be
recursively called right it's going to
look for self key minus 2 and it's going
to do the normal Fibonacci thing that I
think most of you probably know but the
like cheeky cute result here is that
we're caching these sort of
automatically inside of here because
we're updating this table that's what
self is this is like if we go back a few
pages here where we talked about the
colon argument where did I already go
past it was I not paying attention I
already went past it I wasn't paying
attention sorry right here this self is
the table that the method is getting
called on okay so this self is actually
this table so when we update its value
we're saving or caching these values
along the way so instead of taking
forever to calculate FIB 1000 we can
execute it practically instantly because
we're going to save the values along the
way right you can use a bunch of
different options for this you could
like calculate default values that might
be expensive or provide something that
always doubles a key whatever you want
it's a function you can write the code
uh the other two notable meta methods we
should talk about are new index new
index actually gets called when we're
right here which is self key and then
value so that's sort of like self key
and value those are the things that
would get called so you can actually
override what happens when you do new
index uh you could create like a locked
table that just errors inside of new
index and you don't allow it the other
one that's kind of cool is call which
lets you call a table as a function so
you could like store some state sore
some mutable State and call function on
it you'll see this one used um a bit as
well a little less off than then index
and new index so some quick neovim
goodies because now you actually know
basically everything you need to do to
get started writing Lua that's it that's
pretty much the whole language okay it's
really cool here's a few things you can
do I like these key mappings for myself
so you can do Vim keymap set space xx
and that sources a file so let's yo this
and we'll do our same um we'll do our
same sort of thing that we did last time
in the series which was I had my envm
example here and I opened up my init Lua
these are not that exciting uh functions
so we're going to we'll keep the print
just so we know what's happening here
and if I Source this file what we're
going to see now is that we actually
have this key map set for us so if we do
no no remap uh space to see what we have
we see space space X sources the file so
when I press space space X it prints
Advent of neovim if I had you know one
two three like this and I go space space
X it's going to execute the file and run
everything inside of it okay so that's
pretty cool but something that we could
do instead as well that I think is
really nice is sometimes you want to
execute something that's just like the
current line so we could put this in
here and I'll say my file and run space
space X to execute the file again now I
have space X to run just the current
line see how this is running whatever is
on the current line that I'm doing I'm
just pressing Space X here to do that uh
unrelated to um Space X the company but
obviously if uh if we could get
sponsored for just making key maps do
that that would be super cool uh the
last one that's really cool that I want
to show you is we can do I'm just going
to execute this current line by running
Space X now if I select some lines and I
press space X it's going to execute just
my selection these are really powerful
as we start to build more and more of
our neovim config we don't want to
completely reset neovim every time we
want to make a change we can use this
building block of uh keymaps to quickly
execute what we're working on and use
neovim in a live setting and these ideas
are basically how I was doing things
along the way to do cool stuff of
running this I just put it into you know
sort of a special uh buffer to look cool
so that you guys could see this the last
one that I'll do which I want to show
you is um is how we can use Auto
commands and a few of the other things
and how with just the tools that we've
learned so far today in
this 24 minute video that's longer than
I thought but that's okay uh 24 minute
video we should be able to understand
everything that's happening in this
chunk of code right so let's do that
we'll walk through it but sort of think
ahead of me maybe pause even read
through this code and then we'll work
through it together okay so paused okay
now we resume all right so in this case
we're going to use a Vim this looks like
a table because we got vim and then we
have API so we're accessing the API
field in vim and then we're going to
access the envm create autoc command
field in API right so we basically have
something like if you did Lua equals Vim
you can see it's a really big Global
with all of the different functions
available this is sort of like the Vim
Library automatically loaded in you can
do Lua equals vm. API and you can see
hey here's a bunch of different
functions and then we can even do Lua
vm. api. envm create auto command and
you'll see that that's a function you
say great we've got a function what are
we going to do here now if you don't
know what this function does inside of
new of him you should really try
something like this Auto Command right
cool now we can read The Help It says
creates an autoc command event handler
divined by callback or command and then
it gives you an example right in this
case this basically is like an event
listener if you don't know this is so
this says Hey listen to when we yank
some text and what are we going to do
we've got a table now right so we see
our table and we say okay so our
description that's what the desk is is
this string right so this is later when
we check this we'll be able to see what
the description was it has a group right
and we can just read this again we say
okay we're using vim's API we're
starting to piece together okay Vim is
very useful andm create our group right
and then we're going to do something
like Kickstart highlight yank it's cuz I
yanked this code from kick start which I
think is pretty
cool and then we're going to clear all
the other ones you might not know
exactly what that does but you could go
ahead and check create out group here
and say create or get an autoc command
group or autoc command groups if you
remember from last time we can press or
shift K to go inside of here and read
about this not going to read too much
about this but you should basically
think of this as saying like hey okayy
um I don't want to register this
multiple times okay so I'm going to make
sure that we clear all the old ones
before we make a new one and then hey
look at this we have a call back we make
a first class function and we call this
function Bim highlight on yank if I ex
oops if I execute this file by running
space space X and now I yank this line
You'll see I get a little nice helpful
sort of on yank uh option here that
shows me what I've just done if I do YG
then I've got the whole file so that's a
Lua overview that's a little bit of
goodies from NE next time we're going to
start using what we know about Lua now
to start uh building up our whole system
and working on that so I hope you like
this video I hope you like the quick
crash course on Lua and the beauty of
them goodies at the end please like And
subscribe oh if you made it this far and
you really like you know sort of um my
teaching style and other things like
this I'm making a big Lua course on
boot. deev this is the first time that
I've mentioned this any
um I already have a course on memory
management there so you can check it out
with promo code te tej at boot for 25%
off uh and I'm going to work on my luor
soon uh and yeah that'll come out at
some point anyways thanks for watching
really appreciate it hope you lik the
video bye everybody