my guest this week is Simon pton Jones
and I have to be kind of careful
introducing this one cuz I could turn
into a total Fanboy Simon is an absolute
Legend I've got such respect for him and
he's been a huge inspiration for me as
well as hundreds thousands of
programmers he's been a researcher and
groundbreaker in functional programming
for decades he's been one of the key
developers and Shepherds possibly even
midwives of hll which is one of my
favorite languages and Beyond what you
might consider the niche of hasal I
think you can feel his influence on any
language that's been touched by
functional programming trends in the
past few years anything from java to
python to F and Beyond he's even and
this is a kind of separate story but
he's even had a big influence on Excel
programming so despite hascal seeming
like a niche he might have affected more
computer users than just about any Lang
language researcher ever in addition to
all that all his Computing work and
wisdom he's also one of my all-time
favorite conference speakers I saw him
give a talk a few years back about a new
technique for optimizing the compilation
of let statements now in the hands of
literally anyone else that would be the
driest smallest topic you can imagine
but he has such Clarity for explaining
things and such raw enthusiasm for
programming I left that talk wanting to
write a compiler just so I could
optimize Le bindings kid you not he's
that
infectious so I would have gladly had
Simon on the show to talk about anything
that's on his mind but we narrowed it
down to three big topics his past how do
you build a language as large as hascal
out of a very small set of core ideas
what do you put in that core to make it
a larger
language once you've mastered that trick
we get to his present what he's been
doing for other languages Simon's been
working on verse over at epic games I
thought verse was a highlevel scripting
language for Unreal Engine for fortnite
extensions but it might just be a trojan
horse language for the idea of
functional logic programming what's
functional logic programming you ask
Simon's about to explain to us and as if
his past and present work weren't enough
he's also trying to influence all our
Futures he has been heavily involved in
Shifting the way we teach Computing in
this country in England and he wants to
spread that influence far and wide so
that children get taught the
fundamentals of computing just like
they're taught the fundamentals of maths
and
Sciences was if all that weren't enough
Simon's also a thoroughly nice chap so
let's get started I'm your host Chris
Jenkins this is developer voices and
today's voice is Simon pton Jones
joining me today is Simon Payton Jones
Simon how are you doing hi good to see
you again it's good to have you here so
I I was trying to think of how to
introduce you and how to pull together
all the threads of your career which is
a big task you are I wanted to say you
you are to functional programming what
James Brown was to
Soul you are in some sense The Godfather
of functional programming hardly there's
plenty of other Godfathers well yeah
it's it's it's a large family but you're
onwards and yeah yeah and indeed from
Alonzo church and on oh gosh you're
going get all that way back yeah
yeah wellit let's say you're standing on
the shoulders of giants but you're one
of the Giants upon whom we now
stand um I was trying to pull together a
thread that connects what you've done
that we could start with and the one
that jumped out at me was you've worked
on hll obviously a huge contributor to
hll you're currently working on verse
you are a contributor or were to C minus
minus and the thing that connects all
three of those which is I think is
fairly rare in programming language
implement a is they are a large outer
shell which is a lot of syntactic sugar
for a very tightly defined core
language is that fair to say that's true
of verse and haskal I'm not sure it's so
true of C minus
minus designed as a kind of portable
Assembly Language okay uh rather like um
uh rather like llvm has become but llvm
become much larger see was intended to
be um but yes for the um certainly for I
mean it's it's a fairly common pattern
uh to try to uh to design a a sort of a
a a large user friendly language um
which desugar into some some kind of
small elegant
core you seem to have pushed that much
further than most of the language
implementations I know about so I guess
the first question is why why do it that
way well for me it's a um um it's a
testament to the
uh expressiveness of the Lambda calculus
right so one of the things that always
attracted me about functional
programming um is that it's a place
where theory and practice come rather
close together um so you can build
practical programming language that
rests very directly um on some
intellectually robust and small and
elegant foundations so in the case of
the LDA calculus it was always um the
the Lambda calculus in in its in its
Essence is just a Lambda a Lambda term
is just the a variable an application or
Lambda um and what's amazing is that you
can translate an enormous um variety of
programs into that indeed uh um you
could almost imagine two different
foundations for computation this wasn't
the way that it happen but when Alonzo
church and Alan Turing they were
actually in the same University at
Princeton at the same time and Alonzo
church was defining the Lambda calculus
and touring was defining the touring
machine um and both of them are
computationally complete that is to say
uh um if we want to say what can
computers do fundamentally we say well
that they're just touring machines if a
during machine can do it a computer can
do it and vice versa yeah um but you can
also say um they're just Lambda calculus
machines right if a computer do it a
Lambda term can do it and in fact it was
entirely nonobvious but in fact it turns
out that touring machines and and Lambda
calculus are uh inter definable that is
you can write a touring machine which
will run any Lambda term and you can
write a Lambda term that'll run run a
touring machine right they're equally
expressive good yeah um so now then it
didn't really happen like this but you
can imagine that all of imperative
programming is built on touring machines
right was it a touring machine it it has
this tape and it mutates um you know
mutates the tape it it reads and writes
things on the tape the tape is like the
store um it's fundamentally a mutation
machine what is the Lambda calculus well
um at any moment you have a a term a
Lambda term and it simply um uh and you
rewrite it one step at a time just keep
rewriting and you get some answer and
this is a completely different model of
computation that's um and functional
programming is built on the that purely
functional model of computation
imperative program is built on a more um
M mutation based touring machine style
thing so it's almost as if two entire
approaches to programming have grown up
um built on different foundations but
that ultimately ultimately they're
equally expressive so for me um I've
always loved um the Lambda calculus as a
basis for computation and it turns out
that you can translate um well all sorts
of languages including hll into this
very small core and moreover the thing
that I appeal to me particularly um is
that uh that's not just a theoretical
idea it's a practical idea you can
actually build a compiler um that
translates into this small core and
moreover um the the Lambda calculus you
know had a long history of development
including typed Lambda calculi and in
particular a typed Lambda calculus
called system
F and it turns out that it's not just
most compilers typically most compilers
in the world typically take a a language
that might be statically typed and
translates it to some kind of
Intermediate Language and then optimizes
that but the Intermediate Language is
typically not statically typed um but in
GHC our compiler for hll we take the uh
hll and its um and all its glory and
translate it into this core language
system F which is statically typed so
very unusually jhc is one of the very
few production compilers I know that um
maintains a statically tight program
from the front of the compiler right
through to the code
generator I'm not thought of it that way
yeah and that's that's incident you
might you might ask why bother to do
that right well to do that because after
all um all that matters is that the
source program is statically typed right
and we reject it then but since the
intermediate program is statically typed
if the comp if there's a bug in the
compiler a very common uh you know which
is rather common I'm a compiler right
then uh then what happens often is you
get a type error in the intermediate
code right so the compiler has a bug it
optimizes program a into program B alas
program B is type Incorrect and when you
run it it will
crash yeah right so if you don't have a
typed Intermediate Language what happens
is you have a bug in your compiler you
compile a program you try to run the
program and it crashes you think why
does it crash so you can know get GDB
out and work out why it's crashes then
say Oh the code generator is generating
the wrong code why is that oh because
the intermediate program are you know
some many levels of transformation back
ah the optimizer introduced the bug the
optimizer turned a type correct program
into a type incorrect program which
crashes now it's way better for the
compiler to say uhoh I find that I have
turned a type incorrect program into a
sorry type correct program into a type
incorrect program and report so that
that reports the error immediately it
happens rather than compiling it all the
way to machine code running the machine
code and then having to backtrack up to
find the bug in the compiler yeah yeah
okay that makes sense but there's
there's this thing with like having this
tightly defined core which actually if
I'm right is fairly small I mean it's
implementable reasonably if you've got
the knowledge to do it yeah first of all
um I'm just thinking
a lot of people come to this idea as
being like
llvm in that there's this
lowlevel llvm is not as tightly defined
but I'm just trying to get a sense of
where something like ghc's core might
appeal to language implementers and
people interested in how languages are
implemented when they seem to already
have this popular thing called
llvm well by the time you get to llvm
you've already descended several layers
of abstraction right compilers typically
work at um various levels of abstraction
so if I've got a um you know hasore
program I might say to a programmer how
do if I'm trying to explain how it runs
I say well you've got this function call
you can replace the call by the body of
the function replacing the arguments of
the function with the actual arguments
that you passed in the call right now
you just keep doing that and that's how
the program executes of course that's
not really how the program executes um
but really the program does you know
machine transfers and pushes things on
stacks and have things in registers and
stores things in the Heap and runs a
garbage collector um so uh but but
nevertheless if you want to explain to a
programmer how it runs you might think
in this rewriting term rewriting way um
and indeed the optimizer Works in this
rewriting way as well but to get to lrvm
which is a low-level imperative language
you've now had to say oh I'm going to
you know I'm going to allocate function
you know closures for as yet unevaluated
thks and they're going to consist of a
poter to some code together with some
free variables and those are going to be
stored in the heat one at time and then
when have so there's a lot of very
low-level operations that mean that
doing the optimizations you could do in
a rewriting system at a higher level
become essentially completely
inaccessible by the time you get to the
low level right so and this is this is
not new right every compiler has this
idea of we do some Transformations and
optimizations using the high level code
and then we sort of move down to a low
level closer to the machine um and that
at that point the high level
optimizations become essentially
inaccessible but new lower level
optimizations like which register shall
I put it in become accessible right they
were not not expressible in the high
level stuff so the lrvm stroke C minus
minus part is really in ghc's back end
right this the
intermediate um language this system a
flight language that I was describing
which GHC uses mostly that is the sort
of the F the middle of GHC the long
middle that does lots of functional
programming kind of optimizations does
that make sense they're very different
purposes is what I mean it's not the one
is better than the other it's just
they're different so we're almost
talking about a three layer lasagna of
programming yeah yeah you take hcll you
turn it into core you optimize then you
turn it into l c minus minus or lvm and
you optimize some more yeah right okay
so what makes that middle layer the core
or some kind of design sweet spot is it
that it's got um a solid theoretical
backing or is it something else well um
you it's clear that you want to do some
Transformations at the high level when
you still have the notion of you know
first class functions and um and doing
beta reductions and so forth so um you
so you could imagine doing that on
Source
haskal yeah but that wouldn't be much
fun because s because Source haskal has
dozens and dozens and dozens of language
constructs all of which are really
syntactic sugar for some smaller thing
right so it's much more economical to do
a oneoff transformation that you know
gets rid of 20 constructs in favor of
one and then optimize the one rather
than try to optimize the
20 right so so what you want is to have
um an intermediate language that is that
retains all the high levelness that you
need for the optimization right without
any of the superficial syntactic sugar
right that's what makes it The Sweet
Spot I wonder if if I can ask the
similar question the other direction
then so if in a sense hascal boil away
all the sugar yeah and you get down to
this core but then you're saying um the
core of GHC is a very expressive
language could it have been boiled up to
a completely different looking language
is there something about hasal that pops
out of this core language or is the core
a substrate on which many languages
could be built oh no the core is a
substrate on which many languages could
be could be built you know that look
quite unlike Haskell really because it's
really just just a statically typed
Lambda calculus the big thing is that
the the thing that would make I mean
like could you take ml for example and
translate into core well um let's see so
uh uh mostly you could uh the thing is
that that ghc's called is a lazy
language it has um called by name
semantics um and ml is called by value
um and there's quite a lot of research
has been done about could you make a
single Intermediate Language in the
style of this core thing that was
equally good for core by value and call
by need languages no Source languages
you compile many many languages to them
I think the answer is probably yes um
but the details are quite it's quite
difficult to do a really good job of
both at once and in
practice
uh um you know they are
uh Haskell's core is skewed towards lazy
evaluation though it can it spends a lot
of effort on um corbar value as well and
similarly a compiler like the oaml
compiler that the folks are jam stre to
building um uh which they have an
intermediate language called I think F
Lambda they call it um
there they will be skewed towards call
by
value right so this starts to lead into
your current research topic because I
know you're working on another core for
another language that has a third call
semantics you you've been working on
verse yeah which is neither lazy nor
strict it's lenient is that lenient and
also but also more even more
significantly it's a functional logic
language so we talked about imperative
languages um haven't we which is you
mean do this and then do that things
like C or Java or Fortran or C++ um
that's a whole it's a whole class of
language then we got functional
languages par of which hcll is a is a
particularly what's the word um uh pure
example in the hascal hasc's default
mode of computation is purely functional
if you want to do side effects like
input output or mutating variables you
have to use the you know am monad um
so-call so that there's a type system
that keeps side effecting computation
separate from Pure computations so uh
whereas ml doesn't have ml is mostly
functional but you can have um side
effect in
computations as well without delineating
them in the types so we got imperative
programming functional programming both
of which I mean imperative programming
is the mainstream functional programming
is the thing to which I have essentially
devoted my professional life because I
thought it was so cool when I first came
across it when I was you know 21 or so
um and I became kind of addicted to it
and I I didn't think about it like that
at the time but essentially I've spent
my professional life trying to to say
how can we take the idea of purely
functional programming and really make
it go right knock down all the Practical
obstacles that make it hard to do in
practice um or running too slow or too
awkward just sort of you know Crush
those obstacles one at a time um and uh
and so that's what I spent my T to
Haskell is a Haskell is a um uh the
particular vehicle for that research
Endeavor if you like um and um and sure
enough as it turns out I mean research
Endeavors don't often um succeed in that
kind of way but sure enough it turns out
that haskal you know or on its own has
been has become relatively uh you know
successful as in it hasn't died out
after 30 years which most most research
languages don't last nearly that long um
but so functional programming as an
Enterprise has proved to be quite
influential in the mainstream so uh
languages like and I don't see sharp and
Python and so forth you can see and many
other languages you can see absorbing
functional language ideas now yeah yeah
alongside these two right has been
functional logic programming now that is
a much smaller Niche if you think
functional programming is Niche right I
don't think it's niche it's a big Niche
but nevertheless it isn't the mainstream
functional logic programming is much
less popular
I haven't even heard of it and I
consider myself fairly well informed so
yeah so what's functional logic
programming well you've heard of logic
programming like prologue right um and
there you have logical variables and
unification is a sort of key concept
when you're um working with prologue and
you can call you can make New Logic
available you can call functions passing
them arguments that are sort of not yet
completely filled in um it's a very
different approach to programming just
as functional programming makes you
rewire your brain logic programming
makes you rewire your brain too yeah now
um functional logic programming has grew
out of an attempt to say well logic
programming is quite cool and functional
programming is quite cool could we sort
of somehow um merge them so one way to
think of it is this in
hll um you can say let x equal um I
don't know uh um f of 17 in blah blah
blah so that says X is a variable
that denotes a value which is the result
of f of
17 so we that so it does two things it
brings X into scope and it tells you
what its value is it doesn't tell you
the answer of f17 it just say you tells
you that to compute its value you
compute f17 right right yeah um now but
nevertheless x x stands for just one
value in its scope right X doesn't stand
for three and then
four yeah right like in
if you say if you bring X into scope
it's a mutable cell that you then assign
to and maybe assign a different value
later and a different value later so X
is the name for a box whose value
changes over time in hle X is a name for
a value and only one value okay now in a
functional logic language you split the
let into two parts one is one brings X
into scope just says there is an X right
but says nothing about its
value and then SE separately to that you
can have equations that get that explain
something about the value of x so you
can say you can say bring X into scope
which in um R verse calculus we say
exists X right there is an X and then
somewhere in the scope of that exists
you could say x is a
pair so now you've now you've you've
given some extra information you said
it's not it's not a number it's not a
string it's definitely a pair but you
might say and it's the first and second
component of the pairs I'm not going to
tell you they're just Y and Zed
so you might say exists Y and Zed x
equals the pair y comma Zed so you've as
it were refined the value of x a little
bit okay yeah and then somewhere else
you might say first of x equals
three okay right and that's saying oh um
if you compute first of X which now we
can since we know that X is pair right
then then um then and the first
component remember was y then y must be
three
that's I mean that's a very unusual
thing in itself because it almost feels
like we're defining the something twice
well it's not we're not we're only
saying um if we if we say we could say x
equals x is the pair y z and elsewhere
you said x equals 3 in that case the
program would
fail right if you give contradictory
information about a one of these logical
variables right you say exist x 3 fail
right so deeply built into the idea of
functional logic programming is the idea
that a computation May Fail that is
return zero results and failure is not
necessarily
bad right failure is um any more than
false is bad or in hascal um a function
a function that returns a maybe value
which is a maybe value is either just X
or it's nothing so a lookup for example
might return and maybe value so in high
school if you do a lookup and it returns
nothing the value nothing that's not
wrong it's just that the look up didn't
find you know the the key in the
dictionary that's fine programming is
like that that's you know that indeed
that might be partly what you want to do
um so um so in inverse and in functional
logic pring failure is not um like uh
you know seg fault crash bad things
happen yeah it's not a moral judgment
it's just they correctly is no answer to
that the correctly is no answer that's
right in fact verse and indeed um a very
old language called icon um did the same
thing inverse there are no booleans
instead you say if you say if e then you
know then Branch else else Branch then
the semantics is if we evaluate e and e
fails we take the else
Branch right if there's no possible
answer to e yes exactly yeah so that
that's in just just like I say in
Haskell if you call the look up and then
you can patent match on the result and
if it's nothing you do this if it's just
X you do that and inverse you can just
say if the thing fails take this Bunch
otherwise take that Bunch so failure is
not it's not bad anyway so um so in this
functional logic programming Paradigm
you got um deeply wired into the very
fabric of computation is the idea that a
computation May Fail return zero results
um and in fact um inv verse it can also
return many results so that's a the the
another crucial component of functional
logic programming is
Choice um so the expression one vertical
bar
two returns one and then two right so an
expression can yield zero results we
call that failure one result or maybe
two results or maybe seven results um so
this sort of uh multiplicity of results
is part of the core computation model of
ver so as you can see it's very
different to to ordinary functional
programming yeah I I know someone is
listening to this is going to be
thinking this so I have to ask it in
what way is this not
just processing
lists
list it is it is a bit like making um
you know has Call's list monan out into
the fundamental monad of the
language um but um and you could
simulate verse by uh it wouldn't just be
a list monad it would be a logic team
monad for anybody who wants to go and
look up the logic T library or something
a bit like that because remember we got
to do all this unification as well yeah
that's the big difference so
um so a functional well well so one
possibility would be to say well why
don't we just do all this as a library
well the answer is it would be it would
be possible but inconvenient right
programs would look cluttered um yeah
another way to ask the question is what
is the core
computational Paradigm of this
functional logic thing right could we as
we were saying is we can distill hascal
down into Lambda calculus what would we
distill verse
into and this has been your your job
recently right that is my job recently
that's right so so if we're going to do
this functional logic programming thing
we better know what are you know uh what
the the absolutely essential irreducible
essence of functional logic programming
is if we're if we're going to undertake
this endeavor at all um and we are um so
indeed we spent the last um couple of
years
um identifying uh what we've called the
verse calculus um there was a paper at
um icfp last year about it um which
indeed describes a little calculus it's
it's bigger than the Lambda calculus
quite quite a bit bigger actually Lambda
calculus remember it's cor only has you
know variables applications and lambdas
that's incredibly sparse right verse has
about you know eight so the the verse
calculus has about eight constructs or
something it's a bit bigger um but we've
also found a very nice way to then give
it semantics in a similar style that we
give the semantics of the Lambda
calculus how do we say what a Lambda
calculus program means we give it
rewrite rules in particular beta
reduction um so in the verse calculus we
give it we write rules
two you I think you need to define beta
reduction for those that don't know yes
so um so it's a bit difficult to do this
without uh whiteboard but what is what
is a what is a um the
own in when Alonzo church first defined
the lamb calculus he defined this
incredibly tiny calculus which is um
just variables applications and lambdas
and the only the only rewrite rule is if
you have a Lambda applied to an argument
think about a function applied to an
argument then what do you do you take
the body of the of the function and you
replace the call with the body having
replace the bound variable with the
actual argument so you sort of rewriting
the function to be you're rewriting the
function call yeah to have a copy of the
function
body yeah so if I have um I don't know
if I say um one bat of X is x^2 + 1 then
if I see one bat of three I can replace
that with 3^2 + 1 if I see one bat of 77
I replace that with 77 s + 1 yeah right
so each call is replaced by a copy of
the body um with the actual argument
substituted for the formal
parameter that is beta reduction that
step of replacing the call by the copy
of the body after substituting that's
beta right and astonishingly that single
thing is enough to define a
computationally complete language that
is a you know a a uh it's enough to
Define any any computation whatsoever in
the you know in the two in complete
sense it's amazing that that one rule is
enough that that's punching massively
above its weight it is amazing right
it's you know just gobsmackingly
brilliant that Alonzo church right back
in the you know late 1920s early 1930s
was defining this calculus with with a
single
rule Define something that was as
expressive as a toing machine you know
they're into expressive it's not too
surprising that we figured out how
useful that was from touring side
building machines
upwards but yeah but it's interesting
that now time has rolled on and we've
realized that you can go from the maths
down to get it to exactly the same place
yeah that's right I mean they realized
they were inter um you know they were
each as expressive as the other they
realized that very early on um but the
thing about touring machines Is that
real machines you know actual you know
what what whatever it is you know x86
processors they look much more like
touring machines yeah in which the
memory is the tape that is mutated by
the processor that is like the head of
the touring machine so it's quite a
close connection between um the touring
Machine model of computation and what
really happens in our microprocesses
yeah yeah and the the sort of functional
programming stuff has taken a bit longer
to say well it's equally expressive but
if we build a good compiler we can map
it onto the same x86 processor yeah and
that is the that actually is the step we
were discussing earlier when we go from
Lambda calculus down to lrvm or C minus
minus yeah okay so going back to this
core which I really want to explore more
boiling
down we've got to go high level in a
second but boiling down this uh
functional logic programming language
into verse core you've called it you've
ended up with a batch of uh you say
eight rules oh no that we have I think I
forget the exact number do we have
alas rather more than eight rules
there's more like 20 or so I think I can
look at the paper but the I was meaning
the the number of syntactic
constructs calculus only three or four
we have more like sort of eight or 10 I
think in the verse calculus okay but
this core I mean does it the thing one
thing I want to know is can you look at
the two different cores and get a sense
of what the final language is going to
feel like to work with I does does it
have is there functional logic Zen the
fun the Tower of it buried in this core
language oh there is I mean I think I
think
it's a core calculus is the sort of the
essence of what computation means in
that Paradigm incidentally the Lambda
calculus is a subset of the verse
calculus yeah oh is it yeah so every
Lambda term is a verse calculus term um
so it's just that verse calculus has you
know a bit more that doesn't make it
computationally more powerful but we
know that the Lambda calculus is
computationally complete but it but it
has these additional you know functional
logic features built into its
infrastructure and rewrite rules to
support them um but indeed I think when
you stare at the rewrite rules if you
look at the you look at the paper you'll
get uh you will you will get you know
some sense of you won't get a sense of
what it's like to write um you know
programs in inversed in the large but I
think you'll get a sense of what what um
uh what computation means and what what
you can say in this little little
language
and what we're saying is I get the sense
is a version of programming
where that there's so imperative
languages you define what needs to be
done functional languages you define
what is it feels like the verse you're
going to be
defining the shape of things as best you
know them now and gradually building up
a picture of the constraints around the
answer yeah that's a bit like that and
in some ways that's an even higher level
right we we so that functional in
functional program we say it's
declarative what do we mean by
declarative programming like it's what
you were saying what is rather than um
you know how to compute it so you know
crudely you might say imperative
programming say how and in functional
programming say what and we've you know
rather sloppily said well that must be
better
right but but um uh but in a functional
logic language you're even higher level
rather than saying um how can I give an
example if I say um uh find me the X
such that x s is is um
22 then I'm asking you to find the
square root of x right so that's a very
high level thing right it's not a square
root algorithm it's completely
non-constructive right it simply tells
you a property of the number you want
yeah right but it's very
expressive that's good right and and you
you can see immediately what it does if
I showed you a square root algorithm it
would be hard to figure out what it does
if I just say my spec is uh you know the
X such that X squ is um uh 22 then you
say ah now I know what you're doing
right so this kind of um tell me the
properties of the
result way of describing what you want a
computer to do because after all that's
what programming is describe the
properties of the result is a
rather highlevel way to tell your
computer what to
do right as we've seen from this x squ
thing now um inverse you can say um
exists X x^2 = 22 and try to run that
but it will get
stuck right it's not it's not an illegal
program but it but it's one that um it's
one that we can't
um uh we can't we're not going to
succeed in executing right because the
the property we've asked it to figure
out out is too hard we've asked it to
guess a square root algorithm right yeah
yeah but if I say um uh uh an X and Y
and Zed such that X is the pair y z and
um and the first component of X is three
and the second component of X is four
then I've given you enough information
very straightforwardly to solve those
equations and say ah why must be three
Zed must be four and X must be the pair
three four yeah right so the um uh so so
versus if if you like um a bit on a
higher level in in this sort of
Continuum of expressiveness than purely
functional programming but not as high
level as oh I can just ask you to do you
know solve um arit Tre
polinomial yeah or Sol format's Last
Problem yeah there is a danger that
we're going to ask it to um solve the MP
complete problem for us
right
can
you give it sales problem as the spec
and expect the answers you just
magically pop out and that's not going
to happen yeah they L apart exactly yeah
so what is what is from um a questions
this can answer conveniently point of
view what is functional logic
programming good for ah yes so that's
that's a good question right so so then
the the um uh uh we got imperative
programming we've got functional
programm got functional logic
programming I've always thought that you
know since I was 20 I've thought well
functional programming is just the right
way to write programs right
um and um it was very inspiring when
John bachus when he got the touring
award gave this lecture called can
programming be liberated from the Von
Norman style in which he was essentially
saying he a famous person was saying
look I have no truck with these
imperative languages just go gangbusters
on functional programming because it's a
better way to do the job right in the T
TK of telling a computer what you wanted
to do functional programming is just
better um that is to say you're less lik
to make mistakes um you're You' be more
productive and um uh maybe our programs
be who knows depends how hard we work on
a compiler maybe our maybe our programs
will run a little slower but maybe not
much um and maybe they'll be highly
parallel who knows so but it's just a
better way to do the job now um
functional logic programming maybe
that's a better way to write programs
right maybe it's just um so I've argued
that it's more expressive that to say
it's more expressive and a higher level
it doesn't necessarily mean that it's a
better programming medium because it
might be extremely obscure for example
or hard to understand programs for some
reason yeah so I think that the um um
Tim Sweeney my boss and the founder and
chief executive of um um um epic epic
games um yeah firmly believes that
functional logic programming is just the
right way to write programs in the same
way that I firmly believed you know age
20 uh that functional programing was
just the right way to do things um and
I've you know placed my bets on that and
Tim is putting his money on functional
logic programming at the moment I think
there's a um uh I think that's a uh the
good thing about that is it means that
verse takes a view right it is
expressing a a a strongly held and well
worked out view of what programming
should be like um so that's quite
exciting for me as a programming
language researcher um is it do we know
that it's going to be a better way to
write programs even supposing programs
run fast enough and so forth um is it
better way to write programs um I don't
know it could be but I think we'll get a
lot of the only way we'll really find
out is by trying it and that's what
we're doing yeah so uh so Tim is
convinced I'm um uh I think there's a uh
a extremely interesting you know
experiment to be done here um and I'm
prepared to be convinced um but I'm not
yet in the this is just definitely so
much better Camp yeah well that's fair
cuz um you are on the spectrum of um
language researcher to marketing person
you're way over the first end of the
spectrum right oh indeed yes yes that's
right I'm you know my principal goal in
all of this is sort of it's an
intellectual Adventure yeah but of
course the intellectual Adventures are
dramatically informed by practical usage
I'm strongly motivated by the fact that
hundreds of thousands of people using
use hll and I'm strongly motived by the
fact that motivated by the fact that
verse um because it's going to be the
programming language in which you um
enter the you know epics meta fortnite
world and um meterse uh there's a a kind
of captive audience there yeah right of
actually hundreds of millions of people
who will start using verse um and that's
very motivating too because I want it to
be a language that is you know just
works for them and is um uh and is you
know smooth and uh and it you know it's
just sort of obvious what it does
uh whether we'll whether we'll succeed
in doing all of those things we'll have
to see but that's that's the aspiration
and we do have a big user base um yeah
it's it's reminding me of objective c
when Apple decided that you had to write
Objective C to use iOS it's like an
entire world of
programmers just popped up having to
find out how useful and interesting this
was and we're going to see the same with
verse and Unreal Engine I
ECT I think so I mean you can at the
moment you can program with unreal using
C++ um that has its own barrier to entry
um and you can also use a lang a visual
language called
blueprints um which is uh you know it's
a visual language in the sense that you
draw boxes and arrows between them and
the arrows can be data flow arcs or they
can be control flow dependencies yeah
but of course there's a there's somewhat
a limit about about what sort of
programs you can write in blue
blueprints so then you have to descend
to C++ and versus sort of filling the
Gap in the middle because there's
enormous numbers of users I mean you've
got 300 million people are you know
floating about in the um the sort of
fortnite
universe only a very very tiny minority
of those
will um bite the C++ bullet yeah but we
hope that a lot more of them will find
verse a happy place to play yeah I can
imagine a lot of people getting started
with a visual language hitting the limit
but not quite wanting to LEAP up the
mountain to C++ yeah okay so let me let
me um ask this not asking you to bet on
the marketing side but here you
are uh an experienced language
researcher being told okay we've got
this language verse it's a functional
logic language we would like you to boil
this down something semantically
rigorous what's it like to retrofit
semantics to an exist
language oh well it's quite entertaining
actually but and it's entertaining
because um Tim who is the progenitor of
verse right the the unique single
progenitor of verse um he is
fundamentally a geek right he CES cares
primarily about um Beauty and elegance
and you know uh a deep connection to
mathematical logic and just doing it
right um he has incidentally a inly
built a very successful company right so
he's also a very good businessman yeah
but I would say that his sort of you
know genetic core is let's do this right
so um and he has been designing verse in
his head for the last two decades oh
really that just that he's been also yes
a long time long time it's also he's
been busy making epic successful as well
so it's been a kind of you know uh
evenings and weekends activity for him
for ages and
ages uh and so
um so my job is as it were to uh to
figure out what verse is you know what
this thing in his head is and it's full
of interesting and original ideas um and
then try to make sense of it all now uh
supposing we discovered it just doesn't
make sense well we we haven't discovered
that yet but I'm I'm uh
I I firmly believe that if we could
persuade Tim that something really
didn't make sense he would say oh Japs
we can't possibly do
that you must have found that as you
dive right into the very gut of it you
find that actually this piece doesn't
fit with this piece unless we amend the
language then there must be
inconsistencies that you only discover
when you're trying to formalize
something well we are formalizing from
the the bottom up so you know we sort of
starting with the you know the core
calculus that's what this um uh this
paper is about um but um Tim has been
thinking about this long a long time so
the the the um uh the whole thing the
whole enchilada including uh its type
system and verification and
transactional memory and side effects um
and uh classes and inheritance and so
forth and backward compatibility the
whole thing is Jolly complicated yeah um
so um
I guess what I mean is once you
formalize this calculus and you start
building up that Tower are you going to
find you end up with something that kind
of that doesn't quite look exactly like
verse you going to say okay there's a
new release of verse and we've got to
change the semantics because I don't
know so so far we haven't okay so far we
haven't G across any ins superable
obstacles as it were which I think is
also also Testament to um Tim's sort of
single single-mindedness um I'm reminded
incidentally of rust here um uh rust was
a language that was um designed with you
know strong attention to sharing and
borrowing and linearity and so forth um
and but it was designed it was very much
didn't come out of a university and a
sort of pointy-headed academic it came
out came out of a sort of a desire to to
do good practice so I was pretty sure
that when somebody came to do the theory
behind rust right they would find all
sorts of holes in the type
system right maybe not ones that uh
occurred in practice very much but just
that there would be you know uh uh holes
in which which would allow you to write
programs in Rust that simply weren't
correct you know that were disobeyed
rust's um what guarantees astonishingly
that turned out not to be the case Derek
Dreer and his colleagues have done a lot
of stuff on the foundations um of rust
and actually didn't find any major uh
you know theoretical inconsistencies um
that's amazing that means that the
original designers uh had incredibly you
know good intellectual not just taste
but they actually got it right it's an
amazing thing which is Jolly complicated
this business about linearity and
sharing very difficult to get right um
it's it's a remarkable achievement I
think do you have any theories on why
that might be do you think it's just
lightning struck they're just very
hardworking and clever or do you think
there's something about comp computers
keeping us honest uh no I think they
probably just well I computers do keep
you honest but there's an awful lot of
potential programs possible programs
that you could write um and many of them
you know might have uh you know
linearity flaws in them that were not
really apparent or don't show up even
when you run it so so no I don't think
it I I think it's just they're extremely
clever and had very very well educated
intuitions that they sort of developed
over
time and so you must be claiming
something similar for ver if you're
going to formalize these things and
finding their what I'm saying so so far
as I say Tim's Tim's intuitions have
proved remarkably uh you know one might
disagree about matters of taste right so
is it worth having this this piece of
complexity in order to allow that kind
of expressiveness you know you can make
choices about that but what we haven't
found is the thing is just a mess and
doesn't hold together at all is just
inconsistent in some way right yeah so
and I think that is Testament as I say
to his single-mindedness and his sort of
technical intuition okay well in that
case let's talk about climbing this
ladder a bit more because um I I
absolutely don't want to sit a test on
this but I have read the verse Core
paper and enjoyed it and you hint that
you're going to be climbing up into
formalizing side effects and types yeah
how's that work going oh well so um
let's talk about types because that's
really the the next big thing
so uh um so versus typee system is very
unusual so usually like in language like
has school you have the world of terms
and then separately have the world of
types um and types are you know a
somewhat special language in particular
you can statically reason about types so
the type Checker can say this program is
well typed this program is not well
typed now in verse uh a type is more
like a contract in
scheme so a type is actually just a
function a function inverse actually um
and it's a function which uh either
fails in the sense we've been discussing
given an argument it either fails or
let's say for now or it's the identity
function so the int type is just the
function that takes a value tests
whether it's an INT and if it is it
returns it and if it isn't it
fails make sense right yeah yeah so it's
almost like a filter if you like um yeah
just but it but it fails if it isn't the
type so um let's see the type int comma
int the type of pairs of ins is a
function that takes an argument um
checks that uh it is a pair if not it
fails then applies int to the first
component and applies int to the second
component remember apply to means check
that it has that type because int is a
function
so so the pair int comma int is also a
function is also a type which which does
this
thing so any so um uh you can Define the
type say of pairs in which the second
component is bigger than the
first oh that's an unusual type that is
it's just a function that takes an
argument I you could write this function
inverse right just a just a function
takes an argument checks if it's a pair
if it is a pair check the first
component is an in
check that the second component is in it
and then check that the first component
is bigger than the
second and fail if
not so it becomes very much that there's
a unification there
between Type statements saying we
constrain these values to these
rules and logic functional logic
programming in general saying we
constrain these values to these
rules there's there's less separation
between those worlds yeah maybe but I I
think it's I think in the typ connection
I think is that uh a type is just a
partial function partial in the sense
that it can fail so do remember we said
failure is deeply built into the fabric
and we could make that you know done by
some kind of list monad but then it'd be
much more Awkward to say and types do
this so so here um that's what a that's
what a type does but now since a type is
just um you know since I can write new
type new types are just new functions
that I write as a
user right so I don't write have a
different language for defining new
types new types are simply ordinary old
verse function definitions but that
means that the type
Checker has to
understand well these ordinary old verse
function definitions you've just
written so the type Checker has to be to
run verse programs
exactly the type Checker has to be able
to run verse program s yes and of course
you might write something that is
extremely hard to check right so um
uh it would not be difficult to write a
program with a a contract you know or
type that was sufficiently complicated
that it was hard to be sure that the
first argument was going to be bigger
than the
second right yeah like uh I don't know
um uh say you had a type that was true
only of positive numbers and you said is
x squ in that
type well yes it is because we know that
um if I mean if x is an INT we know that
squares are always positive yeah but
that's a property of numbers right so
maybe the verify knows about that
property of
numbers but you can cook up some more
difficult property of
numbers the the the so you can see You'd
rapidly get into arbitrary theorem
proving yeah yeah right so instead of
calling it type checking we call it
verification okay and the idea is still
going to be that just as the the
purposes of type Checker is to say it
eliminates certain classes of bug so the
slogan is well typed programs don't go
wrong where going wrong means some
particular class of Errors like adding
an integer to a booon right hascal means
you can't that could never happen at
runtime right yeah so if you imagine a
runtime which manipulated integers and
booleans are sort of tagged values so
you could tell them apart at runtime and
then your addition operation did a
runtime
test you would know that that runtime
test would never fail yeah right and
therefore you can emit all those
one-time tests and indeed the tags that
distinguish integers from booleans right
yeah good now in ver verse is going to
be like that in the sense that um
verified prrams don't go
wrong right so if the verifier says
thumbs up your program is verified then
a certain class of Errors cannot occur
and the implementation could be
corresponding more efficient but it's
possible that the verifier might say I'm
sorry I can't prove that your program
verifies because it requires me knowing
say that u x squ is always positive and
I haven't been taught that yet so over
time I expect the verse verifier to get
more powerful more smarter right yeah as
it's taught rules for more and more
complex time exactly but there won't be
unlike hascal there won't be a clean
bright line between programs that can be
verified and programs that
can't yes right because it'll be a
function of just how smart has the
verifier become on any one day we might
hope to characterize as precisely as
possible where that boundary lies but it
is a boundary that will move over time
do you think that verifier will ever be
user
manipulatable in that you will write
more rules for the verifier again in oh
possibly um yes I mean you want to be a
bit careful because if the user adds a
rule that is simply false then you know
the program might crash yeah and it
might crash in a truly horrible way
right so um like it might just simply be
a seg fold um yeah so you'd want to be a
bit careful about allowing you but but
if you um uh if you essentially add some
you know some new things to the verifier
that says make this part of the trusted
code base if this is wrong all bets are
off then that's a POS imaginable
possibility yeah yeah okay do you think
I mean I'm thinking verse if if the
verifier is just more verse functions
yeah this leads into side effects I
could in theory Define a type which was
the the type of all strings which are a
valid username in my database yes that's
right that might very have time or space
and who knows so so I think for us types
are going to be pure functions yeah so
now we need an effect system right to
ensure that to um so that we can check
that um uh types are pure functions and
indeed verse has an effect system
[Laughter]
too so you can see why it gets
complicated yeah yeah where are you on
um formalizing the effect system and are
you taking a similar approach to hasc
not similar approach to H because um has
uses these monad things right we don't
want to you get selled up with monads
and types um so uh and
because um yes from a programmer
convenience point of
view just being able to say relying on
sort of left to right sequencing for
side effects is extremely convenient um
so uh and language is broadly classified
to language like that force you to do
you know do use use monads for anything
side Effy and that's a bit of a hair
shirt but um it's an excellent
discipline in my humble opinion but but
it's a it's a design choice and other
possible design choices like verse to um
uh to make a not to make such a strong
syntactic and type level distinction
between side effect and computations and
and not ones but instead have an effect
system that says that the verifier will
for any for any term it's going to be
able to um check whether it's pure and
you can see fundamentally you know
crudely put that's not very hard right
is this expression pure well does it use
any side effects
directly and does it cause any call any
functions that can use side effects yeah
right so at its crudest level you can
see there must be some kind of Purity
Checker that isn't very
hard yes right but to do a systematic
job of an effective system is indeed um
quite a challenge and that's part of
what we're up to at the moment yes
um I should say by the way um that Tim
has an implementation of all of this um
embedded in you know his his C++
implementation the vers he's written in
C++ a compiler he's been developing over
the last 20 years and it's it's only
five or 10,000 lines of C++ it's
incredibly small he is a virtuoso C++
going um but uh um but I think he would
be the first to admit that it's um you
know it makes an amazingly good stab at
all of this but it is not uh you know uh
tight and elegant and complete and
definitely right um in every particular
so it's an excellent stab and it means
that we have it's it's a way that he has
been using to educate his intuitions to
go back to your questions about
computers keeping you honest I think
building that has indeed educated his
feedback
throughout right but where as it were
we're not building directly on that
we're trying to use that as a source of
inspiration to do this more foundational
thing that we're talking about yeah and
that presumably is going to occupy you
for a good few years to come um I think
so though in some the the the um the
scary bit is that we are designing the
airplane at the same moment as we're
launching it into the
sky right
because there is a there is a verse that
has been released as a product if you
just you know Google for verse language
you know epic you'll rapidly get to it
yeah it is a um it doesn't have any of
this functional logic stuff in it but it
does have other things like classes
inheritance and modules um so it's a so
it's a language that um uh is already
usable for building you know games and
um creative stuff in the sort of
fortnite Universe um and programming
gets unreal so it's already being Us by
thousands of people so we're doing this
foundational thing on the side and then
so we sort of launched one to mix
metaphors we launched one rocket you
know into orbit and now we're you know
building some more elaborate and
sophisticated thing we're going to
launch into orbit then they're going to
join up in the sky and
hopefully we we will um so so the scary
bit is we need to do that quickly enough
um that you we can't go on for years and
years and years doing this foundational
stuff because um you know the the the
airplanes flying in the sky we want to
we want to meet up sooner you know
within a year or two rather than in 10
years so right yes I think working out
all these technical details and writing
papers about them will occupy us for
several years um but there is a pretty
big urgency at the same time that I
personally find a bit
scary I can understand that and do you
one last question then do you think
that do you think that these ideas will
be pinned particularly to verse or they
juicy things that other language
designers can pull out of this and steal
oh well um I mean the one of the whole
purposes of writing the paper is to
distill the essence right so of course
any particular language implementation
will be
encrusted with particulars right hascal
is no exception by the way it's an
enormous language and with a lot of
detail to it and you need to get to know
it's ecosystem and cabal and stack and
um hls and on and on right so and vers
will similarly be encrusted with lots of
stuff but if we want to um you know the
purposes of of the purpose
of uh sort of the research um Enterprise
is to isolate the key ideas and distill
them into a form that they can be
digested by other other language
designers and academics right right and
so indeed it is my goal um that um our
you know our first paper and hopefully
subsequent papers about um verse and the
verse calculus will be influential well
you know will be much more than just
saying well this is how verse works
right will but they will rather embody
and and make precise a collection of
ideas that may you know I hope who knows
um have be influential in their own
right yeah yeah as a language research
your um your goal is to make the ideas
bigger than any one language Oh indeed
yeah indeed I often when when talking to
um research students about writing
papers I often say that you know that
the the the the uh the least durable
thing that we do is to build artifacts
you know like compilers in my case um
the most durable thing we do is write
papers right because those papers will
be um you know in in the best case will
be uh read and will inform stuff uh
decades later when you know when the the
particular language implementation is
dust I mean just look at the fact that
we're still you know Alonzo Church's
ideas we are talking about in the
podcast today which is you know a
hundred years since he was first
thinking about them that's amazing yeah
yeah when we go to a concert hall we
listen to people reading Mozart's papers
he called them Symphonies but they are
you know his you know intellectually
written down stuff and uh symphony
orchestras read them of course there's a
great deal of expressiveness and Nuance
of what they do but the fact is that
mozar infected our brains with an idea
that we still find rewarding um yeah and
I think the the um you know the purpose
of uh uh research papers in some ways is
is to infect the brain of the reader
with a an idea that is so persuasive and
seductive and exciting and creative and
interesting that they can then use it to
inspire and build on new things that's
the that's that's that's my hope yeah
yeah we had um we had a guest a couple
of weeks ago who was um hoping to build
a version of that would last 100
years but I and I I I um I certainly
hope he succeeds but what I can
definitely see as some of the ideas
you've been percolating up still being
discussed a 100 years from now and
inspiring new languages yeah I think
it's I think yes languages are surpr can
programming languages actually are an
example of something that can be
surprisingly long lived like Cobalt is
still alive and well yeah but not in a
good way um I think right so um
you know it's not it's not Cobalt is no
longer a source of inspiring ideas just
that we have so much code written in it
we have to still you know run those
compilers um yeah so I suspect that if
um you know hcol is still around in 100
years it would be not in a good way
right whereas I hope the ideas might be
you know visibly embodied in some more
wonderful thing that we have worked out
by then yeah yeah you'd hope that the
ideas there are fundamental enough that
they'll outlive the programs and us
right which actually leads me to the
other Big Arm of your work which is
passing the Big Ideas On to the Next
Generation tell me about that yeah um
Computing education super important and
a bit and we I think we as a you know as
a what's the word as a professional
Community um we owe it to not to our
discipline in particular to our children
to be thoughtful
about what are you know what should our
children be learning about our
discipline um and um in a in a way that
would make them you know empowered
citizens and uh ones who think it's just
the most exciting thing since life bread
which it is um and let's not put up with
uh an education that sort of substandard
in that respect which is
um so so I think it's there's an
Endeavor that we should all be involved
in in some way where would you go with
that because I'm thinking of my own
children's Computer Science Education
it's a bit of python a bit of squeak and
too much Excel and
PowerPoint yes well it's probably a bit
better than it was right so um when we
started Computing at school C the um
organization that is is sort of behind a
lot of changes in the curriculum um the
the national curriculum said you should
do ICT information and communication
technology it was very technology
focused um and that is it was all about
artifacts and not about ideas to go back
to that conversation right um and uh and
it was often no more than learn
PowerPoint and Excel Excel if you were
lucky B would so then um over the the
next sort of five to eight years
following about 2007 we managed to um re
reposition the UK's National curriculum
to State
explicitly that children should all
children should learn the fundamentals
of computer science in the same way that
they learn the fundamentals of natural
science so that
reimagines computer science not as a
narrow sort of rather vocational
operational skill that's useful for
operating computers but rather as a
foundational discipline like maths or
like physics um that an elementary
understanding of which is kind of
essential for understanding the natural
world that surrounds you and being a
citizen in it who can you know have some
agency right some ability to influence
events some understanding of what's
going on ability to make informed
choices and to make well judged you know
well judged decisions do you think
there's a parallel I mean one of the big
reasons we teach children science is not
so they can use a buns and burner but so
they can think critically yeah and but
it's not just it it's a bit more than
just think critically they also need a
knowledge
base if you knew nothing about heat
combustion mass mass velocity nothing
about any of that but you were very good
at critical thinking right it's just
your you know your logical processes
were good but you had no knowledge that
wouldn't wouldn't be any good
right you need to have an elementary you
know understanding of how to think
logically yes the scientific method all
that but you also need to know some
science
facts otherwise how can you possibly
make informed choices about I don't know
global warming or about whether it's
safe to replace the you know to unscrew
the the front of your electric light
switch Yeah so um in the same way I
think for um I I think the sort of
critical thinking and you know logical
thinking absolutely part of computer
science indeed computers are rather good
at training you um to think logically
because they they are so
non-judgmentally but absolutely brutally
cruel about exposing flaws in your logic
that program just doesn't work um and it
doesn't say oh I feel sorry for you
today I'll make it
work which is good when it's controlling
the plane that's about to land you yes
um so um but so I think just as you need
to I think all children should learn
some some Elementary aspects of Natural
Science I think they should learn
Elementary aspects of computer science
so that they're in a position they have
enough knowledge base as well as um
logical thinking and skills to make
well-informed choices about um the
digital world that surrounds them so
pressingly and
intimately and practically for you is
that influencing the curriculum at the
national level yeah absolutely it is I
mean as I say it's completely
transformed before it said you should
learn about digital technology now it
says all children should learn the
fundamental principles of computer
science which is a huge challenge for
schools if you're a primary teacher you
might you might think computer sign I
mean at the time it was put in the
National curriculum you know we were not
long past the time when people thought
well computer science that's just a
university course isn't it yeah and then
suddenly we say oh no primary school
children should have some Elementary
understanding in the same way that have
you know their understanding of physics
is not very deep or biology right but
they but a primary school teacher sees
themselves as you know part of their
task is to give an elementary
understanding of Natural Science and so
so it's a big challenge there because um
we uh uh it's easy enough to say uh
children should get an elementary
understanding of the principles of
computer science and should have
practical experience of writing programs
um because that's that's like the lab
work of the subject if you like it's
yeah programming is to computer science
as lab work is to physics you know it's
really important um yeah it's easy
enough to say that but to turn it into a
practical reality you've got to say well
okay so specifically what should
children learn at primary school and how
should they learn it in what order
should they learn the concept cepts um
and and all and then you know even once
you got that all laid out you got then
got to say and how can we train teachers
to be good at doing that right um same
at Secondary School seems like one of
the hardest tasks yeah so so it is so
the you know that ever since 200 this
became part of the national curriculum
which was in
2014 um Computing at school this sort of
G gorilla um movement in in partnership
with the BCS the professional Society
for computing this country um the
British computer Society Charter
Institute for it been we've been working
together to answer all of those
questions um and the
government uh having changed the
curriculum then waited five years but
eventually they did hoay um uh find some
money actual money to build something
called the national Center for computing
education which is a national teacher
professional development organization
aimed at upskilling teachers and
generating the teaching resources and
materials and curriculum sort of
sequencing um that we were discussing so
that's amazing that was that started in
2018 I became its first chair oh wow
it's all it's all and it's on its second
iteration now and I hope that there will
be a
third impressive quite a lot has taken
place in this country which is not to
say job done and not at all to say job
done because um it's a big job right to
um we are far from the the the place in
which every child gets a great Computing
education yeah but circling back to why
the audience for this podcast might I
would like to say might be interested
but and I and I would I would like to
say should be interested is that I think
this task the one that I've just
described about saying what should we
teach exactly you know when and how um
and with what materials um all of that
is too important um to and too just to
leave to school teachers to make up for
themselves or even from some even if
government funded guango like the
national Center of Community Education I
think we as a technical community should
be involved as individuals and our
companies should be kind of
institutionally involved in trying to
make Computing education into just great
across the whole country in every
classroom okay so I would understand if
I want
to if I want to move verse forward in
some way I would go and download it
write some code in it or download the
paper and try implementing it yeah how
do I I have no idea how I would get
involved in moving the
education of children in Computing
forward in the way you're describing how
would someone get started in that
project yeah um so the uh uh I can give
you the first step is join Cass right um
Computing at school um K it's
many of the members of Kaza teachers but
um there's also you know a third to a
half our it Professionals of one kind
okay and then there are various sort of
thematic interest groups there's one on
AI and there's one on primary that you
could um join um and
um uh so joining CM go to the C National
Conference just becoming better informed
about it there probably a um a cast
local community a sort of physical
getting together of teachers in your
area so going to one of those would mean
you face to face met with some actual
live teachers who are grappling with
this stuff because for me it's it's not
so much about um doing some grand
national scale thing I think what we as
individuals and even companies did to do
is just get stuck in locally that means
that means meeting teachers and not
saying no I'm going to tell you what to
do but getting along that alongside them
and saying and see you've got a you know
a a a um a exciting but challenging job
here right how could I help you yeah is
there any way in which I could be
helpful and there is a way in which I
can help without necessarily being in a
room of 30 children yeah for example you
could be a um there's a uh you might be
a mentor to a teacher or possibly
sometimes a mentor to a child
particularly at the latest stages like a
sixth form yeah yeah so C has a number
of ways for um professional to get
involved in in this kind of thing I wish
I could be I I wish it was oh you can
become a stem Ambassador what are stem
ambassadors so that's um uh you can just
Google for stem Ambassador but basically
means someone who's sort of on a you
know a national register of people who
are willing to help in some way and
schools will when they looking for
speakers will often look for stem
ambassadors and also when you're a stem
Ambassador they will also do all the um
crb checks that mean that you are uh you
know all the legal obligations are done
so you can you can go to a school right
in person
yeah they have restrictions on that
quite sensibly exactly yes so and all
that is kind of done by being a um by
becoming a St Ambassador so um it's it's
it's really hard to give you a crisp
answer for how to get involved because
education is complicated and schools are
different um but you you're you're
saying you've got children and they're
at a particular School you could do
worse than find who is who is the head
of computing in the school say could I
come and talk to you about what you're
doing and you know can we can we talk
about you know is there any way in which
I or perap perhaps by recruiting
others to the task could be helpful and
it might be anything from well just come
and give a talk about um what what you
do in your life yeah because many
children think that um Computing is all
about um uh you know spotty youths in in
windowless basements staring at glowing
screens right but actually it's a rich
diverse um creative discipline which
people do lots of different things and
you um your your you know uh um role as
a podcaster is very different to um the
you know the spotty person in a bundus
room writing weird weird Cod right
you're a professional Communicator right
so the Computing is a very diverse
profession um uh so that's one one thing
that a teacher could find helpful right
because they want to give their if they
say to their children look it's an
interesting and diverse profession that
go yeah yeah yeah right but when a
person
comes and can speak in a you know
persuasive and articulate way about the
richness of the subject and all the
things you could do that's much more
compelling yeah yeah yeah okay um final
question because this is an
international podcast is um are there do
you know if there are equivalent um
organizations in say America oh yeah
definitely all around the world so um so
just to say Cass is UK trick but you can
definitely join Cass from anywhere right
so I have quite a few International
members so that's and that just means
you have access to you know you can talk
to other members of the community it's
we call cast a community of practice
right it's but think of it like here's
here's a good model it's like an open
source project right so right if you if
you uh I don't know subscribe to The
Economist you pay them a subscription in
exchange for a
service if you join the GHC open source
project you don't pay anything you bring
the contributions that you have um which
you give for free and in exchange you
get the um you know richness of the
community they there you get to you know
get all of the free stuff that that
group of people has produced right so
it's not it's the one is a transactional
exchange the other is more a um shared
Community Grassroots bottomup um gift
economy yes C is the gift economy model
right very much it's not a subscription
you pay to get a service you just become
part of a community um and then and of
course that means you make of it uh what
you can um so going back to your
International question so so people
abroad who can um uh you know can still
join Cass and and anywhere there will be
a local version and well probably you if
you're in particular country and you
need help finding out who then I can
probably help you because I've talked to
people in lots of different countries at
various times but in the America there's
something called the computer science
Teachers Association um csta which is a
sort of equivalent of Cass a little bit
more teacher Centric than than casses
but um sort of equivalent of Cass in the
USA uh and I think in every country
there would be this activists who are
busy trying to do exactly what C is
trying to do here cool okay I'll put
links to all of that in the show notes
and hopefully some listeners will get
involved yeah that would be great I mean
I think it I do think it's a it's
exciting and rewarding because everybody
cares about education
right you could can't find a person on
the planet who says well education who
cares just doesn't matter right well
maybe there are a few but not many right
so um and also for everybody listening
to this podcast you probably think um
you know computer science programming
this whole world this is just the most
exciting thing that's why I've devoted
my professional life to
it happily it's well paid as well right
so yeah so I just want to share that oh
and you also have a strong idea of the
you know the richness and depth and
excitement of the discipline I want to
share that with our young people so they
don't get the wrong idea and so that
they do have plenty of input and
opportunities to you know find good
on-ramps into Computing as a you know so
so that all of them end up well informed
able to make good judgments and some of
them end up um particularly
underrepresented groups like women uh
find it you know find a a pathway into
Computing as a discipline because I
think we need lots of people there and
the better informed the better yeah
absolutely and we need to help we need
to help we can't just leave it to the
education system to do they they've got
the message they're trying hard but
they're Educators right they they need
the subject they need subject expertise
and that's us that's us yeah
good okay ideas and education a perfect
note to end on yeah great Simon pton
Jones thank you very much for talking to
us it's been a lot of fun thank you
right Simon thank you very much if you
want to get involved in Cass in the UK
or csta over in the state there are
links to those organizations in the show
notes and if you're not in those
countries but you know of a similar
organization in your country please drop
me a line I'll gladly add the links for
wherever we can uh how do you drop me a
line you look in the show notes my
contact details you can find me on
Twitter LinkedIn masteron you can leave
a comment if you're on YouTube you can
leave a like if you're on YouTube rating
if you're on one of the audio ones you
can subscribe and rejoin us next week or
you can share with a friend and share
the love and
knowledge um what else is there to say I
have started scratching out an evaluator
for functional logic programming in Pur
script of all things I make no claims
about how far I get but it's good brain
food and I've been enjoying it so if you
want to do something similar you'll find
a link to Simon's paper that explains it
pretty well for an academic paper well
from an academic paper in the show notes
and that should give you plenty of brain
food and if you want it plenty of
homework until next week I've been your
host Chris Jenkins this has been
developer voices with Simon pton Jones
thanks for listening