hello folks welcome back today we are
adding a new server to my home lab setup
a proxmark server I will use it to
create and manage virtual machines
starting with the nxo VM today we'll set
it all up using terraform for a fully
declarative infrastructure as
C first of all let me walk you through
the existing infrastructure using a
network diagram
here so here I have the 10 GB router
from the ISP which is connect to the
internet through
fiber in one of the 1GB ports in the
router I have an existing prox MOX
server connected and it is called
Pluto so from the router I have a 10 GB
switch connected to it it's just a cheap
router I bought from alexpress but it
it's working perfectly
fine and in the sitch I have two devices
connected so one is the one is the TR
server it is running in a in an old HP
machine which I bought from eBay so here
I have two interfaces connected to it
one 1GB and uh the second one at 2.5
GB and coming to the server specs for
our jupyter proxmox server so I'm using
an Intel Knock 10 which I bought B 3 or
four years ago so it has 12 course it's
an i7 CPU and 32 GB of RAM it also have
a 2 terab of SSD out of which I have
given 1 tab for proxmox and I left 1 tab
as and
partitioned so here is what we are going
to do today so I already installed prox
Mox and configured it with this IP
address and I also use a DNS for This
Server so this is already configured to
resolve to this IP address and uh I have
this machine configured to SSH into
proxmox so first of all I'm going to use
the proxmox helper scripts to do a bunch
of post install tasks for example
disabling the nag screen and setting up
updates Etc and then I'm going to add a
new NFS volume which is going to connect
to the trest server so I'm going to tore
all the vir machine templates iOS
templates Etc in the truna server and in
order to use the in procm I need to add
a volume for that then I'm going to use
nio as my base image for building the
virtual machines so for that I need to
download the iso and store it in the
location where prox MOX can use them
after that we are going to do we are
going to start working with terao so we
need to set up the providers and set up
the initial project for
terao so then we are going to use terao
to provision a new nyxo vir
machine so this is what I'm trying I'm
planning to complete today So eventually
I will set I will be working more with
NYX and uh set up Game servers
kubernetes and a bunch more
things okay so let's start with the post
install scripts so for that fortunately
we have a project called proxmox V
helper scripts uh I will add the link to
this website in the description so this
project contains a bunch of useful
scripts which you can use to automate
working with prox MOX so this makes our
life much easier so here you can see a
bunch of things like uh for example if
you want to install
Docker if you install a lxc container
with Docker you can use one of
this so what we interested in for now is
to use the prox MOX V post installed
script so I'm going to use that the
script provides option for managing Fox
MOX V repositories including disabling
Enterprise sto adding or correcting PR
PV sources enabling the no subscription
repo adding the test repo disabling the
subscription nag updating Pro Mox and
reboting the system okay that's exactly
what we're looking for since I have SS
access configured I will do s to
Jupiter copy and run the
command the script will per form post
install routines yes
please so we will have the option to
choose what we want to do correct Pro
Resources yes please disable Enterprise
repository yes enable no subscription
repository yes correct safe package
sources yes
please add PV test
repository okay I'm not interested in
that disable the subscription a yes
please
okay disable High availability I don't
need it at the moment maybe we will
enable it
later
okay update prox box V now yes let's do
it okay so the post installation script
is complete we can also do a report if
necessary but I chose not to so this is
now complete the next thing is to add
the NFS volume for the templates let's
do that
okay so let's go to Data Center storage
and add
NFS okay let's call
it templates NFS so true n
cost
okay and uh here it shows the export
list and uh that's the one
okay so it can have a container template
we see the backup
file ISO image dis image all these
things okay let's add
it all right so
here the NFS has been added here
perfect now what else do we need to do
we need to download the nxo ISO into
this directory perfect next is
ISO so we are looking for a minimal ISO
image
for Intel
AMD okay let's use a clean
link okay so we will have to download
this directly in the
nas I'm wondering if where this is
mounted in the
prox MOX see the mount
points okay so this is mounted to mnpv
templates
NFS that's
easier okay so I can do Wate with the
Linux
ISO so the
iso huh actually this this should be
inside template ISO okay so we need to
move the latest nxo ISO into template
sliso folder that is
location nexos is available now
now we can start tform
setup
so I already have the repository called
H lab
I ready let's start the editor
so we are going to have different
projects for procm Tress and multiple
things so I need to keep them separate
in different folders so I like to use a
a folder structure which includes the
site name and the infrastructure project
name so here my site name is Cosmos and
uh inside that I'm going to create a
folder with the name
Jupiter okay so this folder is going to
manage all the
infrastructure within this
proxo okay so inside that we need a
main.tf file a providers. tfile
terraform dotf file
okay so in order to use terraform for
proxmox we need a proxmox provider so
let's prox
mod Okay so so we actually have a couple
of different options and uh what I used
before is this one tmate box MOX
provider and here in resource you can
see it can create a prox MOX qm virtual
machines and lxc and also cloud in discs
so this looks like a good start for
us let's copy this actually before that
we need to use the provider
so we need to initi ize the ter from
Project by adding this
here okay so this is going to use
3.01
rc4 okay and uh
configuration we need to first check the
configuration
part so first of all we need to create a
the new user name perform Prof and uh
assign the necessary permissions to be
able to create the virtual machines and
then provide those credentials in here
to be able to connect to proxmox okay
let's do
this so this is going to create a new
role named tform Pro and uh let's have
quick look through the permissions to
see that it's
correct okay nothing crazy I think then
creates a user and uh here we had to
provide a password
okay then it assigns the role to this
user okay let's add the role
first okay and then
user so I'm going to use a simple
password now and then change it
later because I'll have to add it to my
bit
Wen and
then allow the user with this role okay
and then we need to create a connection
by username and
password
okay so in order to provide this
environment variables I'm going to use
uh D so I can add this
here so what I'm going to do is
eventually
move this to a new password manager so
instead of exporting this instead of
hardcoding this here it is going to get
it from New pass okay so for that I'm
going to use this something called
D so what DM does is whenever we CD into
a directory and if it has a envc it's
going to Source it
automatically so we
can we can also add uh like scripts here
or things like
that so this makes our workflow much
easier so you don't have to run this
command each time when you have to run a
terraform
command Okay so let's uh let's try it
out let's try from it oh sorry I'm in
the wrong folder of
course so as you see when we are new
nvrc file then D will complain that this
is not yet allowed so we have to allow
it whenever we change this for security
purposes so if I do
the allow okay so it's going to export
these two these two
[Music]
variables let's do a simple terraform
plan and see what's happening okay there
are no changes because we haven't
defined any resources yet perfect and uh
what else do we
need okay I don't think we need anything
else so the provider is set up terraform
is ready now we can go
to creating a q km
resource okay so this is how we Define a
virtual machine uh this it is called
proxmox VM Kimu then we can provide all
the parameters like the name of the
virtual machine which node it has to be
be deployed to and all the
additional uh discs CPU memory all those
details so this provider actually has a
lot of parameters to go through so
instead of defining this from scratch
the easiest approach which I usually
follow is to create one VM from here
from scratch and then import it to
terraform then we can start tweaking
this and uh use that as a template for
the
the next set of
images Okay so let's try that let's
create a VM and
sayit okay call it
nxo so here we are using the image which
we just
downloaded so let's leave everything as
default and yeah let's add a chem agent
as
[Music]
well okay diss we will give it let's say
50 g B and under the local
lbm okay this will
be okay CPU let's keep it say two
cores and uh 2 G be Memory looks good
Network give it a VI
brid
okay right two cores 2GB name is nio
looks good to
me so the virtual machine is created now
here what we can do is if you scroll
down there should be an option called
import so terraform has a way
to import an existing resource into the
code instead of writing this from
scratch so let's do
that so
import blocks okay so let's use this
syntax to import this existing virtual
machine into our code so the reason why
we using this instead of the import
command is we can also do code
generation with this so it will generate
the entire configuration for
us
imports.
DF so this will be
prox MOX
vmk
okay dot
nyos and the ID is the VM ID which
is
okay now what we can do is when we do
terraform plan it should show that
configuration for about Target does not
exist because we don't have the code for
this so we can do terraform plan with
generate config out so this parameter is
going so with this parameter we can
Define that uh it should try to generate
the configuration as code for this
resource and uh write it to generator.
TF let's try that and it doesn't
work because you must specify an
endpoint for the prop most envirment
okay so it looks like we need ah of
course of
course PM
P so this is going to be this
URL okay sorry
okay let's let's try
again next trying to read and pass the
resource in valid resource format it
should be node type VM ID what is the
type so node is
Jupiter and I think it's
K okay so now that we specify the the ID
of the virtual machine to import let's
try
the okay so it's not always perfect
sometimes there can be
conflict so I think we can just get rid
of the this parameter to make it
work so generator TF as you can see it
has already generated the entire
configuration for us
so here it was complaining about line
number
77 let's
see see don't pass
through let's remove this part and leave
it as
default
then can we do a plan now so here as you
can see now it is trying to import this
into our state and
uh looks
good we can apply this
now perfect so now we should have a new
state
file so it has created a ter TF typ file
this will contain the entire state of
our infrastructure so we not pushing
this to get at the moment but if
eventually we will encrypt this and push
it to Kit you can also use like a S3 or
some other cloud storage for storing the
state but I prefer to just keep it
simple and uh push it as encrypted into
git okay so this is generated. TF I will
just REM rename it to
n.f okay so let's clean up a
bit remove that part and uh all the
parameters are optional so we can
actually do a find and
replace okay so that removed
everything so these are the only
parameters which we care
about
okay all right looking good so we can
actually try one thing so we can try to
duplicate this and try to create a new
VM without touching the UI so I'm going
to add a nios 2.
DF and then use this as a
template so this will be nxo
2 and um we need to adjust the name to
make it
unique then we need to adjust the VM ID
not sure if it's a parameter here no I
can add a VM ID
= to
1.2 so the previous one was 100 I think
yep so let's make it 1
not2 then it will use the same ISO it
will add a disk maybe let's keep the dis
to 20
GB we are testing
anyway I think I probably added this
okay Network keep it
same and
uh I guess I'm not supposed to provide
this you know what I will just leave
this
details probably we only need the bridge
and the
model all
right let's
see terraform
plan Okay so this will create a new
virtual
machine with the name nio
2 name is here okay same memory same
same CPUs all
good okay
apply and use Target node or agent
nodes did we missed that agent
H I'm going to do a Terra
form fmt to format the code then we can
apply
again it's creating that's good news
let's look at the UI
okay as you can see now the O has
started it's not started yet okay so it
has created the virtual machine with the
exact same
settings you can see memory processors
all good and it is using the CD ROM as
well and the hard disk is also
here so
now let's also keep it started how do we
start this
okay if he set the on boot to true then
it will start at the time of boot let's
do that is it true okay it's already
true VM State should be
running
okay BM state is now stopped so let's
keep
it change it to running so we are going
to start both the instances
okay
apply okay so you can see that uh it's
now changing the Status to running so
this is going to start both the virual
machines okay it is started so let's
check the
console so this time let's go let's
start it
perfect let's check
the so here you can see that we have the
20 GB disc attached and also the
iso so once we install
the once we install the Nyx o into this
disk we can get rid of the iso
well let's go back to a checklist so we
have the terraform set up and we Alo got
the nxo watching machine
running so that's it for this video in
the next video we will optimize it and
start setting up our game server using
NYX o