tom here from lauren systems and as of
july 2022 tail scale has been added as a
package for pf sense plus and pf sense
ce i'll leave a link down below to the
netgate announcement that also has an
embedded video from christian mcdonald
where he breaks down the tail scale how
it works and a lot of the details that
went into writing it because well he's
the one that wrote it great video lots
of information now what problem does
tailscale solve well tailscale's an
overlay network and i have a few videos
where i've done on tailscale and other
overlay networks also linked down below
so if you'd like to dive into that topic
the problem i see this really solving
for a lot of people is with tail scale
you load the tail scale client on mac
linux windows devices but obviously
there's some devices that may not be
accessible to you to load tail scale on
you know iot devices or camera systems
etc by having it on pf sense this allows
your tail scale name space that you set
up to have apf sense in the mix that can
advertise routes and this gives you the
ability then to
have access to all those non-tail scale
devices that are on the network behind
pfsense it also offers the opportunity
for people who have been stuck with
carrier-grade net and can't just put a
vpn on pfsense because well no public ip
address available for them and tailscale
will facilitate routing through the cg
nat space and still allow these devices
let's say you have a laptop and you want
to leave home but be able to still get
to all your devices at home no problem
half tail scale on laptop tailscon pf
sense and that will bridge that access
to all the devices behind there now
tailscale has a lot of features but one
of them is not going to be
absolute the best performance speed even
though it's based on wireguard and
christian mcdonald addresses this in a
video it's based on the wireguard go
implementation so there are some speed
limitations second it's not the same as
using a privacy vpn this is a discussion
people may go well can i just use it for
all my vpn needs not necessarily i have
a link down below for setting up openvpn
as a privacy vpn with policy routing
it's not as much a policy routing type
of vpn it is more a connectivity
solution with the overlay network so
we're going to dive into how simple it
is to set up what you need to get going
with it and just a couple of parameters
and a few security thoughts about it
before we dive into the details of this
video let's first are you an individual
or company looking for support on a
network engineering storage or
virtualization project is your company
or internal i.t team looking for someone
to proactively monitor your system's
security or offer strategic guidance to
keep your it systems operating smoothly
not only would we love to help consult
on your project we also offer fully
managed or co-managed i.t service plans
for businesses in need of it
administration or it teams in need of
additional support with our expert
install team we can also assist you with
all of your structured cabling and wi-fi
planning projects if any of this piques
your interest fill out our hire us form
at laurentsystems.com so we can start
crafting a solution that works for you
if you're not interested in hiring us
but you're looking for other ways you
want to support this channel there's
affiliate links down below to get your
deals and discounts on products and
services we talk about on this channel
and now back to our content the first
place i want to start is the netgate
blog post because
the video that's embedded in here by
christian mcdonald the developer at
netgate who put this plugin together
covers how to set up two pf senses that
do not have publicly routable wan
addresses but allows for the connection
of these devices as a site-to-site vpn
so that's well covered and well
documented along with a lot of other
details so i do encourage you to watch
christian video if that's the setup
today we're going to focus on a setup
that is just for connectivity now before
we go any further i will mention yes i'm
aware and yes i've tested head scale
head scale is a open source alternative
to tail scale so tail scale has a open
source client the protocol they use is
wire guard so everything about them is
open source except for the coordination
server and the back end head scale is an
implementation of tail scale that's
basically open source it does lack a
proper ui it doesn't have a nice web
interface on there to make it easy to
manage
they have documentation how to get it
set up i did go through and set it up
and make sure it works fine with pfsense
and all the other devices but i am not
using it for the demo because well it
would add a little bit of extra
complexity but i'll possibly do a
separate video on this if people have
trouble getting it set up their
documentation is kind of basic but they
do have commands you can go through and
figure out how it works along with some
example configs
now the obvious prerequisite for this
video is going to be that you have a
tailscale account set up you can sign up
for free as of july of 2022 they allow
you up to 20 devices for free and i
mention it like that because one i want
to save the date in case they change any
of the policies on there but of note the
devices this is thomson pf sense lts
telescale pf sense lab and a few other
things i have in there
my tom home pf sense is one we're going
to be focusing on but this counts as a
device and i have it advertising the
subnets behind it this allows
connectivity to the devices behind it so
if we look at the diagram here we can
see like tom's phone this other lab
server we have them across the internet
they want to connect to townspf sense
each of these is a single device these
are not devices these are just extra
routes that are advertised by my psns
that allow like my phone whether it's
connected to the 5g lte network wherever
it is or this extra lab server i have at
the office that i'll demo to talk to my
pf sense and therefore pf sense then
handles the routing between all the
devices
something worth noting as well when it
comes to access controls the access
controls is how you control all the
devices here and their ability to talk
to each other the default routing rules
are yes they can all talk and yes when
you advertise routes any of these
devices can talk to these particular
devices that are set up behind there the
rules have to be done inside of tail
scale so you don't control any of the
rules inside of pfsense for very
specific routing information with the
limited exception that we'll get to when
we talk about the firewall rules a bit
later in the video but for the most part
it's relatively easy to set up it's easy
to add these devices and we'll start by
deleting a device because we already
have this one configured but we're going
to delete my pfsense lab and show you
how to add apf sense to it that part's
really simple and pretty easy to get
started with now this is the pf
synthetic lab and i want to start by
actually log out and clean this will
forcibly disconnect this particular pf
sense so now tail scale is not running
and don't worry these keys aren't
reusable but this is all a demo account
anyways so we've gone into tail scale
and we leave this the same this is what
you would change if you were using
something other than tail scale such as
head scales a coordination server so you
leave the login server the same and you
just put in the pre-authorization key
so right now status is not running so we
look at the settings even though it's
enabled tail scale is not working
because we forced a log out and clean
now if we go back over to tail scale and
look at the machines
you can see that it's offline so we'll
go ahead and just delete it so this is
pfsenselab and we're going to go ahead
and remove it so we can add it again so
we've deleted it here then we go over to
settings
and we want to
go to keys
and we want to generate an auth key
we don't want this key to be reusable
you could if there's some use case you
have for it but it's easy enough to
create a key so we don't want a
removable ephemeral machines alchemy key
will automatically be removed after
going offline as in do you want to be
temporary probably not tags well you can
create tags to automatically put and
apply different things to this
particular key but we'll go with
generate key
then we're going to hit copy and we know
the key is copied
go back over here
paste
then we just hit save
see it's enabled
and then hit save again here
tails count on refresher check status
page we go over to the status page here
it's online and ready to go it's pretty
much instant in real time i did not have
to edit any of that matter of fact the
key already went away because it's been
used the pfsense lab
is already showing up and showing
connected it's pretty much instant when
you
add a device inside of here for it to
show up not just for pfsense but for any
other ones there's not much of really a
delay and down here if we scroll down a
little further on the status i've
blurred out the bottom where it has my
public ip address but it's giving you
all the information about that is
connected and it can see all the other
devices that are within this namespace
of tail scale that it can talk to so
these are all the other devices that are
online of course talk to by default is
all these rules are open you can talk to
any of these devices but if you change
the ecl rules they will still just show
up here but you know you'd have control
over the inner routings between these
now in terms of settings over here this
is where do you want to accept subnets
that other routes advertise this is
where you can get in a more advanced and
this is covered in christian's video and
it's pretty simple you just accept the
route
and
then add
go over here to the routes and for
example in my system it's the 192.168.11
network and if we go to this lab pf
sense the main screen here
that network does not exist over here so
it has a three dot network 40 22
and a 10 dot network but we go over here
to diagnostics then routes because we're
accepting advertised routes there's my
tail scale one nine two one six eight
zero slash twenty four tail scale 0
route combine that with firewall nat
outbound
and then we say we would like anything
heading to that destination to go out
tail scale this is covered as i said in
christian's video this lets devices
behind here talk to that other system
it's probably the easiest i've ever set
up a site-to-site vpn using tailscale it
just makes it really really simple and
if they do have public ip addresses
tailskill will have these devices
talking directly to each other now back
over to my server now my system is
already online keep configuration
advertise this exit node this is an
extra feature that's pretty cool that if
you say i want to offer to be an extra
node drop on internet traffic you can
take and there's options in different
tail scale clients to say hey route
thinks through an advertised exit node
what that means is for example with my
phone i can actually have my phone
routing all the traffic as if it's
coming from my home this is also very
handy if you are traveling with your
laptop and you would like a vpn to wrap
everything in tail scale does have an
option for that as long as you have an
exit node among the nodes and pfsense
can act as an exit node by simply
checking the box now this does not need
to accept any routes because this is
where the routes are coming from not
going to so by doing this we don't have
to put any special outbound net rules i
only had to put in this route that
already belongs to this network and say
hey advertise this route if i wanted
more you can advertise several different
routes the only thing i really want
access to is things on the 192.1680
network it's called nsfw lan i have a
video about setting up pf sense and i've
covered why i call it that but
essentially it's my untrusted network of
devices where things like well and as i
mentioned here we have the mb server or
the trunas server now let's talk about
pinging that server and this is the 192
168 72.110
so this is my little ubuntu lab server
it's actually remote it is not local to
me you can see it's not a 10 dot network
and this network exists actually over at
my office and tail scale is facilitating
this individual device connecting
through a tailed out coordination server
and then getting connected to my pf
sense and then having access to the
routes so we can do things like ping 192
1.8
easy enough to ping it or dot 30 which
is the mb server
now this is where things get a little
tricky and i want to talk about the
security concerns of this
if we go under firewall then rules
please note there are no rules here
under tail scale
let me explain the reason we're able to
and we'll go ahead and open up pf top
and we'll filter for host 192.168.1
and then we're going to go and ping it
again if we ping 192 168.1.8
you'll see the icmp packets coming from
192.168.11 and the reason why is because
the way freebsd is going to handle the
routing is it's going to send a packet
from the subnet by which there is the
most direct path which is going to be
192.168.11.
the routing is being handled internally
by pf sense so by me pinging even though
my origination ip address is this one
here the 198 72.110
that ip address isn't going to show up
inside of here that ip address
so if we go back to painting it is not
the source because it's coming to the pf
sense ip address that is attached to
tailscale might be a little confusing
but it's something to think about that
the firewall rules do not apply to this
traffic because it's handled inside a pf
sensor in this way this is where you
would need those acl rules that being
said what traffic is handled that way
and that traffic is going to be mypf
census tail scale ip which is 192
61 if i try to ping it there's no
response if i were to try to get to the
web interface there's no response so
let's go ahead and add a rule under tail
scale here going to add
pass pass
any
so you just let it all go through this
is a wide open rule here we're going to
hit apply
go back over here and now we can ping
it's as simple as that the control it
does have is over whether or not you're
able to do something with tail scale
within that ip address like for example
the web admin interface is technically
now accessible so if we change this and
we don't have a browser on this system
but if we did this in 104
3 well i have access to it now so now
i'm actually able to from all the other
tail scale nodes be able to get into the
web interface of pfsense that may be not
ideal because they don't need access to
that so we're going to go ahead and shut
that down
so it doesn't need any rules for this
scenario but i can still get to
192.168.1.8 so as i said it's coming out
and routing as the pf sense now from an
ease of use standpoint hands down tail
scale is just simple it's probably the
easiest if you follow christian's video
on setting up site to site which is just
adding those couple outbound net rules
dropping in tail scale
i've never set up a site-to-site vpn so
fast it just makes it really easy to do
especially because if you want to add
things like a phone in the middle of it
to also communicate with the devices
well advertise the routes on both sides
and add your phone and now the phone can
actually talk to both sides of those pf
senses provided on the routes conflicted
with each other so that would be a
different problem to start out as long
as you have completely separate subnets
on all the pf senses as in yes it's not
just site to site but site to site to
site to site hubspoke setup if you'd
like there's a lot of opportunity and a
lot of options here so i'm really happy
the integrated tail scale in here i will
work on if there's enough comments down
below about doing a head scale video i
kind of want to dive into it i really
like the way headscale works it's quite
simple because it doesn't need to join
in and neither does tail scale by the
way the routing that's being done is
between the devices it only goes into
relay mode where the traffic but
unencrypted with a wire guard tunnel
would pass through the external server
under the circumstance where no way
could it negotiate any of the udp hole
punching essentially it is used in order
to get the
devices talking to each other but
even without opening any ports all this
works extremely smooth
and i've talked before and i dove into
with the other videos as i mentioned how
udp hole punching works and i highly
highly recommend you read the entire nat
section of tailscale because it explains
all the different varied versions of nat
networking not as it relates to tail
scale but just how nat works in general
and it's actually a great lesson i think
in network engineering and just a
wonderful read for those who go i wonder
how nat works and i wonder all the
little different facets or how do you
deal with something when it's double or
triple netted and behind sieging hat or
what if two devices were behind cgnat
could it work tailscale is a solution
for even devices that are
on cgnat where it can see the
coordination server and still talk and
this is still functional inside of pf
sense and
it's basically the full feature tail
scale client on there and whether you
use head scale or tail scale it does
work so leave your comments down below
or head over to the forums for a more
in-depth discussion and thank you for
making it all the way to the end of this
video if you've enjoyed the content
please give us a thumbs up if you would
like to see more content from this
channel hit the subscribe button and the
bell icon if you'd like to hire a short
project head over to lawrences.com
and click the hires button right at the
top to help this channel out in other
ways there's a join button here for
youtube and a patreon page where your
support is greatly appreciated for deals
discounts and offers check out our
affiliate links in the description of
all of our videos including a link to
our shirt store where we have a wide
variety of shirts that we sell and
designs come out well randomly so check
back frequently and finally our forums
forums.laurensystems.com is where you
can have a more in-depth discussion
about this video and other tech topics
covered on this channel thanks again for
watching and look forward to hearing
from you
you