hi I'm Alex from tail scale and welcome
into today's video where we're going to
talk about cloud in it this is a
technology that lets you preconfig
virtual machines that you're going to
spin up in the cloud just by providing a
few lines of text in this video which is
the first in a series that we're going
to put together over the next few weeks
we're going to manually configure a
virtual machine on digital ocean in the
next video we're going to cover
deploying that machine with terraform
and after that we'll move on to anible
so if you've been looking for a way to
automatically preconfig your
infrastructure to join your tailet then
this is the video series for you as
always all the resources and time Stamps
will be down in the description down
below so let's take a moment just to
talk about what cloud init is first it's
a tool used mostly by folks in the sort
of devop space who want to automate the
creation of infrastructure specifically
virtual machines that they want to
create certain users or perform or run
certain scripts when the machine's
created as part of the initial boot
process cloudinit was originally a
canonical project the company behind
auntu but more recently it's now a fully
open source project and distribution
agnostic so in today's video I'm going
to walk you through the process of
creating a virtual machine or a droplet
as they call it on digital ocean these
droplets support the injection of cloud
init configuration in What's called the
user data field you can provide this
text just by copying and pasting it into
the digital ocean interface so let's
jump in and take a look now I've already
gone ahead and got logged into my
digital ocean account over here and I'm
going to click on the green create
button up in the top right hand corner
and create a droplet now there's a few
things to pay attention to here first of
all I should note we're going to do
everything in this next few minutes
manually going to do automation with
terraform and anable later on in this
video series but today everything is
manual so we'll need to pick a region
I'm just going to pick New York because
that happens to be closest to my
geographic location but where you put
this kind of matters a little bit like I
don't want to put it in Sy if I live in
the Northern Hemisphere for example but
any of these us data centers or a
European one if you're in you know
Europe or the UK or something should
suffice in terms of latency so just pick
something that makes sense to you in
this list next we're going to want to go
ahead and pick an OS I almost always
just pick abun to's latest LTS which in
this case is
244 then I'm going to go ahead and
select the type of droplet that I want
to create in my case we don't need the
$32 a month one or we going to need is a
basic $6 a month droplet down here that
will suffice for our needs today next up
I've already created an SSH key on my
digital ocean account although this is
entirely unnecessary if you're using
tail scale ssh what I will say is if you
don't select an SSH key here and you go
and try and connect to the virtual
machine in the digital ocean console
you'll be asked to create a password so
it is advisable probably to just have an
SSH key there because creating a root
password manually feels a little bit
Draconian all right so next we're going
to give this one a name I'm just going
to call this one banana and then under
the advanced options just up here this
is where the magic happens so if we
click on this add initialization scripts
option we want to paste in our Cloud
init stanza into this text box so I'm
going to jump back over to the tail
scale knowledge base article scroll down
a little bit and then just literally
copy and paste this entire Cloud config
block here you should note that this
head here the hashtag Cloud config must
remain intact this is a key word that
must appear as part of the beginning of
a cloudy knit stanza next we're going to
need to go over to Tails scale.com and
generate our orth key this is the case
of just going to tale.com our admin
console click on settings click on
personal settings down here in keys I'm
going to generate an or key I'm just
going to call this one banana but the
name is not important reusable yes why
not because it's a demo ephemeral no I
don't really care about that for this
and tags if you want to you can go ahead
and set up a tag this is defined in your
acl's by the way if you don't see these
tags you need to go ahead and create
them in your acl's as it tells you down
here and you do that by clicking on the
access controls tab here and defining
the tags in your acl's just here that
isn't important for this demo so I'm I'm
just going to leave that alone and then
90 days that's plenty for what we want
to do today so generate the key copy
that to my clipboard go back to my
digital ocean uh Tab and then just paste
in this line just here oh no I need to
leave the or key equals don't I there we
go now there's a few things going on in
this Cloud config file but we are
largely done at this point you can see
that first of all this Cloud config file
under this run command option here it's
downloading and installing tail scale
then it's setting up ipv forwarding
using CIS C L this is so that if you
want to use this node as an exit node or
do some kind of subnet routing the Linux
kernel is able to forward TCP packets
next up we're going to authenticate this
node to our tail net and then enable
tail scale SSH and finally request to
advertise this node as an exit node now
I'm going to go ahead and click on
create drop plet and I'll be back in
just a second when it's finished
provisioning now on the right hand side
over here I just want to click on
console and this can take a couple of
minutes for the VM to kind of boot up
and warm up
and once that has happened I can click
on that console button and be dropped
into a shell in my browser for this
remote virtual machine and we should be
able to see that tail scale is actually
already installed on this VM because of
the cloud init stuff that we set up
earlier and as you can see banana is now
a member of my tailet so if we go over
here back to my tail scale console go to
machines we can indeed see that banana
has been set up also note that SSH has
been requested and also has the exit
node functionality as well so we could
now use this virtual machine we didn't
have to type anything well we have to
copy and paste our or key but we didn't
have to do any you know apt get install
or curling scripts or what have you it
was all handled by that cloud init stuff
that we copied and pasted from the
knowledge base with tail scale earlier
you can append any other arguments that
you would like here anything else that
you would pass to the tail scale set
command you can string these together
into just one line if you would like to
and it's worth noting that I'll put a
link to this documentation down in the
description down below now doing things
manually isn't really the point of cloud
in it we want to start automating this
stuff and so in the next couple of
videos we're going to show you how to do
this using terraform and anable as well
but here's a quick sneak peek at the
terraform stuff so one of the key
principles of infrastructures code is
that we can Define our entire
infrastructure in a text file or
something that we can commit to a git
repo somewhere put it in Source control
I'll put a link in the description down
below if you'd like to get started with
terraform and also keep an eye out for
the video that's coming in the next week
or two to deploy a machine with tail
scale pre-installed and Docker
pre-installed in my case to digital
ocean is just as simple as typing
terraform apply and then enter a value
yes in order to actually go ahead and
have terraform perform those steps and
so what we'll see if we jump back to
digital ocean is we will see in my main
Dev project over here we will see that
now there is a new virtual machine being
created by terraform note in the
background down here it's still creating
it says 10 seconds elapsed uh this is
creating via the API terraform is
creating on digital ocean a new virtual
machine automatically with the cloud
inet stuff pre-populated with my or key
with my digital ocean API token it's
able to go and create those resources
for me in the cloud so what we could
start to do with this is in part of CI
environments we could actually start to
sprinkle this stuff into GitHub actions
or you know Jenkins workflows or
whatever you're using for CI these days
we can do this stuff programmatically
and so I'd just like to double check
that everything went okay with my
automation one of the easiest ways to do
this is to jump into the console of the
virtual machine and just try and execute
a couple of commands so I'm going to
jump back to the console of the digital
ocean droplet type tail scale status and
we will see that this node is now
already on my tailet and what this means
is that this node that's in a data
center in New York somewhere can now
talk to any other node on my tailet as
if it was in the same landan so I'm just
going to do a ping uh MVP ballrick
that's the laptop I'm using to record
this demo for example so that uh digital
otion droplet is now talking directly to
my laptop over tail scale even though
there's a residential firewall in the
way with no ports open or anything it's
it's I just love this stuff okay I also
snuck into this cloudinit file a Docker
install script as well so this node not
only has tail scale pre-installed and
pre-authenticated to my tail net it's
also ready to run Docker containers out
the box as well so hopefully you can see
that terraform is incredibly powerful
and we will dig into that in the next
video but for now thank you so much for
watching I've been Alex from tail scale