you
[Music]
so just just to start with the problem
space that NYX is trying to solve there
is a when we went back edge things in a
Linux distribution or or in any
packaging system really there is this
loop of state where a package outputs
which are files land on the file system
and then the next package picks up those
files among new packaging meter data and
and uses that to to build you know
another package and and this look goes
on and on and on and at the end it's
hard to see really what was compiled or
build with what and it's even you know
and worse it's it's not reproducible
right so we have kind of two spectra you
know two things that are trying to solve
this problem on one inspector into the
continues ation so start from scratch
and you know go through through the feet
through the state loop so many times and
always end up at the same thing or we we
use Nick's
where we try to be precise and use a
purely functional language to to to be
able to to compose things together which
you know should in theory give us a bit
more precision and power to to to our
charter pipeline so yeah mixed language
it's you know I think it's almost 15
years old
it's a DSL so you will see that some
areas because of that are like debugging
are not a good story yet it's fairly
functional it's namely type it's it has
lazy evaluation so I assume most of you
are our Haskell developers here so I
will that's assumed during this talk and
yeah this is how you basically you would
you know get started you install it
through this terrible download through
the internet thing that you know people
tell us all the time it's a terrible
idea
but how do you bootstrap a package
manager if not through internet you're
encouraged to use the GPG keys and so on
and then the current version doesn't
come with ripple but you can install it
and you
you can get started so let's let's go
into a language a bit I think it's good
to build that baseline through some
examples we we have you know it does the
right thing when it comes to dynamic
languages if you you know do try to use
operators that doesn't make sense it
will like error out you can query for
what type what type of a do you have and
also you can a search types and say I do
we have a string as I've said it's a DSL
for packaging so it has a kind of
special properties one of them is it has
a single quote well first of all it has
double quoted strings there are you know
the plane the thing you would expect and
then it has like this single double
single quoted strings which basically
what they do is they strip out all the
the indentation you will see here that
basically it it takes the most left part
of the string and strips everything out
and including the the prefix it keeps
the suffix new lines for example and
this is nice so that when you will make
expression and you nest them in your
editor you don't have to like always
strip that because in convicts you don't
want this indentation right so this is
kind of the the motivation behind it so
you just
just in just the orientation not nothing
else so it preserves everything else so
in Enix we have this something called
preamps these are the functions that
come with links you can see the whole
list if you just type built-ins and you
know we have something we call attribute
set up there and for example there is a
function called attribute names and you
can get then all the the keys in there
and again if you pass it like a boolean
and it will like say that you know
you're you're not doing the right thing
with right type functions that's kind of
the core of it right we have lambda
functions that's the notation at the top
it has the same kind of application as
Haskell and there is you know there that
the bad parts of Nyx is this where if if
you don't put a white space there it
will consider this as an URL yeah that
there's some bad I didn't include all of
them but there's there's some dark
corners um and this is really bad
because well we don't have types so
suddenly you know something instead of
getting a function gets a string and you
know debugging becomes a bit of Hell so
these are kind of the things I would
like to do that
Diggs would clean up after you know
through time but we'll see and then it
doesn't have well the pattern matching
is basically you can have these
attributes as as a you know as a
function input like this is a function
that accepts a and B and then you know
it uses the plus operator and Harry pass
a and B and we get for out this is like
the core of Nyx where you pass packages
and attribute sets in and then you do
something with them you wouldn't use
integers usually the main type is all
attribute sets all the way in index
everything else is like
secondary and then there's also defaults
in attribute and attribute sets when
they're you know as a pattern match for
the for the function so you can say that
if you don't pass a it's true and then
if you pass an attribute at empty an
attribute set you get a false back but
if you pass it in then you get you know
the logical thing now this is also kind
of useful to set defaults when when
there's you know something not saying
we'll see that later on there's these
you can get all of the all of the inputs
in in the arcs and there is one caveat
there the defaults are not included so
if you have a default like this and you
don't pass a explicitly in the the arcs
will be will not include it that's
another trick that another tricky thing
that yeah hunt hunts you and then
there's some you know syntactic sugars
around it like if you if you we have the
light in okay that's pretty obvious if
we have an attribute set like upstream
we can create another attribute set by
you know using the dot something more
from from the guys using pure script or
Elm and and the you know the shorter
version is to use inherit which
basically means take the upstream
attribute set and then you know inherits
a and B from it any questions so far
right pretty basic and then there is
this recursive function that basically
you can have an attribute set that that
references other other values within
itself instead of doing this let in at
the top yeah basic so and there is this
width which basically means declares the
namespace so if you have an attribute
set and you say with this attribute set
then you don't have to always prefix
that
it says and you can just go we usually
use this for a big package set so you
don't have to say packages dot blah blah
blah one one thing that's really tricky
with with statements if you have with
eggs and with you know epsilon the the
first one prevails after the second one
so it doesn't overwrite which is really
an iterative and you have lists yeah
they're without commas so anything you
do in here you have to put in
parentheses otherwise you will you know
you won't get if you have a function and
you want to you know call it inside the
list as an expression you have to put it
in parenthesis otherwise you'll get real
results as I've said it's a language
language we have these imports statement
that basically means it doesn't have
modules at all where you basically
import everything that a file returns or
a function returns in a file so if we
have a a file and and B annex and B Unix
you can cross cross import and if you
use instantiate command you can evaluate
it and so yeah and then you can say you
know then you can use the attributes
after you get three chambers
this is kind of like the the core of how
packages work trainings
yeah that's usually yeah you get usually
what you do you have a top level
function in the file which is like an
attribute set where your pet remains the
attribute set and you know you you kind
of get the the inputs and then you
return an attribute set of off packages
and things you want to it which it
wouldn't have fully evaluate well in
this case B and in this case a right it
was just a code chunk whatever yeah and
we have paths one of the another one
quirk is if you want to refer to a
current path you have to do dot slash
dot which is again something if you if
somebody doesn't tell you you say dot
and and it's it's it's like an edge
pivot set X's I think and then you know
weird errors happen again mix was never
meant to be successful and you can see
that in some places and yeah we
differentiate between strings and and
paths and I have have a blog post in
progress that kind of explains it's
pretty actually complex how onyx handles
the difference so I won't go into that
now sorry maybe maybe we can yeah maybe
maybe I published that dog dose and you
can read it and tell me if that makes
sense
and then it has kind of three ways to
the exceptions one is well just to
forget the try evil for now if you say a
board that's like you know aborts
evaluation and there is no way to to to
to go around that there is the tro which
you can actually then catch retry evil
and it says you know either success is
true or false and then either you get
the value or you don't get the value and
this is what we do in x packages to
evaluate each package because if one
fails we don't want the whole thing to
fail and then we just print out the
error and we go on and then there
there's also the assert so a third
expression and another expression that's
follows and you can also
catch that with a try evil yeah this is
another great area dark area where it's
kind of tricky a lot of times to be
precise of what areas you want to catch
and what you what areas you don't want
to catch there's not enough precision
and then there's there's buildings like
read file and you know if you have a
file foo and it has contents bar you
actually get that back so the question
is where's the purity right that it's
it's not we don't have types so we
where's the dick you know where do we
declare purity so NYX has a bit
different model than Haskell so yeah
let's let's look at that so for now we
have this basic language it has you know
attribute set list blah blah blah but
it's very pure we cannot interact with
the world right it's pretty boring now
now this is where the gist of it comes
in the derivations and the derivations
they produce build products and you know
from so from expression to a derivation
this process is called evaluation time
so we take NYX you know files and you
create you evaluate them you get a
derivation files and then if you realize
they're evasions you get build products
so it's a two-step thing and the reason
why that that's the case is you might
want to evaluate NYX get the derivation
files copy to you know distributed over
machines and then you want to realize
them so it helped that's why the it's a
two-step thing so the derivations are
basically intermediate representation of
Niki's expressions fully evaluated so oh
let's say we have a very simple C
program which basically only does it
gets an environment variable out and
then you know it creates the file we
compile it and this would be our most
simple derivation up there it requires
three fields the name what system is
going to build on and what's the Builder
the Builder is an executable that
creates the
the output path that's the that's the
minimum thing it has to do and down here
we see this process so this is
evaluation which you know goes for mixed
expression into the duration file and
you see this long hash and then next or
minus our realizes that and builds it
into and calls the builder to produce
the output path so for those that use
Nix Nix build is basically you know
those two steps combined essentially as
a convenience if you're on this if
you're building and in realizing on the
same host that you use Nix build so so
then comes the question of where is this
hash coming from this has is a hash of
all the inputs for for the derivation
right so it's basically content and rest
and and and and this is where the purity
comes in the relation is built in a
sandbox like separated from the file
system disabled networking everything
and and all the things that are allowed
to influence that that builder are
coming from the derivation attributes
this is the purity part so inched
instantiate takes an X file avail
evaluates it into a derivation out and
well the relation is basically this
internal representation of what mix is
gonna do
that's it's hard to show it here I also
show it later and and then Nick store
minus R is it takes this intermediate
representation and actually goes and
executes the builders so realization
part
yeah so you you would want you would
want to for example let's say you have
you know a lot of Knicks expressions you
want to to evaluate them and then
distribute the bills right so you
wouldn't be able to distribute to the
building part if it would be just one
one thing or at least it would be harder
to do so right because they're evasions
basically for a dependency tree so you
can write write an algorithm that takes
the leaves and and you know like
distributes them
good question
so Gabriela Gonzalez wrote this really
cool too
let's see
part of part of this darkest
he wrote a Haskell parser for it but
it's basically it's kind of instructions
right yeah yes so it's like all the
outputs it's going to create all the
inputs it needs what's the the Builder
is going to call to actually build
things in the sandbox or you know what
is the environment what are the
arguments to the Builder and so on
so everything NYX really needs to build
this thing in in the sandbox and this is
this is you know a hash that's this is
the hashes are actually hashes of all
this inputs and this this is the purity
part yes it's kind of like implicit
because all the inputs you gets already
include the hashes in string so it's
yeah yeah and yes and then it basically
knows that you know you have different
hashes and it goes so it forms a
dependency graph so that the way it
constructs a dependency graph is
basically it scans for hashes through to
the derivation files and and the same at
runtime I'll explain that a bit does
that answer your question
you seem to be in part ok oh maybe maybe
as we go on it becomes clearer or we can
go back and revisit this so yeah this is
not the best way but sorry and then ok
and then then comes this you know very
common problem in packets in the
bootstrapping right now okay in in in
this case we took the compiled you know
file as our builder and that was our
input which was you know pure as we
always get the same builder otherwise
the hash would change if the contents of
the touch file would change but now we
want for example to compile it from
source right and then you get into this
bootstrapping problem of like where do
you get gg8
know GCC from
so you have to start somewhere in
bootstrap and this is where Nix packages
come from you have we have something
like standard environment which is like
the baseline so we we take binaries of
GCC and so on and bootstrap the the
basic derivation with the binaries we
compile that again to from source and
then you get standing environment which
includes that the batch builder and GCC
and kuru teals and or all of the the
standard tools and and the make the make
file is there and and so on so quite a
lot of things that you get out of out of
the box so and and then this is more
like something you would really use for
minx packages okay I'm here it becomes
tricky this is like the the typical
pattern or however you want to call it
where we importing expected jizz and
then we we put it into our namespace so
we don't have to say packages that stand
in environment blah blah blah and this
this is the part this is the function
that calls the primitive derivation and
and you know NYX itself doesn't come
with any packages so it's very you know
it's meant to be a general purpose thing
but to do anything useful you need to
have this environment to build things in
this is this is yeah we would need a bit
of time to go through all of this I'm
sorry for being a bit vague on this one
and and then the make derivation kind of
is is except these more high-level
attributes like you can tell it where
the sources and you can tell it build
phases and the way this works is
actually it's a long bash file that
basically executes - functions and these
build phases are basically bash
functions that are then like inline into
this hole builder bash process of course
nobody stops you you could basically use
Haskell as a builder and you could like
pass it in and and all of these
attributes are passed in as an arguments
to the Builder basically on the common
line so nothing stops you from for
grading
Haskell builder if you want to go so far
there is actually a GU weeks which is
kind of like
I would say competitor but a friendly
experiment which reduces Kyle to go all
the way down so it uses guile as a you
know the language for describing the
derivations but also the Builder is
written in God so you have the same like
language all the way down so that's yeah
we were here Nick goes the pragmatic
approach and and God and and Greeks goes
a bit more extreme and yeah and here we
do make derivation you already get GCC
and so on so you would be able to guess
so every time you would you would change
that see basically this source here
would you know this the con the content
of this source would change so to hold
the hash would change because of that
basically yeah that yeah so all the
inputs right in this case source is is
the whole yes yeah so like for local
development if you have local things
like you know like an editor on an
editor config or so on you have to
filter that out other words becomes part
of the hash I hope I hope that's a it's
a lot to cover so I cannot you know we
would need a couple of days to really go
through all the details and there is the
there there is these are con you know
contents and reservations but there is
also a fixed output duration which
basically means instead of calculating
the hash we give the hash to the
derivation and then you can allow
network access because anything you get
can be hashed at the end right so this
is how you this is how you do networking
then
and again we have a determinism by by
this hatch that we provide and the
factory would use you know curl in in
the background in the derivation
download it and then assert the whole
the whole output has this this hash yeah
that's that's our you know that's our IO
basically it's based on the fact that
you you you assert yes so so what what
this allows us to do really this this
hatch hashing is that I think for the
very first time we have a lacking system
that is source and binary right this
hashes uniquely identify how our
packages were built so we can basically
ash ask a service Oh with this hash can
you give me the binary package if not
I'll build it from source so mixes is
transparently its its source and binary
at the same time right and we use this
binary we call this binary substitution
which you can use SSH or HTTP or
something like that to ask for the hash
or you build it from source and and this
is what we do in our GK as well we have
the binary cash so actually you can get
you know a thirty megabyte compiled
Haskell binary for most of our commits
that that are in the github and and I
think one of the one of the you know
major you know things that makes really
you know invented or discovered to be
precise is that we have this path a
location like memory management you know
when we went to high level languages and
you can say give me some memory and all
this stuff this is what does with
pass right you say you know give me a
path with with food a tags name and and
with the contents bar and you know you
have it and then you can nest that and
it builds the dependency tree so this is
how it's you know collects what belongs
together
and so there are two garbage collectors
one is on the language itself you know
if things go you know we things are not
references it's it's garbage collects
them but there is the the second garbage
collector that actually as we as we
allocate these pads right there needs to
be some way of saying how do you clean
them up because it's it's it's immutable
it just creates them and then nothing
really you know deletes them and there's
the the carbage collection part which i
don't really talk much about in this
workshop but essentially what you do is
is you define a strategy how do you want
to collect things you can say like i
want to have ten gigabytes off of my
disks free and everything palaces is you
know should stay there and and it has
this concept of GC roots of where you
define you know you link the buildning
sneaks expression into a GC root and
that means it won't garbage collected
and it's it's it's better to read that
Labatt's it's pretty it's not important
really we have a terabyte disk so
whatever
yeah then then there's this concept of
entering this environment in which the
Builder will be built the derivation and
this is where where Nick shell comes in
this is the development tool right so if
I say if I if I have a default Nick's
file which is like the convention of
what it will use and I say you know
entered a hello attribute and this is a
derivation in that file then instead of
you know actually taking the the input
and and X you know building the
derivation in the Builder it will just
take the inputs and enter a shell with
all of those inputs present and because
our if our builder is bash of course if
you would take Haskell then you would
have to implement kind of your own shell
I guess this then it would huge you know
the g8 CI as a shell but in this case
you you get into a bash environment all
the inputs that would be used to build
the hello package and by default that
inherits your environment so it's
convenient for people if they have
editors and so on that you know they're
still around but you can say pure and
then you know if you if if whatever is
not declared as an input to do the hello
derivation will not be there so you know
now we're going to to a part where
workings become very blurry for most of
the people it's like how do you then use
this you know functional language as a
way to to override our packages like
that's what we kind of wanted right if
we want to have this precision then we
better use it and let's see let's see if
we can cover this quickly so a very
typical package would be something like
as I've said an input up there that you
paid rematch on all of the packages you
will you will need to Bill it and then
you would use the standard with make
derivation and then use those packages
as you go across the different stages
and the point is now you can override
these inputs or these packages that
you're getting in but first we need to
build a framework for that so the first
neat thing you would you know one would
do is you would have an attribute set of
packages you would import them and then
like fill in all of the inputs and and
these inputs would actually come from
this you know top level attributes set
so it would like feed them in so for
example input one would be here another
another package and input two would be
another package and so on so of course
you cannot have cycles right but that's
how how the top level mix packages
basically if you open that file you will
see a long list of packages like this
now the problem the problem here is that
every time you have to you have to like
every time if you rename input one for
example you would have to rename all the
packages that get it in and so on so
it's a bit cumbersome to do that so what
makes offers is this built-in called
function arcs where you can give it a
function that has a an attribute you
know that pattern matches an attribute
set and it will tell it you know what
inputs does this function have so it
will say oh it has an X which which
doesn't have a default this boolean
means if it has a default or not and it
has an epsilon that has a default right
so you know it's it's a bit more than
just that but what call package is
something you see in expect users very
often does is essentially that it
extracts all the inputs for this package
and it just you know figures out oh I
have to fill in the X input and the Y
input into here so you don't have to be
as explicit about it so you can pass an
empty attribute set but if you want to
be explicit and override an attribute
said you can just pass it in and
everything else will be you know kind of
like reflected from the function
arguments but this this one explicitly
will be overwritten is that
is that too magical or because the the
to define call package it's a bit of
work and hopefully you get the idea of
how the I will give it at the end and a
reference to Nick spills which is kind
of like the long version of what we're
going through why does it return false
or and true this is this basically means
does the in does the input have a
default value or not so this is the this
is the default so if you say a question
mark something then if you don't pass in
you know epsilon this will be the its
value and and this is so that you know
yeah sometimes it's useful but in in the
in the Cole package I don't think that's
really used it's more just what inputs
does it have to feel it any other
questions and then then what what call
package does is it adds on on the
derivation that's a couple of attributes
one is the the override function that
you can basically now take this
derivation and override it input so as
you see up here right these are these
are the inputs that we kind of used for
further derivation and and you can
override them so you can basically what
you can do is you can take I don't know
GHC and you say override use different
version of Lib GMP and you have to g8
sees now one built with with one version
of the library and one with the other
and you can basically use this
overriding mechanisms you to be to build
you know different different different
sets so one of the things I did in the
past is basically we wanted to test we
wanted to batch benchmark software and
we basically did
matrix of different kernels of qmo
versions and so on and basically use
that to benchmark the the software but
basically by just overriding which is
something you cannot really do in docker
or it was like that and and this one
actually overrides at this these
attributes here here that's faceted to
make the relation doesn't say so
yeah this attributes here that it's best
to make the relation so you can either
override a function up here or the
attributes at past which which can also
you know be a well you know there can be
left in in in between and it can do you
know some concatenation or something so
it can it can have different values
there so this is like the the high level
of writing then there is this this blog
post a gift by Russell O'Connor in 2014
where he goes to explore how do you do
dynamic biting and nicks right so the
problem is if you have an attribute set
like this and you use the req function
then you know X here will will come from
from from this definition but if you if
you use if you merge attribute set which
is something that you know you take an
attribute set and another one and you
merge them together then that then this
wreak function won't have an effect
anymore it's it's only it's local to
this attribute set up here so you will
see that the X here will we'll have this
overridden form def but the the rec part
that was ever lated here actually
evaluated this X in the original
attribute set right so then why is this
really important because we want to have
a package set and we want to add new
things to it but we don't want we don't
want the any reference values in the
original ones to to keep the old the old
values right we want the whole thing to
to actually to be precisely overwritten
so what we do is we define the fixed
point or the Y Combinator
like right here and I won't go into you
know how that most of you probably
already know if you don't and yeah
there's there's enough materials out
there so what weather it basically does
this this fixed function then gets
basically the return value as an input
and then you can basically instead of
using the rack you do self eggs and then
what you can do is you can stack these
attribute sets together and you get them
as an input also this would be later how
it works but you know this is kind of
like the baseline this is the this is
one of the parts that you know it's kind
of hard to grasp but but the fixed point
is kind of the build to build that our
helper here and there is a bit of other
things that that he does in the blog
post trying to build a framework for for
for this of a writing of package sets
which will see very soon yeah I I
haven't bothered to go through the whole
thing it's pretty long actually
but you'll you'll see how it's used then
if you if you know that it's a fixed
point I think that's enough to to to
understand how it works okay so so this
is the overriding part how do we
override packages and how do we use then
you know the lake's language to to
really to get the to solve basically the
dependency held the multi version hell
and and be precise about it
sang-doo slash slash
yes oh so there is there is one part
missing here which will which I'll show
a few slides later on how how that
really then is used to merge the
attribute sets okay now I want to now
move into more howhow Haskel ecosystem
uses links first of all there's the
stack tunics integration it's like with
Knicks integration that most of you use
if you use Cardno and basically what it
does if you say in stock that the ml
file enable and you know here are the
packages then what it does is is behind
the scenes it calls stack you know if
you call stack install it basically
execute you know Nick shell it basically
constructs this this common liner and
then it calls stack again so that's it
reap asses the arguments so it's
basically the same thing as you would
you would say Nick shell and and these
two packages and then you would call
stack it's just a clarity of in the
stack file alright and you can go a step
further to say okay don't like lease the
packages but actually use an X file and
then it's the same thing as a Nick shell
and then you know executing stack within
that and the purpose is of course to
provide the system libraries to stack
the problem with with this approach is
that stack stack knows precisely what
Haskell packages it wants to build but
it has no idea about the global system
state so every time you you change
basically Nick shell anything in it it
will like recompile everything from
scratch because it's like oh I have no
idea how this effects right my all of
the build so the best thing to do is to
start from scratch and and that's yeah
really unfortunate when you have a
creditor which has like a 360
dependencies if you want to build full
thing
so yeah let's get into a bit of
infrastructure of hask and minks and
there is this cabal tuning tool that
basically parses Cabala file and
translated into how NICs would build
that that cabal file so it takes haskell
infrastructure divided defines another
mega derivation which is like one step
you know it it wraps the make derivation
for the standard environment and it
defines like Haskell specific attributes
that you can then tweak like is this
should we build the library should we
build an executable what are the
dependencies of the library test
executable and so on and this is all
extracted from the from the cabal file
and and all of the values used here are
also in the closure of this function
here so that we can override it right so
that we have this power from the for
that we can override this up here this
function up here and that you know
reflects then in the derivation build
for alex in this example and then you
know what we do we go through the whole
hackett and call basically cobalt unix
on all the packages and you get this
huge attribute set right in the past
before snackage came we kind of like
petty used to you know try try and build
things together now we just default to
the latest takcs and then we the rest
of the packages we take the latest
version so we basically curate the
packages that are not in stack age
because we want to have the full later
set we used to have the full history but
that was like you know it would be a
couple of megabytes right now so it's
doable but you know if somebody would
want to do like a community project it's
doable to build all of this I think we
calculated if you want to build like
with profiling and without the profiling
and the whole it would be like 20 or 15
terabytes of all together to have the
whole package in all the common ways to
use it so it's it's you know it's not
unreasonable but nobody has done it yet
all right and then okay so we have this
you know very high-level Haskell
attributes that we understand as a
builder how you know how that reflects
how that affects the building and then
what we do we define this Combinator is
basically that you know take the
derivation and then override it and may
for example check means run to run the
tests so we have a do check and don't
check combinators that means you can
take so what it means is you call cobalt
unix to generate you know the what it
gets from cobalt but then you can say
okay enable the tests or or disable the
tests right so if for example if you
have n CL package you can say don't
check and you get an a new package bag
that won't run two tests and then you
can use this combinators basically to
compose and and tweak all of these
attributes here more or less okay any
questions so far
sorry yeah I don't know if you maybe
maybe it's too vague or maybe understand
everything now it's okay and then okay
and this is this is where our previous
fixed point comes in where where
basically what we do is if we start down
here these these this is that this is a
hackage attribute set of all the
packages and then we extend this with
Nick specific configuration and with
common configuration so the difference
is this adds the system libraries this
overrides some of the versions that you
know depend on what the versions are in
hackage and then we have a compiler
specific on thing like itself coffee I
have no idea what it is and and they're
all rights this is like your other
rights that you want to apply so what
this does it uses a fixed point and then
it uses you know it basically it's kind
of like lenses you you take the original
packet set you apply a bunch of other
rights and and you go on and on and on
and and the way it works is you have two
two inputs one itself and super so super
super is for example in Nick's
configuration super is Haskell packages
and self is Nick's configuration itself
so it gets to its own return value as an
input so you can either for example if
you all write something you can say like
take the the package from super or you
can take the package from from our own
attribute set that we changed yeah
that's this this file is a bit
simplified but that's basically what the
infrastructure in in Haskell does and
and then you know it's all SEC together
any questions about this yeah
yeah it's basically two Landers so you
can you know do currying and then you
know it's to lambda so it passes passes
that in I mean this make extended
extensible and extends is kind of like
the what uses the fixed point in to pass
in the preview set and then the set
itself of through a fixed point any
other questions
and then you know this is that at the
end how you would use all of this what
we covered so far is you say oh I want
the Haskell packages with compiler eight
point zero point two so for every we
take the hackage and then we pass the
compiler in and we create a new package
set
so for each compiler we do that and you
can get this package set by basically
saying packages dot and compiler
including you know jtj s or whatever and
then you override this set and you say
overrides and then now you have the
access to the to the whole thing and you
can say for example okay in my in my
attribute set that I'm interested in I
want to build stack but in that
dependency graph I want to take the MTL
but don't build you know don't be able
to execute the tests for example and so
on and then and and here comes all the
precision where you know we override and
our package set
I see subway-tile face some faces are
confused some faces are like so I guess
it color correlates with experience of
nich's
we would have to do like a three-day
workshop ready to go but you know it
yeah it takes a tight the major problem
with Nick's is it does so much and it
covers so many things that it's really
hard and it does it all with attribute
sets yes and and and and the functions
that operate on the attribute sets are
you know not as precise as you would you
know you have them in Haskell for
example right so there's there's legacy
okay so now I want to cover a bit how we
use NYX in yhk just on a very high level
one of the first things that when you
you start using Nyx's it it uses this
you know lesson and and more science
which basically means the take take this
NYX packages from the search path which
means this NYX path and Bosch
environment variable and this is you
know this is a pattern that goes through
the language packaging I don't know who
invented it but it goes on and on and
it's it's this again this global thing
of the environment that you know it's
really hard to figure out what's going
on and I can make sweet we have this
channels that basically then provide any
spectators and you update and them and
and you know it's all a bit stateful so
I recommend usually not use that at all
what we do in our HK and actually this
was this was a joint effort by a couple
of people to come up with this idea is
we have this NYX packages - source like
JSON which you know pins down expect
adjust your very commit and then you you
import this file that's present in all
repositories that basically uses a
derivation to import the NICS packages
and then you import that and you then
you have the next packages to be used
from their own so there is no this
global thing but actually what is used
is part of the git repository itself
pinned down to the committee
yeah the how its implemented it's I
won't cover it you can like look it up
but it's it's definitely it's it has
improved our you know results a lot in
terms of determinism compared to this
because like when you have a CI you have
to be careful that nicks path has the
same packages as you locally and so on
and so on so on so it's kind of
cumbersome then the second thing we did
we wrote this - cool tool called sec
tunings so what it does it basically
uses inside inside infrastructure of
stack to build the whole package set
that stack would basically build you
know either it comes from Hackett's or
it comes from a local folder or all it
comes from grid and then it calls cobalt
or nix on all of those and b builds our
own package set basically and and why
don't why do we want that we want the
developers to use the same packet set as
they did use in production so we at
least have some you know guarantee that
this was tested and used right we don't
want that the deployments just use a
completely different set and and and
then we start finding our box and this
is the the packet in the famous packet
generator power that you have to use -
and this is a bridge so we want
developers to use tag by deployments to
use NYX and and this is our bridge
between the development and the
deployment world it was recently
rewritten and it's you know quite fast
now it supports Mac OS it doesn't have
this cabal revision non-determinism that
you were a lot of you were hitting and
so on one of the one of the things we
want to improve is to to be able to
override a compiler right now it's
hard-coded to eight point zero point two
but you know getting there and then yeah
then Carano itself provides a package
set again which is directly translates
from what stack uses and you can say Nix
build card on or sell and you would get
you know the Cardano cell package and so
on this is is the you would run this
inside a card on OSL git repository and
for example we wrote the connect scripts
so now you can actually
build a full node and and this would
basically build a best script that would
run the note and you just run you know
for example if you want to connect to
maintenance you say the first line if
you want to connect to staging the
second line and and so on and so on and
there's also we have this top-level
attributes area where you can like you
know override for example you know
topology file for example for people who
want to use different apology file and
so on
so we're now able to build different
kind of best scripts and and the next
step is going to be testing them right
we'll take a virtual machine will will
run run its run all of those inside and
make sure that they all work right and
you know you can also use docker we also
have a doctor function and you can use
basic basically it uses the connect
scripts in the docker it just you know
provisions the Cardano inside and then
use those connect scripts and this is
what whatever what some of the our
partners use to build the docker image
and then and then the one of the
questions was if I remember it correctly
what but we would like to cover is how
do you you know develop packages UNIX
instead of using stack there is this
attribute on each package called
environment and this is what you can
like enter into so for example if you
want to develop on the wallet you can
say Nick shell and you would get you
know basically all the packages that are
passed to building the wallet and if you
if you if you're going to modify
anything that's not in the wallet but is
a dependency of the wallet then you will
have to re-enter the Nick shell because
that's a dependency and you'll have to
rebuild it but if you just work on the
wallet and you know and and what's nice
about this you can switch back and forth
between branches like stack would
recompile the whole thing here once you
once you you've build the dependencies
once there you run your machine so you
can just go back and forth and
yeah yeah future work what what we see
in what I see in in diet K what were we
going to focus on one is NICs 1.12 is
probably coming out soon that's been
going on for the last year so very soon
it has a lot of really really nice bug
fixes and and features I won't go into
that there is a talk by ELQ odo store at
Nick's comes this year that covers
what's coming so better just watch his
talk and four deployments Ria's
currently mix ups which is kind of like
Nick's OS but with provisioning of the
cloud services
the alternative is terraform terraform
is is way better when it comes to
provisioning because the community is
huge and they have a lot of things you
can provision so there there are now
different companies exploring how could
we like breach those two so we would use
like Nick's OS for the operating system
but terraform for provisioning part and
you know and then there is this
different ways to do it doll Jason
techniques and the HDL which is the
terraform language at the end it's all
JSON so yeah you pick your precision one
of the things is the multiple outputs GC
which is like a patch that has been like
ongoing together with with guys from
tweak we have been trying to get it in
but it's kind of hard I think I think it
needs a couple of days more work so what
does it do is we talked about before
where you create this out you know outer
folder which is this whole mix hash
thing you can create multiple of those
called lip paint la blah blah and so
when you when you when you generate a
runtime dependency tree you can like
leave things out right if you example if
you can compile the executable
statically and then you don't put in all
of the Haskell libraries so instead of
downloading you know one gigabyte
encoding
see you download just the 30 megabytes
of the static executable which doesn't
reference that and you know there is a
separate output for documentation and
and so on so you can be more precise of
what are the runtime dependencies so for
example right now we have this - static
packages so they don't pull in and and
this would be back kind of like now out
of the box all the binaries you would
reference - they don't have this huge
thing you have to like download so it's
mostly about reducing the what you have
to download yeah which is really nice
when you like build a docker image and
hand it to someone it's nice that it's
like 50 megabytes instead of like a
gigabyte and so on there is the cross
compilation we you know we would ideally
we would have nix for you know all the
platforms
so going from Linux to Windows compiling
with Nix there is a lot of work in the
GHC right now to go to arm and you know
how do we deal with template haskell and
so on one of the things that is also
interesting is the CI there is the the
Hydra what we use is completely pure so
it's like you know if you have inputs to
the Nix it distributes the that and
builds and gets through the build
results back but in CI there's always
this impure part where you know we have
to do some extra stuff interacting with
the world so there is there is a lack of
a good tool right now we use a build
kite right now but it's far from perfect
and then there's the NIC so as tests
which is basically kind of a driver how
do you operate with the VM so you can
say okay use this Nick so Nick so as
config build a VM and then wait for this
service do you listen on this port wait
for this service to start you know blog
this sport see what happens and so on so
this is like really nice for
reproducible tests and I think in our HK
we actually michael already wrote
initial version where we basically
launch four nodes and they started the
blockchain and and you could then you
know make some transactions and
and and an exit and get an output of
locks and and like analyze that and you
know graph for example you know I don't
know how long did it take to create
blocks over to ten minutes how many
blocks were missed and so on so this
could be all been automated that it's
this is basically almost ready the part
that was not working is actually that it
uses VM so on Amazon if you do nested
virtualization it's basically emulation
on trivialization and it's really slow
so the blockchain can keep up and it
starts to do to fall over so we will
have to use bare metal machines probably
to do this kind of things so we have to
provision that yeah this is these are
some of the references I would mainly
recommend reading the next pose if we
can just cover that so this goes into
very much in details into well what I
just described
there we go and there is you know it's a
it's a kind of a long tutorial about the
insides of the neck spec packages it's
pretty long and but you know at least
then it explains you sorry yeah they're
the the other you know it's a before you
go to sleep kind of thing
[Music]