Hello everyone friends in this video
tutorial we will analyze such an
opportunity as working with
pseudo graphics namely forwarding
using the console to our guest
operating system there is an option
called wish console
which is responsible for the ability to
connect just to the Crystal
operating system why is this
required
suppose you have some
hypervisor located not on the territory of
your city of your country and you
set up some script which
used firewall rules where you
made a mistake and let's say you prohibited
access to your guest operating
system let's say port 22 or ran out of
space on the hard drive
well let's say there are a lot of options in order to
fix this situation we need to either
call there technical support there
call the administrator so that he
fixes this situation and was to go to the
office if it is somewhere on the territory of your
city you are sitting at night well that is a whole
hemorrhoid to protect yourself from such
manipulations and let's say you have
access to your hypervisor then
accordingly no problems in working
with apse graphics namely connecting
using wish console you should not have
let me show you
how  these options
where should be located what are they
called actually
we lead up to the sheet as we see I
have one operating
system running actually it is not important
we can use both on switched off
operating systems pre-
prepare also they and on
switched on there are two configuration
parameters that are responsible for just
working with psy this is
called graphics stalemate is called 1 this is a series of
that by 2 console give them this business we
will demonstrate we lead a lump edit and I
will indicate
12 so as not to write this long
name what is accordingly 10 we are
now leading serial type these
options are included by default after
installing any distribution of
independence windows operating
system unix operating system linux
operating system that is any
operating system these these
options are included by default in your
configuration file of
your guest pepper skills environment
accordingly the type series and is responsible for
apses graphics that is and some no some
console utility that allows you to
use just forwarding of all
graphical interfaces but the type console
accordingly allows the wedge
console command to implement this technology
well let me demonstrate how with
these options if  we have no settings not
configured hypervisor namely guest
operating system
if we lead up console again
number 2 I will put and if I start we
press enter it breaks through as you can see
no manipulations with this turntable does not
happen if everything is good then in our
case it should dad we should get it
login and password and our guest person
tizen let him sit I will demonstrate in
our case it is also necessary to configure the
parameter responsible for just working with the
console yes this option is called
console
it should be registered in the
configuration file roughly
let's connect to the guest
operating system status and 219 to
bring the books lieutenant 123 123
and as we see we have now got to how
our guest person system and now
if you want to use pink you
need to register it in the group.  kfg
located in the home directory but
or if you use let's say so
often update your production
environment then it is better of course to specify this
option in the configuration file where
all the default parameters for your
roughly well let me demonstrate this to you
vim this is c default and
actually groups we need on those
parameter responsible for groups cmd line
linux and specify here the
console option equal to 1 of 0 as you
remember port 0 and accordingly the
data transfer rate 115 115 200 in such a
not complicated at all not complicated way
we have now configured our
console now we just have to
apply the parameters for our kernel we
lead to the boy group 2 m to the config with the
key about what does on put on put
group2
groups mean.  cafe g we press enter
accordingly our
configuration file is rewritten now we can
make sure that everything is fine with us
console is equal to yours for example yes and
but group2 groups.  cafe and as we see
this option got not just into the
parameters of launching our operating
system
after which we can actually
reboot and try now after
that open
but not top df wear was zero now we will
make sure that our system is fully
loaded we will not allow any errors
namely since I am a guest
operating system of work via
dhcp requests will be possible at the server api
address we see that in this case we
received api addresses of our virtual glasses and
now we can connect via
ssh
as we see everything is fine everything works and
now we can
play around with you namely let's kill that
forest h-service and on this everything will be fine with us
that give up from what ktr stop
sshd
excellent in our case we are all at bide
and now we can exit accordingly
if I now try again to
connect to this turntable they
tell me that connect reviews so that
means that well and the old port is unavailable that is
us h-service something happened to it
and now we can in with the help of k
boys in wish console as we remember
from so again in view wish console
id  2 we press again the center we
get our apses graphics where the system
offers to enter a login respectively
password
let's make sure that we have csa demons the
cocktail of active with hd
we see that inactive let's check that
api and sasha and tha 0ov
let it be 192 168 print packs 2
here is our api address to which we
actually now tried to connect well
let's run the service of the catelli systems
start sshd make sure that we have access
from the sinks typhus parasite okay and now let's make
sure that in the service we have to dry on
2 old ports
in case I will not use to the
boy on the quotes but I
will demonstrate one of the included in the
package and the first round service
called the ussr with is responsible just for
viewing all socket connections as for
dp therapy and beer 4 and beer 6 and so on further
further s4 from what does a beer
4 mean the key you denoting tise pi the key
means show all the services that are
listened to and accordingly the key and
display exactly in  hourly values
okay as we see we have by stan dries
port 22 actually ssh is available to us
now we can log out with you and
this is just press the counter with a bracket and
we are out now if
reset and now if we connect with you
all worth 2 168 122 19 as we see
we are all good here they are the last
commands that we had with you in
this case what friends if you
have questions about working with the console
if
some things are not clear to you write in the
comments but I tell you
subscribe put likes and as
always bye bye