well hello Internet and welcome to my
Lua video tutorial in this one tutorial
you're going to learn pretty much
everything you could ever want to know
about the Lua programming language and
in the description underneath the video
I have a cheat sheet that has everything
that I talk about in this tutorial and I
have a lot to do so let's get into it
okay so first thing you're going to want
to do is install Lua so you can either
install these binary files here you can
just go to lu- us.org
swiki slab binaries like like that or if
you're on Windows you could go to
code.google.com/ P Lua for Windows you
can use either one of those I am on OSX
doesn't really matter everything here is
going to be exactly the same no matter
what operating system you're on but you
can see right here is everything you're
going to need to install and you should
have no problem with that so let's start
writing some code okay so on the left
side of the screen I have where I'm
going to be inputting all the code basic
text editor Sublime on the right side I
have my terminal and if you are on
Windows this would be your command line
so let's just jump right in here and
you're going to have the extension of
Lua for all of your files and this is
just lu. Lua right like that and let's
do a Hello World so we're going to say
print hello world just that simple save
that jump over here and this is how
we're going to execute our programs just
Lua and then the name of your Lua file
and boom hello world so hello world is
out of the way that is how you would
print to the terminal now your you're
going to be able to make comments just
like this or you can make multi-line
comments like this you can see how they
popped up right there so multi line and
there we go comments are out of the way
now your variable names can't start with
a number but they are going to be able
to contain letters numbers and
underscore and we just create one right
like this basically Lua is going to
dynamically type based off of whatever
you save in this variable so this
automatically becomes a string because
this is a string right here and your
strings of course can either be double
quotes or you could have them be single
quotes doesn't really matter another way
for you to be able to print stuff out in
Lua is to go IO write like this and you
could say something like size of string
and then you could separate that if you
wanted to put the string inside of here
and on top of that let's say that we
also want to get the size or number of
characters in our string we would just
put a number sign and name in this
situation and then there's going to be a
bunch of things you can backslash this
is going to be a new line like this it's
just a short easy way for us to be able
to throw a new line in here which is
just going to skip us to the next line
and there's a couple other little
backslashes you can use there's a new
line of course you can also do a
backspace you could do a tab of course
you're going to need a way to be able to
print a backs slash inside of something
like IO right you're also going to be
able to print quotes double quotes like
this and also single quotes and those
would be used in situations of in which
you have double quotes here but you want
to put a double quote let's say right
here that would allow you to do that and
we need to do this because otherwise it
would not know where the string ended
and if we file save that execute it you
can see size of string is five it
automatically prints out for you now an
interesting thing here is even though
this is defined as a string currently we
can just as easily come in here and go
name is equal to four like that and that
is not an error so you'll be able to
start off as a string and then convert
the data or the variable over into an
integer we could then come in here and
say something like my name is and name
like that and you can see my name is for
comes out there no errors are thrown
other programming languages would throw
errors however now Lua only has floating
Point numbers or what they call just
simple numbers and the biggest integer
that you could store inside of Lua is
this gigantic guy right here and if we
can go and add one to that you're going
to see that indeed that is true so let's
go and try to print one more than what
we have there with big num like this and
you can see it comes back out as a
negative number so this is as big as it
gets in regards to integers you could
easily come in here and then check the
type of this variable by just
surrounding it with type and calling the
function type jump over here and you can
see big number prints out there and
number prints out right there so you can
see that everything integers or floating
Point numbers are all considered just
basic numbers inside of L now as we all
know floating Point numbers or as some
of us know anyway floating point numbers
are not necessarily precise so let's
come in here and check the Precision
basically with a floating Point number
you're going to have your digits be
precise up to 13 digits so that just
means like this 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11
12 like that and then we could come in
and add another digit to it so let's
just throw in 12 zeros and then tack
five onto the end of it and Float
precision and you can see that it is
precise indeed right to that point if
however we tacked on another additional
digit onto there and reran that you're
going to see that it lost Precision so
your floating Point numbers are precise
up to 13 digits which is normally more
than enough now let's say that we wanted
to come in here and create a string that
is going to go over multiple different
lines and at the same time also keep any
white space that you would type inside
of here you would just put those two
opening brackets like that and you can
type in I am a forever right like this
and you're going to see if we run this
that it's going to not only print out
the whole entire string but also pay
attention to any white space and any new
lines that would occur within that long
string let's go in here and throw in
another string there's my name if you
wanted to combine or concatenate strings
inside of Lua we could just go long
string like this is equal to and let's
just use long string here you would just
put two dots inside of there and name
take that throw that in here instead and
you can see that it went in there and
automatically tacked on the other string
just with this little operator that we
have right there just so we can cover
other data types that are available we
also have bullion so able to drive let's
say we wanted to monitor that and a
bullion is going to either allow us to
use a value of true or a value of false
and of course we could come in here and
also check the type of this so is able
to drive like this you can see it comes
back is bullan and another thing that's
a little bit odd about Lua it doesn't go
out of its way to try and show errors so
let's come in here and let's try and get
a type of made up variable so madeup
variable has been basically just created
right there in that line it's not been
defined with any value and you're going
to see right here that everything in Lua
by default gets the value of nil if it
does not get a value assigned
specifically by you inside of your code
so there's a rundown of a lot of what
you need to know about variables now
let's go and take a look at some math
functions okay so basic math functions
we have in little we can add subtract
multiply divide and this is the modulus
and let's just go ahead and save that
and execute it and you're going to see
exactly the results we're able to
produce here just pay attention that
this is a modulus operation right here
and not what is commonly known as a
remainder operator if it was a remainder
operator it would actually give the
value of 2.2 and this just is the
remainder of a division by three so what
it does is automatically cuts that off
just make you aware of that everything
else here is pretty straightforward in
regards to this basic mathematic
operations it's also important to know
that you cannot perform common shorthand
notation like let's say we had number
Plus+ can't do that you can't do
negative negative and of course if you
can't do those you're not going to be
able to use this or this just common
things that are in other languages that
Lua does not have currently and this is
version 5.3 of Lis so it's the most
current at least as I'm speaking right
here another thing you can't do is this
type of short notation
which is normally equivalent to number
is equal to number + 1 if you want to do
this inside of Lua you are actually
going to have to instead type that out
there's a whole bunch of built-in math
operations inside of Lua these are some
of the most common ones that you're ever
going to see see right here we have
floor ceiling Max Min s cosine da d da
da da and I'll show you some examples of
how all of those work here's a whole
bunch of math functions we're going to
check the flooring the ceiling the max
minimum power and square root see
exactly how all those operate the only
difference between floor and ceiling is
the floor is going to round this number
down ceiling is going to round it up and
you can see here Max is going to give
you the maximum min's going to give you
the minimum and there's power and square
root functions as well something that's
rather neat is using random numbers and
you will probably use random numbers a
lot in your programs let's go in here
and generate a random number right now
so let's just go IO right and you would
do that with math. random right like
this and let's say that we want to come
in here and generate a random number
between zero and one random and that is
all that we would do but that's a little
bit boring you may also have noticed
here there's no semicolons at the end
you could put semicolons in there but
they are not needed in any way let's go
instead and create a random number
between 1 and 10 you just come in here
type in 10 and then you could also come
in here and also Define random numbers
in very specific ranges so let's say we
wanted to go random number between five
and 100 there you go 5 and 100 5 and 100
and if you see if we execute those they
all work pretty simply another thing
that is kind of useful is we're going to
be able to set our seed value and that
is just going to help us calculate a
random value and how we do that is just
go math random seed and the best way to
do that is to use os. time right like
that and that is going to generate for
us a nice random value another thing
that is interesting is we can come in
here and print our float values uh in
other ways so let's just use print I'm
going to be bouncing around a lot just
to show you all the different ways we
can use these things if we wanted to
format a string we just go string format
and let's say that we wanted to get Pi
is equal to and then we wanted to import
directly into our string a value and
let's say that we wanted it to be 10
decimal places long f for float right
like this and we could also get the
value of pi by by calling the math
library right like this you're going to
see that we got the value of Pi to 10
digits automatically sorted out for us
also however be aware that this is only
going to have a Precision of 13 digits
anything over that and it's going to
start botching itself up and that's just
the way floating Point numbers work in
almost every programming language okay
so now that we got the math functions
out of the way let's take a look at
conditionals okay whenever we're using
conditional statements we're going to
have relational operators as well as
logical operators and the relational
operators going to be greater than less
than greater than or equal to less than
or equal to this is the funy one well
that's fine that's just equal but not
equal is actually going to be Tilda and
equal to very important to remember that
just Tilda and equal to this one right
here which you may be aware of is not
used and then your logical operators are
going to be and or or not spelled out
exactly like that and I'm going to
demonstrate how all of these work so
let's say you have an A AG which is
equal to 13 and let's take a look at if
statements and how they work now we're
going to be able to perform certain
operations depending upon the value of
age here we're just going to say if age
is less than 16 then make sure you put
then inside of there you're going to see
it automatically indents we're going to
say write and something like you can go
to school another thing to be aware of
is any variable that we would Define
inside of our if statements Force
statements functions so forth and so on
we to called local variables and that
just means that they are local to this
if statement and the value that is set
here cannot be found outside of the if
statement more on that here in a second
now if this if statement doesn't come
back as true maybe we want to check
something else so we would go else if
right like that no space between there
and then we could say something like age
is less than or equal to 16 and let's
say that we want to check a couple
things well this is where our logical
operators come in we can say and and we
can check check another one age is less
than or equal let's just make it less
than 18 like this then make sure we put
our then statement in there and then we
can come in here and print something
else out so we can say something like
you can drive and then finally as a
default we would use else throw
something else in there and you could
say something like you can vote another
thing that we have to remember is
anytime we have an if statement we
always want to use end there whenever it
is finished now let's jump back to this
guy as well well as also check out
exactly what goes on here if we would go
print like this and we would go local
variable we're going to see what happens
here let's load this you can go to
school but this comes back as nil like I
said once you to find a variable inside
of here a local variable this is inside
of the if statement and it cannot be
accessed anywhere outside of the if
statement and we're going to see more
about that later on just wanted to make
you aware of it now we come in here and
play around with logical statements a
little bit more more just so we can
check out how all of them work say we
want to check if age is less than 14 and
we could use or which is going to give
you a value of true and then operate
with whatever is after the then
statement if one or the other of these
is true could say age is greater than 67
like this and you could just keep on
going you could go iio right like this
just keep CH just keep typing
everything's going to work say like you
should
work and then we could continue on the
same line and then end and don't forget
to come in here and put an age in like
that and come up here and execute it and
you can see you shouldn't work comes
back because 13 is the value right here
this comes back as true which means that
we are going to print you shouldn't work
out onto the screen now you can do this
but it kind of gets sloppy so watch out
there just wanted to demonstrate how The
Logical operator works and also make you
aware that you may see people use really
sloppy long statements like that now
we're going to also be able to come in
here and format or convert from multiple
different variable types to other
different variable types so let's just
come in here and go print and string and
then use format again and I'm going to
demonstrate the not logical operator as
well so let's say not true what will
that do well I'm going to come in here
and if you want to put a string inside
of here you would just put a percent
sign and an S like that however we're
going to have to convert our bullan to a
string and how we do a cast or convert
to a string you can throw anything
inside here throw a number or whatever
and you can see right here the not true
part right there and if we save that you
can see that not true this logical
operator before the value of true is
going to give us a value of false and
you can also see how the bullan value
this guy right here was converted to a
string so we could use it inside of our
print statement now there is no Turner
operator inside of Lua and a tary
operator normally looks like something
like can vote is equal to age greater
than 18 like this and otherwise false
that's what a Turner operator looks like
in other programming languages and it
basically just says if age is greater
than 18 we want to assign the value of
true to the variable can vote otherwise
we want to assign the value of false to
the variable can vote so we can't do
that however we can pretty much knock it
off inside of Lua how we would do that
is go can vote is equal to and we could
go age is greater than 18 and true or
false so it looks very similar to the
tary operator and it works exactly like
the tary operator and we could say can I
vote and we can come in here and go to
string again and can vote let's change
this to can vote and you can see right
here the answer comes back as false so
there's an example of how we can use
conditional statements or if else and
else as well as knock off a tary
operator and it's also good to know that
there is no such thing thing as switch
inside of Lua but you can also basically
knock that off with if and else
statements now let's go and take a look
at some strings and ways that we can
work with them okay so I went and
created a really really long string
right here for us to be able to play
around with and I'm just going to do a
couple simple little string operations
that are common and then as the tutorial
continues I'll cover some more so let's
go and say that we wanted to do
something like get the quote length
right like this we could come in and go
Len and then throw quote inside of there
and then make sure we separate
everything with commas and you can see
right there the quote length comes back
at 111 characters and we can come in
here also and see that we can just go
like this and then throw the number sign
inside of there and get exactly the same
result this is the most common way to
check the number of characters that you
have in your string by the way you could
also come in here and replace certain
strings so let's say that we wanted to
replace I this is going to be bad
English but replace I with me for
example we could then go string dog sub
like this and then you're going to put
inside of there the string that you're
going to want to change and the value
that you're going to want to change and
then the value you're going to want to
replace that with so we'll say me and
said like that and always make sure that
you close off all of your brackets so
make sure you have a closing one for
this one and file save and execute
you're going to see right here replace I
with me and it went and changed all of
the versions of I and inside of this
great big giant string to me instead so
it says me changed my password to
Incorrect and da da da da da another
thing that we can do is find any
matching indexes everything inside in
regards to Strings is going to have an
index every character so this is going
to have the index of zero this space
right here is going to have the index of
one this is going to have the index of
two and we'll be able to search through
this grapic giant long quote and find
out exactly what the index is so we
could say something like index of the
word password and we're going to use
string doind and again we're going to
pass in the string that we are going to
be searching for and then the word that
we're going to be searching for which in
this situation is going to be password
and make sure we put a little common
side of there and you can see right here
index of password is 14 so that's 14
characters into our great big giant
along quote is the location of the word
password and two other little simple
things we can do let's say that we
wanted to make all of the characters
inside of our quote uppercase we could
just put string upper or lowercase we
could just go string. lower save that
execute and you can see right here made
everything uppercase and everything
lowercase now we're going to get more
into Strings here in a second but let's
go and jump in and take a look at
looping and how that works inside of Lua
I'm going to start off with a while loop
and what we're going to need to do is
initialize or create a variable that is
going to define the starting value that
we're going to be looping through and
then we're going to say something like
while I I the value of I is less than or
equal to 10 we want to continue looping
through or executing code inside of our
while loop so let's just say we got IO
right and we just want to print out the
value of I there you go and inside your
while loop you're of course going to
have to increment the value of I
remember we can't do something like this
not allowed you have to type everything
out and then let's also say that we
would want to jump completely out of
this Loop and not continue looping
through it anymore if for example I has
a value of 8 well then we're going to
say something like break and of course
we have to put an end right there that's
going to end our if statement but then
we're going to need another end that is
actually going to end our while loop and
then we could do something like print
and throw a new line in there you going
see if we execute that it's going to
print out 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 and it didn't
continue printing up until 9 and 10
because right here we said if it gets to
the value of eight we want to jump
outside of the loop and stop executing
all together also very important inside
of Lua to understand there is no
continue statement so you might be used
to that in other programming languages
but it's not going to work here another
thing we can do and this is more like
the common do wow Loop in other
programming languages we have something
else that is called the repeat statement
so we're going to say repeat and we're
going to continue to execute code inside
here as long as a condition is true and
let's come in here and also demonstrate
exactly how you can get user input from
somebody so we'll say enter your guess
like that we could then come down and
store inside of the variable guess
whatever they enter in the keyboard and
that is how easy it is to get keyboard
input just io. read and then you're
going to come down here and you're going
to define the condition that this is
going to continue looping now we are
going to want to convert the guess that
they made it's automatically going to be
stored at as a string so we want to
convert it into a number remember if we
want to convert two strings we type in
string like that but in this situation
we want to convert it into a number so
we're just going to put guest inside of
there and then we're going to say equals
to 15 so this is going to be a little
number guessing game in which it will
continue asking them for a guess until
they enter in 15 we type in that and
there we are enter guess you can say 10
and it's going to continue to ask until
15 is entered and then it's going to
exit so that is how to convert to
numbers and that is how to use the
repeat until or what is commonly known
as the do while but inside of Lua it's
known as repeat until now let's take a
look at four loops and they're a little
bit different what we're going to do
we're going to Define an iterator just
like we did with the while loop
previously and we're going to give it a
starting value then we're going to give
it an ending value and then we're going
to say how much should it increment each
time we're going to put a one inside of
there for that you could put a two you
put anything let's go and print the eye
statement you could also throw a break
statement in there as well and you can
go ahead and check out exactly how that
would work and you can see it just
cycled through there and printed out 1
through 10 right on on our screen now
what I'm going to do is this is a table
which we're going to talk more about
here in a second but it's basically like
an array in other programming languages
it's just going to be a variable that's
going to allow us to store multiple
different values inside of it and I
jumped ahead to this right now because I
want to show you how easy it is to cycle
through all of these different tables so
here we'll just go four and then we'll
say key k for the key let's just call it
key just so you can see and value
because everything in a table is going
to have a key in a value or it's going
to have an index by default if you do
not assign a key and we could say
something like pairs pairs doesn't
matter you can put anything you want
inside here it doesn't matter what the
name of that is and we could say months
and then we could say do like this and
then we could cycle through our table
just like we did cycling through indexes
and let's just say in this situation we
just want to print our values out to the
screen and of course we have to end our
for Loop right like this and of course
make sure that we put value inside of
there and not V and if we execute it
you're going to see that prints out all
of the different months with a space in
between each one of those months and of
course we're going to be able to do more
interesting things with tables and
things like that but this is just a
quick way for me to demonstrate all
those things and since I brought up
tables why don't we go take a look at
how a table works now basically as I
said tables are going to take the place
of arrays dictionaries tupes and such in
other programming languages and how we
can create a table is just go in here
and say something like a table and then
put two curly brackets like that there
you are there you have a table we could
come in here and add values to the table
using a for Loop so we can add them just
you know on their own but this is just a
quick way to throw a whole bunch of
values inside of there so we'll say a
table and everything is going to be
stored inside of an index so this is
going to increment through different
values of I and it is going to just
assign those values to I and this is the
index so the very first index in our
table is going to have the value of one
just like you see right there and then
of course we're going to end that and
we're going to be able to commit here
then and access those using the index
that we assigned so let's say we want
the very first value stored inside of
their index you're going to see that we
have one there once again because we
assigned it that way could also be zero
or could be anything else and you can
see first comes back as one right like
this so that's one way to access values
inside of a table you could probably
guess exactly how we would find out the
number of items that we have inside of
our table let's just come in here why
don't you guess okay time's up and let's
just put a number sign in table table
inside of there and that is exactly how
we're going to be able to access those
values and you can see number of items
is equal to 10 just like you may have
thought we could also come in here and
insert a value inside of a table we're
going to put table don't let this
confuse you a table is the table table
is the library we're going to use here
and if we want to insert a value we just
go table insert Define the table we want
to insert into we then Define the index
that we want to insert into and then the
value we would want to insert and there
you can can see it didn't do anything
let's go and print that out and you'll
see it go like this and first and let's
just let that set for one and we go like
this and now you can see the value of
the first index inside of our table is
now zero could also come in here and
change this to 10 you can see everything
was moved up as well so there's N9
instead of 10 which it would have
originally been set for we could also
come in here and take a table and
convert it into a string and then Define
how we want all the different items to
be separated let's just use print again
here how we would do that is table
concat concatenate or combine same thing
and table and then we could Define how
we want all those items to be separated
let's say we want to be separated with a
comma could do that come over here and
there we can see exactly how that prints
out you can also see the zeros in there
because we inserted it in there another
thing we can do with tables is remove an
item at a specific index we would just
go table remove and Define the table we
want to remove and the index we want to
remove from copy this just so we can
print this out again and you can see
went and removed the zero out of there
and we could also come in here and
create multi-dimensional arrays so let's
go multi or multi-dimensional tables
sorry about that again we're going to
create our table right like this and
we'll use a for Loop to come in here and
populate this whole entire thing so
we'll say 0 through 9 do then we'll go
multi-table like this we're going to
Define an index so we want to save
inside of there and that is also going
to be a table create another for Loop
that is going to also p populate this
guy so we'll go 0 through 9 again and do
and then a multi-table and we'll say I
and you're also going to be able to come
in here and pull values from these using
exactly the same thing let's say we want
to store them as strings two string I
and then we want to also throw I and J
inside of there just for the heck of it
and then we can go end and then finally
end this for Loop now we're going to be
able to come in and access the values
that are stored inside of there of
course by using the indexes as well so
let's say table and we wanted to get
whatever is being stored at the index of
0 0 inside of our multi-dimensional
array go like this or multi-dimensional
table sorry about that and we can get
zero and zero like this and you can see
it comes back as zero of course we could
come in here and go one and two save
that and you get one and two right like
that that's how everything is stored
inside of the multi-dimensional array
and like I said before we're going to
use pretty much the same exact format
for our for loop as you can see right
here to cycle through and print out all
of our items inside of our table make
this and you can see that every item is
printed out there right there on our
screen and exactly how they are
formatted go like that and you can see
the z0 index so this is the zero index
for both of them and the 01 and so forth
and so on and you can go through and
play with that and get a little bit more
aware of exactly how tables are set up
inside of Lua and exactly how to use
them so now let's jump over and take a
look at function functions okay so a
function is going to allow us to reuse
our code as well as better organize our
code and we are going to just create a
function by just typing in function and
we give it a name like get some
something like that and if you want to
pass values into a function to perform
operations on them we could do something
like number one and number two like that
and if you wanted to perform an
operation and then send it back to
whoever called for our function to
operate that is exactly how you would do
it and then you would type in end we
could then come in here and I'm bouncing
back and forth between using print and
the right command just to show you how
to use them and we could do something
like 5 + 2 is equal to if we want to put
a decimal inside of there we just put a
percent sign and a d like that and then
we would call our function with get sum
like that and then pass in five and two
separate with a comma and there you can
see our answer and exactly how we're
able to call that function now let's
come in and create another function
let's have this one called split string
and it's going to receive a string
passed into it we're then going to
create a string table like this see I
said I'm going to keep coming back to
all these different things want to
define a local variable inside of this
and then let's cycle through the string
and store anything except for spaces
inside of our table how would we do that
well we would go for and our string in
and then we would type in string. g
match and then pass in the string that
was passed into our function this guy
right here and then if we wanted to
basically capture all the strings up
until the point in which there is a
space what we're going to use is a
percent sign this is going to represent
the beginning of a string or a bunch of
characters or numbers or whatever that's
what this little carrot symbol
represents and then a percent sign an S
this is what is known as a regular
expression I have tutorials on regular
expressions and I'm probably going to do
another one here pretty soon so
basically what we're saying here is we
want to cycle through the string that
they pass into our function and we want
to start capturing characters up until
we reach a space and that is what we are
going to be storing inside of our string
table I'm going to see here as we
execute it exactly how that's going to
work so we're cycling through the string
we're going to go string table and I for
the index for our table and we're going
to be pulling out each of those strings
and storing them temporarily in a
variable named Str Str and then we're
going to save them to our table then all
we need to do is increment our value for
I and then end okay so we have all of
those set up and now let's also show you
how we can return multiple values from a
function we would just go return and we
can return our string table which is
going to contain a bunch of values but
then we could also send back the number
of matches the total number of words
that we found inside of our string and
maybe this might make more sense if we
typed in word right here and then and we
typed in word right here so either way
it works and that's the way it operates
then of course the end or function we
put end and then we'd be able to return
or receive those multiple values that
are returned from this function right
here called split string by just going
split let's just say string table so
this value right here is going to be
stored in this guy right here and then
the number of strings inside of there or
a number of words whatever you want to
call it and then we just call our
function like this and let's just keep
it simple and let's just say something
like turtle let's just pass in two of
those guys we could then come in here
and cycle through everything that was
passed back inside of that table go one
again number of strings we're going to
keep cycling through there this is the
maximum number of strings and that's the
maximum amount we're going to Loop
through two and then we could print out
on the STR on the screen let's go and
format this guy and we can print our
index separated by the individual words
that we also pass back inside of there
so let's get J and then we'll go split
string table this guy right here and
then throw the index inside of there
then final thing we have to do of course
is end our for Loop and if you went
inside of there you can see that it
returned the and turtle and then nil
there's always an extra little nil
inside of there whenever we create
tables and we could of course get rid of
that by just going number of string
minus one and you can see that it just
prints out the and turtle so that's how
to go in call A function how to have it
return multiple different values how to
split a string into a table and how to
return that value over here and save it
into multiple different variables and
then cycle through it so there's a whole
bunch of different ways we can use
functions inside of Lua let's go and
talk about vertic functions this is how
we're going to be able to receive an
unknown number of parameters inside of
our functions again just create a
function and let's just call this get
some more if we don't know how many
different parameters or attributes or
whatever that could be sent inside here
we're just going to put three little
dots inside of there and we can do
something like local sum is equal to
zero we could then come in and go four
and this is the key and this is the
value once again in pairs this is going
to be passed in here as a table then
we're going to put curly brackets 1 2 3
it's going to automatically just keep
cycling through there depending upon the
number of attributes or parameters that
were passed inside and we go sum is
equal to sum plus whatever value was
passed inside of course end that with an
end then after it's done go return the
total sum and then close off the
function and then we could print all
this out on the screen call get some
more you're going to be able to pass as
many things in here as you could
possibly ever want to let's just keep it
as six and it gave me a little bit of an
error you can see right here get sum I
can type in some more like that and
there we go sum is equal to 21 so that's
how we're able to pass in an unknown
number of parameters and then use it now
now another thing is kind of interesting
inside of Lua is a function is a
variable in that we can store them under
variable names as well as we store
tables and we can also pass and return
them through function so let's
demonstrate that let's say double it
there is a variable we can actually put
a function inside of this so let's say
it gets a value of x and then we can
just say return x * 2 and then put the N
function on there so we have basically
just made double it a function it is a
variable also however you can see right
here if we just go print and double it
like this and then pass in a four so
automatically going to pop out an eight
now going along those same lines a
closure is a function that can access
local variables of an enclosing function
so let's go and let's create one so
let's go function let's just call this
outer Funk because this is going to be
an outer function that is going to
contain our closure you're going to see
exactly why this is interesting so let's
create a local variable I equal to0 and
then let's put an inner function inside
of it so return function like this and
then inside of this guy let's go and
increment the value of I and then return
so this is a function inside of a
function this is a closure and the
reason why it is a closure we have to
end this and we also have to end this
one now whenever you include an inner
function in a function that inner
function is actually going to remember
any changes made to the variable inside
of the inner function now let's go and
let's store our function inside of a
variable called GI I so we'll go outer
Funk like that so there we stored it
inside of there now what we're going to
be able to do is go print get I like
that and it's a function and then do
exactly the same thing again reason why
this is a closure is you're going to
actually continue to increment and store
the changing values of I that are inside
of here as you're going to see right
here and there you can see value of I is
is starts off off as one but then
whenever it's called a second time it is
going to increment it even though we
assign the value of zero right there so
that's an example of a closure and
exactly how they work and how they store
values as they are being called multiple
different times so now let's go and take
a look at a similar thing which is
called a co- routine now a co- routine
is very similar to a thread in other
programming languages except that they
cannot run in parallel and a co- is
either going to have a status of running
suspended dead or normal and you're
going to see what all those look like so
let's create a Cod routine how you do
that is by just coming in here and going
Co routine and we're going to say create
and inside of this I'm going to put a
function and then inside of this I'm
going to say 4 I is equal to 1 give it a
starting value and 10 is going to be the
ending value and one is going to be the
increment and then inside of this we're
going to say print I value of I and also
let's go print Cod routine status just
so we can see the changing statuses from
running suspended dead or normal how we
do that is pass in COD routine name
inside of there close that off and we
can say something like if I is equal to
5 then and if we want to pause or yield
over to another co- routine we just type
in co- routine yield and then we're
going to end our if statement and on the
next line we will end our for Loop and
then on the next line we will end and
our Co routine so there we go have all
those saved maybe it makes a little bit
more sense come in here and go like this
and like that now if we want to come in
here and check our co- routine and see
what its status is whenever it very
first starts we'll just go co- routine
status like that and Co exactly like
this and you can see it starts off as
suspended now we can call for this Co
routine to resume or start executing and
then we can come in here and also check
the status after we tell it to start
running and you can see starts off as
suspended starts coming out here and
printing out all these numbers and comes
right up to five and you can see it's
also technically running right there
that's the status until it hits five and
the reason why is it says if I is equal
to 5 we want to yield this co- routine
and stop its execution now let's come in
here and create another code routine
that we're going to run at the same time
very much like we would do with threads
it's equal to code routine and we're
going to create one and this one's going
to go function create a function right
inside here here create another for Loop
we go I is equal to 101 can start it off
at 101 and have it count to 110 and
increment by one and do and print
whatever the value of I is each time and
then end our for loop as well as end our
code routine and now we can see that if
we go in here again and go code routine
resume like this let's just have this be
CO2 like that but then also do exactly
the same thing or restart or continue
execution inside of our original code
routine that we created and you can see
the process here starts off as suspended
gets up to five running then it gets
suspended jumps over to the other co-
routine which doesn't get suspended or
doesn't have to yield its time at all
goes through its entire process and then
whenever we call the code routine to
continue execution you can see that it
continues executing until it is finally
dead and you can see right here if we
come in and get the status of this code
routine right here it is in fact dead
after it has done or executed all the
code inside of it so there's an overview
of cod routines now let's take a look at
something that a lot of people are
confused about because there's not much
good information online about it and
that is file IO now there's many
different ways that we're going to be
able to operate on files and you can see
all the different ways right here we're
going to either be able to have the file
set as readon which is the default we're
going to either overwrite or create a
new file a which means we're going to
append or create a new file if this is
used this is used for for read and write
of an existing file overwrite read or
create a new file and then append read
or create a new file I'm going to come
in here and actually start opening files
and storing things inside of them so we
can see exactly how this operates if we
want to create a new file that we're
going to be working with we just go IO
open right like this and then we're
going to give it a name let's say I'd
call this test Lua like that and let's
say that I want to have the opportunity
to create a new file CU I know this
doesn't exist right now and then I want
to also be able to overwrite and read
from that file so I'm going to just use
that guy right there cuz that works for
all the things I want to be able to do
and there you go you just created a file
and you're able to write to it and read
from it and also make it now if we want
to come in here and write some text to
the file we just go file write and then
we'll say random string of text and we
can use new lines inside of here for our
files as well and let's say we want to
put some more stuff in there so we'll
say write again and we'll just say
something like some more
text throw another new line inside of
there we can use seek now to move back
to the beginning of our file by going
file seek like this and then we're going
to type in set and then the index where
we want to jump because everything is
indexes inside of string so we want to
jump back to the beginning of our file
and that's how we do that and then if we
want to go and read everything from our
file we'll just go file read right like
this and then we'll put a star inside of
here and an a meaning that we want to
read everything from our file okay so we
wrote to our file we created our file we
jump back to the beginning of our file
and we're going to read everything from
that point final thing we need to do is
close our file and there we go and it
popped up a little bit of an error I
keep the errors inside here just want to
make sure we put our quotes inside of
there because I think whenever you see
me make an error that's going to help
you keep from making errors and you can
see right there printed out random
string of text and some more text right
like that now let's say that we wanted
to come in here and also continue
working with our file but we want to
append data to the end of our file how
do we do that well we can just leave
this named as file because Lua is real
nice about stuff like that and we'll
just say IO open and again we're just
going to type in the name of the file
that we want to work with and then in
this situation I want to append so I'm
going to say A+ like that I can of
course come in and write some new
information to our file and let's just
say even more text again remember you if
you want to read from a file you have to
jump back to the beginning of it so
we're going to use seek to do that and
we're going to say set and then we're
going to say exactly where we want to
jump to you can put any index in here to
jump around all over inside of the file
and then we can say print and of course
we're going to read data from our file
and we want to get all of that data
inside of there right like this and then
finally we want to close our file and if
we do all that you can see random string
text and then some more text comes in
there and then even more text gets
printed out on our screen so that is how
we're going to be able to work with our
files inside of Lua now let's take a
look at modules okay so basically a
module is like a library that is full of
functions and variables and you're going
to be able to create it and then use it
inside of your program so let's go and
let's create a module so we'll just come
in here and go new file and I am going
to save this guy using the name convert.
Lua of course and then save that so
let's create create a module it's very
important that your module name and your
file name are exactly the same and to
create one I'm going to go local convert
the name of this guy and there is our
module and then inside of this I can put
a function let's say I want to do
something like convert feet to
centimeters so we'll go Feet 2 cm and
this function is going to receive an
attribute of feet and then it is going
to return whatever that value is times
30.48 I think that's right and n and and
then you also need to return the module
and save it and that is how we're going
to do it just make sure we have convert
here convert here and convert here very
important and also the name of the file
has to be converted or convert well now
we can come over and do something like
convert module doesn't need to be named
convert module name it whatever you want
and if you want to be able to get access
to that they have to be in the same
directory of course we're going to say
require and convert right like this and
then we'll be able to come in here and
work with this module function this this
and let's say that we want only three
decimal places that's how we do that
with a floating Point number and there
is centimet and then if we want to call
our module just convert module just like
we created right there and then follow
that with feet to CM which is the name
of the function we have in the module
and we can pass in a value of 12 and you
can see it gets back the answer of
42.4 CM so there's a quick example of
how we can work with modules inside of
Lua now let's take a look at meta
tables now a meta table is going to
allow us to Define how operations on
tables should be carried out in regards
to adding tables together subtracting
multiplying dividing concatenating
comparing tables and so forth and so on
so let's come in and create a table and
put some default values in it so I'm
just going to go a table like this and
create my little table and then I'm
going to use a for Loop to jump through
here and just fill it up with stuff
let's just say 1 through 10 two and and
a table and of course we're going to use
the same indexes here and just store
whatever the value is inside of there of
course close that off so there we go we
got a table now we're going to Define
our meta table and how we're going to do
this is go Mt and then we're going to
Define how table values should be added
and you're going to be able to Define
like I said before adding you're going
to be able to also Define how table
should be subtracted how they should be
multiplied how they should be divided
how they should be if you want to use
the modulus and how they should be
combined which is the same as this guy
right here which we've talked about
previously I'm just going to focus on a
couple of these so I'm going to go add
there's two spaces right here by the way
there's two underscores all right so
we're going to Define how these are
going to be added together we're going
to go function and we're going to say if
you pass in table one two tables I'm
going to Define here exactly how they
are going to be added together I'm going
to create a sum table like this which is
going to be the table that is going to
be returned and I'm going to go 4 Y is
equal to 1 and I'm going to cycle
through the number of tables that we
have right here and just do that for me
and then let's say that I want to also
come in here and check to make sure that
the table values are not equal to nil
well I can just go table one like that
and get the value of that is remember
it's not it's the Tilt sign not equal to
nil can do that and both of these have
to be true for this to work I can say
table two and then also put the Y inside
of there not equal to nil well then I
will do some stuff well make sure that
we put this guy over here close that off
and then put then there we are open this
up a little bit better what am I going
to do if I got what I need here well I'm
going to start adding stuff to the sum
table so sum table the value is going to
be stored inside of the same exact index
is going to be equal to and this is just
what I decided how I want to you can
decide how you want to add table values
anyway but this is the way that makes
logical sense to me so table two so I'm
going to take the values that's in one
and two and then store them inside of a
brand new table this guy right here else
let's say that one of these came back as
nil what do I want to do in that
situation well I want to say Su table Y
and let's say that I want to store zero
inside of there I make the rules in this
situation so that's how it's going to
work because that's how I decided it'll
work and we want to close off our if
statement and we want to close off our
four statement and then after we have
created our brand new table with all
those sums inside of it I want to return
that guy right there and then I want to
end this I'm going to say end and I'm
going to put a comma right after that
now I can also come in here and Define
how table values are going to be checked
for equality and how we can do that is
to underscores again put EQ inside there
is equal to fun
and I can go table one and table two
like this and then I can just go return
table one get the value inside of it and
make sure that it is equal to table two
and get the value out of that as well
and if both of those come back then we
know that that is going to work for us
then of course we have to come in here
and we want to end this guy right here
so we go end and a comma another thing
we can do is we can also check if it is
less than and I'm going to let you use
that as your homework assignment to
figure out exactly how to make sure that
these values work for whether a table is
less than or also if it's less than or
equal to another object right there and
then also figure out exactly how
subtraction and multiplication and
division works hint hint hint it's going
to be something very very similar to
this guy right here okay so now that we
have our meta table all set up we need
to attach The Meta methods to our table
how you do that is go set meta table and
and there's the table we're going to
assign it to and there is our meta table
so met set meta table right like that
and then we can come in and check if
they were equal so a table is equal to a
table that's going to work of course and
had a little bit of a bug up here in the
a table change that to uppercase right
like that and then down here inside of
the equality check make sure that those
are equal fix that and if we do that and
execute you're going to see that this
comes back as true just as you may have
thought with this right here and now
we're going to test what we did in
regards to adding tables so we're going
to create a new table called add table
and then we can go add table is equal to
and then we'll just pass in a table we
can pass in different ones but it
doesn't really matter and a table and
you've seen this before we can just
create a simple for Loop that's going to
allow us to cycle through our new ad
table we just created right here and
whenever we execute it it's going to add
all those values together in our brand
new table and print them out on the
screen so there's meta table and meta
methods and how we can work with them
now let's take a look at objectoriented
programming or at least Louis version of
object-oriented programming okay so just
so to make this very clear Lua is not an
oop language and it doesn't allow you to
Define classes but you can in some ways
fake it using tables and meta tables so
what we're going to do here is we're
going to create an animal table right
like this and I'm going to Define all
the default values for everything inside
of it so we'll have a height and a
weight equal to zero and we'll also have
a name the default name is going to be
no name and then we'll also have our
animal type of objects also have a sound
let's just have no sound okay so there
is the table we have created for animal
or the object that we were trying to
create inside of here now we have to
define a function for our table that's
going to allow us to initialize this guy
and how we do that is with function
animal and I'm going to give it the name
of new and it is going to receive a
height a weight a name and a sound very
similar to an objectoriented programming
language what we're going to have to do
now is set our meta table and we're just
going to throw in a junk table right
there and then animal right there so
that's how simple it is to create that
meta table now if we want to refer to
height weight name and sound for our
animal objects we use self cuz we don't
know know what the name of it is so
we're going to say like this and we'll
just go and create that then we need to
do that for all of the other different
attributes we want for our animal
objects so we're also going to have
weight and change this to weight and
then we're going to have name and then
finally sound so we're creating it in
very similar ways to what you have seen
in other programming languages and this
is going to initialize and create a new
animal object and after it initializes
everything it's going to return that
animal object of course and the function
with end say we wanted to come in here
and also create a function that is going
to allow us to print out information
about our animal object let's call it
two string it's not going to receive
anything and we can then go animal
string like this and string this is
another way of using string format that
I haven't showed you and we could just
go sign s ways and then let's get a
weight for our animal pounds is s on F
Ines tall and says and let's get the
sound that it's going to make then if we
want to import all those things for our
specific animal object we're going to go
and get the self name and self weight
and self height and then whoops make
sure we do this right self height like
that and then finally self sound so that
is a way for us to import all of those
specific things for our animal into the
two string function here and then we can
just just go return animal string and
end that function so this is an object
function inside of here and this is how
we initialize it and this is all the
defaults and The Meta table we Define
for it so it's all very very similar to
things we've seen in the past so let's
go and create an animal object let's
call it spot how we do that is we would
go animal and we call our initialization
function and let's just pass some junk
values inside of here there's his name
and then his sound let say a sound is
Wolf because that makes sense okay so we
just called for our animal object to be
initialized we could then come in and go
print spot weight like that and then we
could also go print spot and then if we
want to call the function we just go to
string like this two string it doesn't
have to have that name it's just the
name I gave it that said it was
unexpected let's put this quote inside
here that should fix it and there you
can see it works so 15 comes out that is
how we're accessing the weight with the
dot operator right like this and then we
can call that function which is
automatically going to get all that
information about spot and print it
right there on our screen so you may ask
yourself well does inheritance work
inside of Lua well yes it does and this
is how we're going to use it so let's
say we want to create a brand new object
called cat we can inherit all of the
functions defined inside of our animal
object just by calling new right like
this there we go now we have all we have
the two string we have the height weight
name and sound all that St stuff inside
of our new cat object we can of course
come in here and overwrite any of the
functions so one of the functions we
want to overwrite let's say we want to
overwrite new and how it works inside of
our new cat objects well we're just
going to come in here and replace animal
with cat and let's say that our cat
objects are also going to store in
favorite food and not just height weight
name and sound well we're going to set
our meta table here to be cat instead of
animal and then the only thing we need
to change down here is to come down and
grab this guy right there throw that
down and let's get favorite food and
let's also store that inside of it right
like this and it's going to return and
everything's going to work exactly the
same we could then also come in here and
override our uh two string function if
we'd like let's go and get this remember
we just changed this cat new instead of
animal new throw that right there and
we're going to do the same sort of thing
for two string we're going to say cat
two string and then how this guy is
going to change is we're we're going to
say something like says whatever and
loves and let's get his favorite food
inside of here so there that is we'll
just go self favorite food and now let's
come down and create a cat so let's call
it fluffy and we'll just call it with
cat new just like we did before and
let's just keep it simple 25 fluffy
fluffy says meow of course and Fluffy's
favorite food is tuna and of course
we're going to be able to come in here
and go print fluffy two string call that
function and you can see fluffy weighs
15 lbs 10 in tall and says meow and
loves tuna so there you go guys there is
a ton of information about Lua hope you
guys found that interesting of course in
the description is a link to all the
code and a cheat sheet as well as links
to all of the individual pieces I talk
about about Lu so please leave your
questions and comments below up next CP
otherwise till next time