it works on my machine have you ever
heard those words it works on my
computer over here but not on your
computer over there and the reason will
turn out to be some subtle difference in
the way we've got our machines set up
and I don't know what it is but
apparently it's important so we have to
dig down and find out and eventually
this is going to end with someone
updating the readme to say "You must
have OpenSSL version 3.2 to installed
first and no one actually ends up
reading that read me so the problem
keeps coming up but at least you can say
it's there in the
docs to be fair that's probably the
worst case things have got better since
those dark days because generally now we
solve the different environment problem
by shipping the entire operating system
to everyone that needs to use it as
defined by a Docker file
docker has become the tool of choice for
reproducible environments and it's been
really great in practice it has worked
out terrifically well i personally think
it works a bit better in production than
in development for production it's
generally quite reasonable to ship a few
different virtual machines it's never
sat entirely comfortably with me in dev
because if I need access to three or
four quite different programs I
shouldn't really have to run three or
four different virtual operating systems
in Docker Compose that always seemed
weird to me and generally I don't
actually there's a different approach I
use that isn't Docker but that solves
the reproducible environment problem and
ends up feeling a lot more like you've
just got everything installed locally so
this week I'm joined by Juliani and
we're going to talk about Nyx which
started life as a PhD thesis in how you
make builds reliable and has grown into
this tool that can define and build just
about any programming environment you
need i use it I use it basically every
day on every project I have and I find
it's particularly good if you end up
jumping between a few different projects
that all need different environments so
this week Julian's going to unpack what
Nyx is how it works and why you might
want to add it to your toolbox or
actually more specifically why you might
want Nyx to become the box you hold your
tools in i'm your host Chris Jenkins
this is developer voices and today's
voice is Julian
Arie i'm joined today by Julian Anie
julian how are you doing out there i'm
doing great thanks for asking
got you here you're over in Basil in
Germany basil basil it's pronounced
Basil basil on it's it's in Switzerland
on the border exactly on the border with
uh France and Switz and Germany so if I
go for a run uh it doesn't have to be a
long run it can be a 5k run um I can
cross into the three different countries
right past the country that's cool do
you have to take your passport uh
officially yes but I don't think anyone
does and I I never
have the freedom of movement that I've
lost but let's not get into Brexit
that's a different
podcast so you're here to talk about
building things
DevOps a topic sometimes I shy away from
cuz I found it so painful in the past
understandably yeah but but there's So
maybe I should tell you my background
just for a change
i worked at a company that used Nyx many
years ago as a contractor and they
basically paid me to learn Nyx because
they because I had to right so I've
always felt that I've come at Nyx from a
strange angle the the initial hump being
paid rather than voluntary yeah yeah so
and mandatory that was the other thing i
never had the here's why it's good i
just got told by dictat I should use it
so I'm hoping you can start by filling
in the why is Nick's good question
exactly so that I can convince all the
other people who are not being forced
and paid to do it to take a look at it
yeah um I think uh you know the sort of
space that it's operating in is the the
space of sort of reproducibility right
making sure that works on my computer
works on yours as well
um and that's a space that we as
developers are very familiar with and we
have our techniques to solve it right i
think uh Docker is is is maybe is by far
the most popular one u but
u Nyx is coming at the same problem um
from a very different angle
um
and and as a consequence it doesn't have
a lot of the problems that Docker has
which is actually you know to some
extent most obviously that it's not that
reproducible um if you want to you know
run the same Docker file twice and it's
not cached you could get very different
results but then additionally number of
other things it's hard to sort of
abstract over them it's hard to connect
multiple uh docker files together
combine them you end up spending so much
time um when you have docker images sort
of poking holes at their isol at the
isolation so that they can talk to one
another it's very different than the way
in which you program locally right like
usually you know if you think about the
Unix philosophy you have a pipe operator
between two different programs and
that's how you compose them whereas if
you have Docker images you suddenly have
to have HTTP ports and make them into
web applications or whatever whatever
mechanism it is it's very different than
than how you traditionally locally think
of programs and so there are all these
costs that are associated with with the
Docker model that aren't there in Nyx um
and additionally there are lots of
things that it enables that you wouldn't
even think are possible right so I think
um some of the things that are are quite
phenomenal is just the sort of uh the
sort of incredibly sophisticated build
caching that it has um and
um and you know with with once you sort
of start using Nexos the sort of which
hopefully we'll have time to get into
definitely
the it gets even even more exciting I
think right like you can sort of see uh
roll back sort
of get your machine to any any any state
very precisely um and know exactly what
state that is be able to diff machines
in in incredible detail
um with your usual sort of version
control tools um
cuz definitely Docker files sometimes
feel like a bit of a black hole
yeah the you know it in some sense it's
a it's a very nice interface the Docker
file that it's a very familiar interface
on the one hand right like you write a
essentially a bash script it's a little
bit different than a bash script but you
write a bash script and and then you
know it's like it's cached and you know
kind of isolated um and it's that that
sort of initial experience is very very
nice but then uh but then as you start
progressing beyond that first you know
those first five minutes it it becomes
cumbersome in a variety of different
ways yeah i think one of my least
favorite is that if you add a command to
a Docker file everything's groovy if you
want to go back and change an earlier
one suddenly you're in a real buildtime
problem right yeah that linearity is
very strange right like in some sense
the the caching is is linear right and
so uh uh you have to think very
carefully about the order in which you
do things and as you said if you change
something early on it might have
downstream consequences because you know
maybe you're downloading something
something from the internet and the
cache version that you had so far
changed and now um and now everything
else is going to be different as well
right so you're kind of in this Yeah
yeah yeah
so I think we should build up the
picture of how this all works and then
we can really talk about it so what's it
doing that Docker isn't what's the
what's the mental model for next yeah uh
Docker uh in some sense is you know
taking a snapshot of the file system at
a moment in time right you just take a
picture of whatever it is whatever state
it is that you got got into after
running a few commands and you save that
um and there's a story about layered
file system and whatnot but that's but
that's essentially the the approach
right yeah snapshot the whole OS call
that a base and then keep adding
snapshot changes on top yes exactly yeah
um Nyx is is much closer to a different
technique that is also very familiar uh
which is the package lock files right so
we we uh what I mean this by this is you
know you have language specific uh
tooling such as cargo or npm um that
nowadays or you know python pip uh or
the various other python tools um that
take you know your project and uh maybe
some some version bounds of dependencies
that you specified and talk to the
internet find out uh what versions are
available that match match what you
requested uh pick those versions and
then output that into a lock file what
versions it's picked now yeah to pin the
specific binary or the specific source
code exactly exactly so you can think of
this as what's happening is you know
after you've pinned this um the process
of dependency resolution with that lock
file is deterministic meaning it will
always be the same because you pinned it
you know prec very precisely not just a
version number because sometimes
uh you can change the meaning of a
version number uh but also the hash very
often right like it's a specific source
hash of so then after that if anyone
else tries installing it they'll get
exactly the same version um yeah because
it's usually p it's often pinned off git
which means it's cryptographically
secure all the way back through the
source code so you get bite for bite
exactly the same exactly the same
and so this is kind of you know that
lock file um is if you take that lock
file and extend it in two different ways
you get something that's that's
essentially the next idea right
um the first one is that you extend it
to everything right like it's not just
for a specific uh language language
dependencies right like it's not just
for your Go dependencies or just for
your npm dependencies it's for
everything it's for all your different
language dependencies all parts of your
projects your system libraries um your
various you know like maybe images or
whatever you're downloading from the
internet everything that uh you know is
speak is outside of this isolated
sandbox that you need to fetch ahead of
time um including for instance you know
the the UTC time or or or all of those
things everything that could go matter
to your build you're pinning
um yeah cuz if like you and I build the
same Rust project because of the block
file we get exactly the same cargo
dependencies we might have a different
version of lib opensl exactly or zlib or
or whatever else it is right or or a
runtime binary that you use right that
you're expecting to be there that's not
a rust uh project right yeah yeah uh
maybe you use core utils or something
like that right
or Yeah and often with languages you
even sort of you know you pin all the
versions down but you don't pin exactly
the compiler version or something like
that right like somehow the the domain
in which these lock files operate is
just the library versions
someone says it doesn't build on my
machine and you say well which OS are
you on which version of rest have you
got yeah and then you start waiting
through those reads even and that what
you mentioned is is a really good
reminder right like even another thing
that's down um is the OS version or
whether your architecture is 64 bits or
32 bits or whether it's an Intel or ARM
uh mic or Linux right uh all of those
things are pinned down um so that you
know like really
conceptually if you build it twice even
without C even without caching you'll
get exactly the same thing now I say
conceptually because there are small
exceptions that maybe we can get into at
some point um but that's but that's
number one right you you start with lock
files but you're going to pin down
everything right um
and then the other thing that I think is
a is a very very big deal is once you've
done
this you can use
um you can use when you build your
project right so you have you pin down
not just the Rust dependencies not just
the Go dependencies maybe you have a
multi- language project in a mono repo
that involves various different uh
languages you pin all of this down and
you ended up with a binary
the cool thing here is that you can give
it usually you know you you you might
end up with out or some some binary
version like that or my project and
that's the name of the binary but what
you could also do is name that binary
the hash of all of those inputs your
lock file plus your source code right
the lock file that includes everything
else that's not your source code and
your source code right yeah so you get a
cryptographic signature of that specific
binary yes yes and so now you have a a
very good name to refer to that binary
and you can have various different
versions of the binary coexist right so
you build that for instance and then you
check out a different branch and you
build it and now you'll have two
different binaries with two different
names and they won't overwrite one
another usually when you do a cargo
build or npm build or or whatever it is
you you you will overwrite whatever
binary you had previously built uh
because there's a a specific name there
that that keeps changing and that has
you know if anyone was using that binary
now they have they'll have a different
version right yeah whereas with mix you
you tend to use these names and there's
there's there's a lot of infrastructure
around making it easier to refer to
software without having to explicitly
mention these hashes uh but that's you
know you're going to name everything
this way um and so various different
versions of of
of binaries of artifacts can coexist
without a problem right you do this for
directories as well so when you do a
system upgrade in Debian or whatever
operating system it is that you have
usually you'll overwrite the version of
Python that's in user bin or wherever it
is
sometimes with immediate regret exactly
go back and use it yeah yeah whereas
here you know my project can say "Oh I
want exactly this version of Python
that's known by this hash." And then
it'll never never as long as someone's
using that version it'll never get
deleted but you can upgrade your OS and
it'll just install a different version
of Python alongside it with a different
hash name yeah you know I've used this
to great advantage specifically when
I've been uh contracting for different
clients and you've got like one client
that's on this version of the JVM and
another that's on that version and you
want like maybe they have different
underlying C libraries and you want both
versions to coexist on your laptop so
you can work for both clients without
going insane it becomes trivial right
yeah yeah and this is this is where one
of the superpowers of Nyx that it's
quite famous for and readly so comes
from right this this notion of dev
shells um we have we have a little bit
of this uh sorry we have a little bit of
this with
um with virtual ends and things like
that that allow you to sort of enter in
again in very limited ways enter a
specific Python environment with a
particular version of Python installed
and whatnot but Nyx again does this for
everything right so you can now create
development shells that are um that have
all of your all all the versions that
you want installed and what that does is
it just sim links into your path the
specific Python version you know they
have a hash python/ash or whatever hash
um and you just sim link that as Python
into your dev environment um when you
enter it um and then nonsim link that or
remove it from your path um but you know
you're never deleting anything or
overwriting it you're just sort of
entering an environment that exposes a
specific version of each of those things
under the path so that then you can
develop with the version of Python that
you want with a version of cargo and
rust C or whatever it is that you want
um and and this you know this is one of
the great joys is you know you can
create a project um in at work or in
your open source project make a dev
shell specify the details of a dev shell
for it in Nyx and people who come along
instead of needing to sort of read
through a read me um and carefully try
to emulate everything can just do a Nyx
develop and enter that devshell with all
the tools that they need to build and
test and yeah yeah I I have I thought in
the past when you've got like
installation instructions that are more
than just build the language project
you've also got to install these
dependencies first
that's where like that should have been
next or something very similar right
yeah yeah also because it's you know
it's not just hard to sometimes hard to
follow those instructions but it's also
sometimes I mean I think very often hard
to write them correctly right because
you don't
know the dependencies of your project
are very often implicit right like you
don't know whether your project is or
you've forgotten whether you're using
zlib or or whether a particular version
of bash has to be installed versus
another because you know you have uh you
know some particular syntax that's only
available in bash 4 or up or whatever it
is right yeah yeah this is another thing
you get with Nyx which is the isolation
which gives you an environment that
doesn't include the things you're used
to having on your laptop yeah yeah
exactly so that you know exactly what it
is that matters right like it's uh being
able to empty empty your environment is
really important to understanding what
it is that you actually need right yeah
yeah so I'm sure I've hit that with
something like image magic it's like oh
yeah you also need to install image
magic i hadn't put that in the
instructions cuz I've always got it
installed yeah yeah yeah exactly and I
hadn't thought about it yeah okay
so I think I think there's if you if
someone has bought into the argument
that like a cargo.lo file or a package
lock file or something like that is a
good idea we could go deeper and apply
that to all the surrounding stuff for
the language the question is how how
does Nyx do it and what will it cost me
to start using it yeah
uh you know fundamentally uh what what
what the experience of you know I think
the the fundamental sort of unit of uh
uh nyx is a build derivation you know I
won't go into details about that
terminology yet but um fundamentally you
know a recipe for how to build a project
is is and then actually building it is
is what Nick cares about and the way
which does that is by isolating the
build environment in sandboxing it so
that you don't have
um don't have uh anything that you
didn't specify right so and then there
you specify usually something like a
bash uh and this way it's you know
somewhat similar to to docker you
specify a little script that says this
is how you will build my project um you
know maybe it's cd into this directory
and and do a cargo build or a make or
whatever it is right
and there's a little recipe there but
it's running in without network access
um without access to the rest of the
file system that's not your repository
or main directory so it's not
accidentally picking up hidden inputs
that you hadn't thought about exactly um
you won't have a version of Python at
all unless you say I want a version of
Python and then you have to say what
version this is right yeah yeah
um and and so then you have this recipe
that you know uh can be run by someone
else that will you know next will again
um do do exactly the same thing isolate
you know create an isolated sandbox um
and then run this recipe right um making
sure that any dependencies that you
specified are in fact available to it
right so if you said I want this version
of Python and this version of cargo then
those things will be available but
nothing else
will Yeah that's that's that's how it
kind of operates but uh you know there's
also this sort of surface level language
and the same way with with the docker
file there's there's this semi bash
syntax you know um in next there's also
next language that's the equivalent
right so it's you you write these little
data structures that explain your build
recipe right and most obviously what
that contains is the script that will do
the building and then also the
dependencies right so you you specify
packages just bash or whatever
um and that will add those things to uh
to your dependencies so one thing I've
always wondered and never actually
looked into maybe you know the answer to
this but if I want to build my Rust
project Mhm i will specify one of my
dependencies is Rust the language so Nyx
will go off to the recipe to build Rust
the language and it will find that one
of the dependencies is GCC let's say
yeah and goes off for the recipe for GCC
it finds one of the dependencies to that
is a specific kernel how far back does
it go what's the if it's turtles all the
way down what's the base turtle of this
build
uh there is you know there's work to
sort of have a minimal sort of
uh minimal base um so that you know
these usually with these things it's a
little bit like these compiler versions
right like with compilers very often
compilers are written in the language
that they compile yeah I don't know an
example is I think rust but also hasll
right like um and so how do you get to
how do you get to produ produce the
current compiler version well you get an
earlier one and you use it compile the
source code right and you know this is a
little bit annoying for reproducibility
and for for making sure so so there's
work to to to make the space a little
bit simpler um but in practical terms it
won't go that far down right because
when you need a dependency such as u
rust it you know someone in the next
world had to uh build that Rust compiler
uh but there's an XOS organization that
um for 100 thou nearly 100,000 different
packages does the builds are already um
and this gets into a different thing
that um is very very nice about Rust
about Nyx um which is binary
substitution right so if you're asking
for a thing by this very specific name
right if you're asking for cargo with a
specific
hash because
everything is specified in that hash
already everything that possibly matter
is in that hash if anyone that you trust
has already built that you can sort of
just ask the internet you know you have
to be careful that you trust these
people but you can ask the internet has
anyone built this and and if they say
yes you can just use that instead right
so you won't be building when you build
a cargo project you won't be building
all these things you'll be downloading a
binary uh that is the already built uh
because next can calculate that it must
have come from the same tree of depend
the exact same tree of dependencies
exactly exactly in order to have the
same output hash name yeah yeah same
hash
the git trick isn't it it's the same
trick that git uses yeah yeah hash it
build a tree of hashes yeah yeah yeah
that's right
um yeah hashes are you know in some
sense the the deeper lesson is just that
hashes are really good names for things
yeah content what's it content
addressable file systems we have to get
that terminology in yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah that perhaps that's the solution to
one of the two hard problems in
programming right naming things by the
hash yeah exactly which to be fair also
you know Docker to some extent does as
well right but it hashes the output to
the result of what it built rather than
the inputs that went into
it yes
yeah that makes me just want to say I
think this is true you can confirm for
me you can also use Nyx to build Docker
images but with better hashing right
with better hashing like you get a NYX
quality input hash for your Docker
output that's That's right there's a
project that's quite widely used and in
in X packages itself that's a way of
building a layer docker image that where
the layers are quite minimal
um so you know it's easy to
uh if you think if you think about the
way Nyx operates right with these hashes
in some sense
it's solving
um solving the the problem that Docker
has that we mentioned before with
linearity right like with Docker it's
like if you change something earlier on
you don't know what how that's going to
impact the rest of the thing so you have
to go back and start building from that
from that line that you changed
essentially
but with Nyx we know that uh when you
build a dependency when you add
something to the file system uh it'll
only uh influence u nothing else will
influence it right like the that when
you build a python with a particular
hash version it'll be exactly that um so
you can really sort of make very very
fine grain layers and you can also
rearrange them somewhat more safely um
and
that's that that is something that you
people use a lot
Yeah yeah i've I've definitely found the
experience of refactoring and rebuilding
a Nyx file to be much faster
than that a Docker file yeah yeah and
these things start to matter once it
becomes large enough that it is
something you want to maintain right
yeah yeah i think that that that's true
the other thing that we're that's a bit
harder to sort of give a sense for and I
recommend people just try out is that
you know has these ability to create a
you know what I always say is you
mentioned at the beginning of this
podcast you know like oh like DevOps is
something that I often shy away from um
and I think that that's a totally
comprehensible perspective because you
know when
we live in within a programming language
there's very clear semantics and we kind
of know how everything works and we can
kind of abstract things in exactly the
right way and capture them in you know
really find nice ways of expressing
things and the language doesn't work
against us and there's so many different
languages to choose from that you know
really almost capture the language of
thought itself um and then you have
these libraries that abstract over bits
of functionality and you can combine the
libraries and whatnot but then when it
comes to to infrastructure to DevOps
right like it really is like gnarly and
feels like duct tape all all over again
yeah
whereas Nyx goes much further in the
direction of of making
uh DevOps feel like programming again
right like you can abstract over these
if you have multiple different servers
talking to one another not only can you
describe bills but you can describe
entire servers and not only entire
servers but entire sets of servers right
and so you can sort of
really abstract over the idea of for
instance having all of your
infrastructure servers talk to a
Graphana Prometheus export things to
Grafana and Prometheus and that's just
becomes a flag right like something that
you can just enable um uh in all of your
servers yeah yeah like you can start to
because the description language the
equivalent of the Docker file is a lot
more like a programming language yes you
can start supplylying arguments to your
Exactly yeah supplying arguments and
writing functions that you know abstract
over uh Yeah exactly yeah yeah i'm
defining a build that builds several
different versions because it's
effectively just a for loop or a map
over build files yeah yeah
this So this sort of gets us into the
space of because we've talked about Nyx
the there are three parts to Nyx
possibly more nyx the tool for building
stuff with this dependency tree we've
talked about Nyx the language for
specifying those recipes you've hinted
at Nick's OS do we have to buy into a
whole other OS
we do not have to buy into a whole other
OS this is entirely
optional entirely optional i you know
people I for instance run XOS and I
think a lot of people who uh are given
the chance and the opportunity to to
spend time learning Nex um often will uh
because there's a lot of joy to begin
from it but it's it's completely
optional
uh so what does it get you why would you
make that option
yeah I think you know when you think
about
um what
getting what getting a server to be to
be ready to do to to do the
functionality that you wanted to do
maybe run your your your web server or
whatever it is you know your website
um there's usually like a lot of very
sort of imperative instructions such as
pseudo app get this and pseudo apps get
that and then you know move this file
here and whatnot right
um and
um and and as we generally know that
this this can be really really dangerous
as well because it's a very state
stateful system um if we if someone uh
logs in because they notice that there's
a problem maybe with a missing version
or whatever a missing binary maybe they
do a pseudo app get there um while sshed
in and that's you never know that that's
that was part of what makes this machine
tick what makes it go in the right way
um and that's a big problem because if
you need to migrate it somewhere else or
if you need to you know redundancy or
whatever you won't um uh you won't have
captured that and you'll forget about it
the next time around next if as we've
been talking about you know like it's
very much about sort of really isolating
uh uh isolating your system from all of
these uh stateful interactions right you
really have a build recipe that you
specify once declaratively and that's it
right like this the state that happens
afterwards that accumulates the croft
that accumulates in your in your uh your
own uh computer for instance is is
ignored during an X build for instance
right like it's all all about this
isolation that that captures that makes
it makes the recipe capture everything
there is about a build and it's the same
with OS right so you can specify an
entire OS that tells you exactly which
files you need uh to have installed um
which locations which systemd services
it's a Linux based distribution which
systemd services um are there and
um and then you have all this
information right so you can really if
you want to spin up a new server you can
very easily do that um uh by just
reusing this this this recipe
um yeah it's it's part of this I think
is again that that moving things from a
readme with a list of commands to type
at the command line into an actual
programming language where it's
repeatable right yeah yeah absolutely
yeah if we're describing it in pros
repeatedly across the whole industry we
ought to be describing it in a
programming language yeah yeah
absolutely yeah and and you know there
is
a people say you know like if if you're
doing the same action multiple times
often a technique that I heard that I
like a lot is write a little bash script
um that at first you know just prints
out uh the different section the steps
of the read me and you say like have you
done this yes or no but then you can
slowly start abstracting that right like
if there's a step that um is you can do
automatically you can change that
instruction line for instead of just
echoing the instruction
you actually do it so this is you know
this is a
uh this doesn't solve the problem of rep
reproducibility but it does automate
something right this this shell
shellbased system whereas nyx really
solve the problem of reproducibility as
well right so that you don't need the
readme anymore right you just have one
command that does everything for you
yeah yeah and it also takes care of some
of the sequencing right if it doesn't
matter which order you run the commands
in then you don't need to worry about
that and if it does you can specify it
as an actual sequence dependency right
right right right yeah and you can build
all you know all these dependencies that
we were talking about right like we can
build them in parallel right let's say
that you need both a Python version and
a Rust version usually you won't build
that locally yourself because as I
mentioned you'll be using a cache that's
already built it for you let's say that
for some reason you know you have a
patch to Python and you want to build it
yourself and the same for for uh the
Rust
compiler with Nyx you know like because
these these are very isolated you can
safely run these in parallel right um
and so this the sequentializing this
this annoying sequentializing of of
Docker um is something that happens a
lot less yeah and that specific example
I've seen play play out two ways the
first is that you can build each
language on different threads yeah and
and the second is like if you wanted to
do that with Docker would you get a
Python base image and add in Rust or
would you get a Rust base image and
install Python
it's probably just a question of which
one's harder to install first and that's
not the best answer I can imagine yeah
it's just the wrong structure in some
sense right
like a list yeah yeah append only is
probably not the right data structure
for uh build tools yeah
yeah okay so from there I
think one thing we haven't talked about
is time the effect of time on this
because I have found Nick's very
interesting when I go back to old
projects mhm
it's like
I especially when again I come back to
the time when I was doing a lot of
contracting for different companies
and I would like build a project and I
accumulate this croft from old projects
and things I had to install for old
projects run out of disc space clear it
up go back to the other client and then
find I've got to reinstall all the old
dependencies for the previous project
which might not even be possible or easy
right to find those dependencies anymore
yeah yeah and then you get into like oh
now I've got the latest version instead
of the version I installed when I was
working there 6 months ago yeah it's one
of those one of those nice advantages
like once you've actually specified all
this in code either it's in the cache or
you can go and grab it from a remote
cache and rebuild it exactly as it was
right yeah yeah i Yeah it's it's it
feels like one thing people say a lot is
that it's a it's a little bit to a lot
more upfront cost um because you know
let's say that you're building a project
uh you already have a version of of of
uh Python that you already have
installed if you're a Python programmer
um and it's very easy to just be like oh
like Python so and so like put in a read
me Python Python this file is all you
need to do because for you it's no extra
work right like you already have the
Python version installed it seems like
it's no extra work you might maybe even
have the dependencies installed somehow
globally that he didn't
notice whereas Nyx forces you to be
upfront about that cost right like you
really have to uh you really have to uh
think about what Python version it is
that you're doing and you have to
specify those things but once you've
paid that cost up front it continues
it's a gift that keeps on giving for
years in the future as you as you as you
mentioned right because if you come back
to a project from four years ago or five
years ago it still works yes yeah if you
you've got a good reason to believe that
it will still be able to build that
entire source tree again and build it
some of it may have aged out of the
remote cache but it's still possible
and and the cache has uh so far the
policy with the cache with the sort of
Nixos the Nyx or cache the sort of
official cache has been to keep things
indefinitely um that will probably
change but but it's still
uh it's still the case now even after a
number of years and um and that's really
exciting right like not only can you
build it again but you can build it
without doing a lot of rebuilds right
yeah without having I suppose that must
play into the amount of disk space it
uses because if you wanted to store the
binary for um every Docker image that
would be a different thing because
that's going to not just have Python
3.7.6 but it's going to have Python
3.7.6 for every different Docker file
that uses it right yeah yeah yeah that's
that's so the disk space issue is is is
a serious one both with Nyx and with
Docker and it might be more serious with
Nyx than with Docker right like Oh okay
tell um
uh as you mentioned you know like um
with with Docker you have uh if you have
if you in in one Docker file you have a
Python version installed and another
Docker file you have a different Python
version installed and they don't share
uh layers um because they're different
images um or you did something earlier
on that's different then you'll have
that Python version that same exact
supposedly exactly the same Python
version installed twice
That's the thing that Nyx solves if you
have the same Python version that you're
using in two different projects it will
it will be stored in your Nix store only
once so on the one hand there's an
advantage here
but
um because every time you do a build
with with Nyx and you know if you're
working with Nyx this can happen a lot
whatever you change an environment
variable here or something else there or
a GCC version all of these things will
change the hash you know anything that
could possibly affect
um your project will change its name
which in turn means that it will be
stored twice um in so let's say you're
building a Rust project and you have a a
you want to add a comment in your source
code
and you built built it once with Nyx and
then again with Nyx
Because the source code is now different
the hash of the resulting artifact the
resulting binary will also be different
which means that they'll be stored in in
twice with some exceptions and small
optimizations here and there but
essentially that's the idea right so you
end up using
accept that yeah I I think I can accept
that if I've changed the source code to
my project I've got a different output
but there's a there's an almost
philosophical question here if you have
two ver if you have a version Python 376
built with this version of C and Python
376 version with a built with a
different version of C are they the same
Python 376 no nick say not nick says no
yes and you know that's the
philosophically I think that's the
principled answer right because in fact
it could be that there's a bug in in uh
GCC or or uh or whatever C compiler
you're using slightly different behavior
yeah yeah exactly yeah they I think the
realistic answer is yes they're the same
until you're the poor poor muppet that's
trying to debug the difference exactly
yeah yeah yeah you don't want to be that
guy yeah yeah that's right
so this I mean this
raises one question I wanted to get in
from that is because I don't know what
the current state of this
is i
remember five six years ago with Nyx
there being a slight problem in that it
worked brilliantly on Nyx OS and Linux
it didn't work as well on Macs because
the funding for build machines because
it's an open source project right and
you need a whole farm of Macs to build
the caches up
what's the state but now that's I should
say for the record now that's much
better and it works perfectly for me on
OSX what's the state of Nix on Windows
uh I think I I think there's like very
um to be honest I don't have a very good
sense um the truth is neither I nor
anyone I know develop on on Windows
uh we'll have to leave that for the
comment section then
yes there there is I think you know
efforts to support uh Windows and and
there's always W is Windows subsystem
for Linux and whatnot that u that do
allow you to use uh Nyx via WSL um but I
don't know what the experience is like
right i think that that's really a very
important question is is what does it
feel like when you actually try using it
how and I have no idea yeah actually
that so we'll we'll have to we'll have
to find another way to get information
but that does lead into something I've
experienced using Nyx it feels a lot
more like I'm running software on my
computer as opposed to I'm running a
virtual machine on my computer yeah yeah
that's right um I I mentioned a lot you
know these the sandboxing right and then
and that's in the in the build process
you do you do want to sandbox things and
kind of isolate them from the rest of
your computer but once you have that
binary you can now safely use it as if
it were any other binary in your
computer whereas with docker usually you
know you build something and then you
continue use running it you know if you
have a python version or whatever it is
with certain dependencies and it's still
running inside the docker container
right yeah it's not just the it's not
not just getting the Python versions
even after that you have to continue
using Docker and so and then when you
you know when you want something when
you want to communicate with that it's
always a bit more of a hassle or a lot
more of a hassle whereas with Nyx you
really you know you really can just pipe
things call them as in a bash script or
whatever it is right and yeah yeah you
don't end up with Nyx doesn't have an
equivalent of docker compose right no No
and maybe I should get you to explain
why it doesn't need one
uh fundamentally it's it really is
because you know in some sense um these
um again you know when you're thinking
about infrastructure when you're
thinking of large scale infrastructure
and deploying it to multiple servers
then of course there's a question of
like how do you how do you coordinate
how do you organize capture that
infrastructure uh declaratively right
and that's one thing that people use
docker compose for but they also use it
locally right um and that part is
necessary index because you don't need
to be spinning up several docker images
to run specific versions to run your
back end your database or whatever it is
right you can just run them in the same
ambient environment um yeah you're
running Postgress as though a local
binary rather than a separate virtual
machine that connects to your source
codes virtual machine and Right yeah
yeah
so I mean I've been I was sold into Nyx
but I've been a convert for years and I
use it for all my projects but but you
have gone further you've been uh you've
been sold into it to the extent that you
want to build a whole service around Nyx
that's right yeah so what's missing in
the world of Nyx that you felt the urge
to build
i think actually quite a lot um in some
sense this is what's missing in Nyx you
know to make the experience of Nyx users
uh better um but in some sense it's also
you know like it kind of feels like when
I think about Nyx right like it's
already a relatively old project but
when I think about Nyx uh the adoption
isn't it's not the the industry standard
yet in the way that Docker is no um and
it feels a bit like discovering inks
feels a bit like uh you know discovering
a garden uh where there hasn't been
anyone you know like an full of apple
trees there hasn't been anyone who saw
this and you know this is not like it's
like somewhere off in the corner and not
the main thoroughfare so when you go
there all the trees are really laden
with fruit and you can really pluck the
the low hanging fruits without any
effort right there's so many benefits
that that people haven't yet um explored
and investigated to their full extent um
in in that sort of paradigm
shift and and that's one of the things
that really excites me right like I
think an example uh so two two big
examples is you know like uh how much
better CI can be if we base it um based
it on nyx instead of uh anything else uh
how much faster how much easier
how much more reliable but then another
is u you know how how much better our
deployment infrastructure can be right
so that we can really um abstract away
ideas such as you know like having three
server three postquest servers servers
with redundancy and failover or whatnot
how we can get zero downtime deployments
really easily atomic upgrades so that
you know different web servers don't
need to um worry about being back
staying backwards compatible or forwards
compatibility which is a huge when you
know developing um uh all of these
things you know like once you sort of
start thinking in terms of the basic uh
conceptual infrastructure of Nyx uh all
of these things become possible right so
so partly it's you know solving an
existing problem for Nyx users um
namely
um the situation is a little bit like
you know get before GitHub right like
GitHub came along
and
made get much more accessible right
previously you had to you know you were
a Linux kernel kernel developer probably
if you're using it and you had to sort
of format patches and attach them to
your mail client and then also verify
the signatures and use GPG and whatever
it was it was you know it's a it's a
workflow that for a lot of people was
actually quite enjoyable uh but
definitely not for everyone right
whereas yeah GitHub comes along and
makes this really clear that this is
this you know a that version control is
a really good idea and that git is a
good implementation of it but then also
you know makes this accessible to people
who aren't developers um and they can
use this interface and see and see their
change directly in the UI make changes
and I think like this is something that
Nick still needs it needs a company to
to or several companies hopefully uh to
come along and say hey um we can all of
the accidental complexity we can take
care of right like if you if you want to
enable CI um it's just one button if you
want to deploy uh you know seven
different servers in two different
environments that's also you know like
two or three lines of code um and that
will really
um potentially potentially even
abstracting away some of the experience
of using Nyx itself so that you know um
this this becomes that so that we can
benefit from the conceptual advances
that Nyx brings without the admittedly
quite high um barrier to entry give me
an example of how that works cuz it's
like I feel I remember there being a
project called Nyx Ops right yeah which
was attempting to say we can describe
infrastructure using this same language
you're using to describe builds yeah
yeah but that
project I think died for lack of support
i don't think it's still going that's
right um it's not fully dead um but but
it's nearly uh are you taking up the
mantle of that core idea which is we
shouldn't have a separate language for
builds and a separate language for
deployment infrastructure
uh somewhat I think that that idea has
already pervaded some of the way in
which in which uh people use Nyx right
so Nyx has this agenda let's call it
called flakes which is a sort of a
standardized way of
um of organizing your project
um and uh and that means you know like
you know next to language allows you to
to build things but you know
pro you probably want to separate you
know the packages from the tests and
make clear to people what it is that uh
those are and have a standardized way of
saying I want to run the Mac tests
because I'm on a Mac rather than the the
Linux uh Intel ones
and and you know sort of specify again
in a sort of like very simple key value
way almost um what the dev shells of
this project are right so so fakes is is
is
um is has become um a somewhat
controversial but also de facto standard
um for how you organize your your your
projects yeah you've you've you've raced
past that one point i'm going to
emphasize it it's very nice to have as
well as like a a script that defines how
to build it also says these are the
tools you'll want available in the shell
when you're developing yeah yeah that's
a really nice angle of that yeah yeah
the dev shell as you mentioned sorry
carry on yeah
uh so so they're um so they I think the
the majority of of new projects by far
um use this this sort of uh use flakes
and
um and they allow you to specify uh also
Nexos machines which I mean as we
mentioned you know you can have entire
uh Nexos systems built on Nyx um which
can you can run locally in VMs or which
you can deploy Okay um and so what we do
is say okay like well given that you
probably are already writing all of
these things um if you're um if you're
coming if you're nicksavvy uh there are
options if you're not Nicksavvy
but if you've already written this what
we say is okay we'll just build all
these things without you having to
specify any more details we'll just
build all your packages and and checks
on CI and if you say I want to deploy
these seven servers or these five
servers we'll also deploy those servers
for you right so so we're not coming up
with a new uh idea about how to
um about how to
uh this uh how to deploy and and specify
uh large scale infrastructure in Nyx
because this has already been there are
some already accepted practices in that
regard we're just making it automatic
right so it's a it's a a platform as a
service right like you push to to GitHub
and we run all your tests and we deploy
um automatically so kind of the ease
that you might expect from from Heroku
or something like that but with a Nyx an
entirely Nyx based system is the trick
here
that is the trick that a Docker file is
more like a bash script than anything
right and you you
can't you can't really like build the
syntax tree and do compile time analysis
in the same way in a Docker file that
you could on NYX the language and what
you're doing is saying we can peer into
this language and peer into these
specifications and figure out what
they're trying to do and use reuse that
machine language for a different purpose
the purpose of deployment absolutely and
and and it's beautiful like I I I really
get a lot of joy from thinking through
the various ways in which this this is
such a beautiful idea and concept right
like one of the things that's really
great is you can actually see you know
because because you can peer into the
structure as you say um you can say
things like oh what what is my my
network topology which machines are
talking to which machines um or what are
the versions you know let's say that uh
uh uh we know about a CVE that just came
out in Python affecting uh you know this
version range i can say okay what uh
what which of m machines have this
version of Python installed right uh
anywhere anywhere at all right um so you
can really peer into like into into with
remarkable detail right and into uh your
entire uh uh infrastructure and really
start you know programming with it right
like uh uh coming up with uh uh yeah
coming up with questions to ask or or
ways of automating systems and whatnot
that that really uh well we we talk a
lot about infrastructure as code we
don't then make the leap to say code as
source of information we can automate
further right yeah yeah yeah there is a
yeah yeah yeah absolutely
uh there is this there's this nent idea
in in things like puli for instance
right like we let's use the data
structures of of a proper programming
language so that uh but there are
problems with
with with using an existing language
like that to do these things right like
um there isn't there isn't really
clarity about about these structures and
running the same script twice might
result in different structures and you
never know and um
so so it feels again a bit ad hoc even
though it recognizes the importance of
being able to manipulate uh
your your infrastructure as a data
structure
yeah cuz you
want it does sort of push if you want to
really unlock that it pushes you away
from languages that are inherently
imperative you want to get more towards
a language that's more like just a big
data structure right right yeah which I
guess is kind of a trick that Lisp
figured out back in the 60s and we keep
relearning right yeah yeah yeah that's
right yeah
okay
so tell tell me so your service for this
is called Garnics right yes and I do
want to know what state it's in and what
cuz I'm always interested when
programmers get so obsessed they become
like builders of services yeah yeah
what's that road like and is the is
there much competition is there much
uptake how is your life now as not just
a fan but a seller of mix yeah yeah yeah
i think uh you know we've again the way
we've been thinking about this is um you
know again like building a platform as a
service based on fundamentally different
approach based on nyx um has a lot of
advantages has enormous
advantages but one of the things that we
also sort of uh took for or a conclusion
that we came to is also that um to do a
pass to do the CI/CD pipeline you should
really do the CI pipeline very well um
and and the reason here is you know when
you when you see all these other sort of
uh companies such as render or fly or
whatever there's a
uh the technique is something like oh if
you want to try try us out we'll build
your project using build packs or
whatever it is um and then deploy it but
usually at some point you'll switch to
GitHub actions for running the tests and
whatnot and then you have to call into
us and to let us know um to let us know
what it is you built push the binaries
out and push the the Docker images or
whatever it is to us but this is kind of
a narrow waste right like you lose a lot
of information there's there's one
component GitHub action say that's doing
the build and another component that's
hosting and as we mentioned you know
there's a there's a lot of information
it's really cool to have a lot of
information about your infrastructure to
know exactly what's deployed what's
talking to what uh how it's structured
what versions you're using
um and and if you have that narrow waste
not only do you have does the user have
to deal with two different things but
you lose a lot of information in the
communication process so we focus
initially on CI and we have like a
decent number of companies now sort of
using this as their main CI um and I
would consider that very stable um the
the hosting part is also something that
we have more and more companies adopting
um uh but it still has some rough edges
and some many features missing and then
another component that we uh recently
released is what we call GX modules
right and the idea here
is you know the reason why NX is is part
of the reason
why part of the reason why Nix adoption
is is is being less than stellar is
because of this big big steep learning
curve right so what we do is we say okay
here's here's a way of generating the
base uh uh nyx configuration for various
different types of projects if you tell
us hey I have a Rust project um and it
uses this version of of of cargo and
rust and then we can generate something
and create a PR in your in your code
that captures exactly what it is that
you need to do so that you don't have to
learn next at first right so that that
initial hump um isn't there yeah yeah
there does need to be a kind of here's
uh here's your first recipe
automatically written for you exactly
yeah yeah so then you can get to you
know in three minutes or five minutes
you can get
to CI and deployments working and you
know dev shells and whatnot working uh
without having learned next right and
then if you need to change the cargo
version it's relatively intuitive what
to do and you can learn gradually um on
an a per need basis rather than you know
spending so much time and effort um up
front before seeing any serious results
which is hope I guess you're hoping is
why you won't need everyone who learns
Nyx to be a paid contractor for Exactly
yeah yeah yeah it it you can think of it
you know this last component modules you
can kind of think of it like anible I
think right like anible has this YAML
syntax where if you have uh the Ansible
uh recipes I forget what they're called
u you can expose a way of calling those
arguments via YAML so for most users you
can just learn learn how to use
uh the YAML component of of anible but
for users who um are more familiar with
Ruby and the the Anible internals they
can write these recipes right and so so
uh it's and maybe at some point you sort
of migrate slowly from being one type of
user to another but but you're you're
uh maybe amortizing that cost uh over
the lifetime of of your interaction your
usage with of anible or of kinx modules
yeah do you know I've never quite been I
I see the logic of that i've never quite
been fond of that approach because it
means that as you become more advanced a
user there's inevitably going to be that
point where you have to switch languages
yes yes and presumably you're avoiding
that
u we'll still see right and I think to
some extent uh part of
uh part of what we think is like you
know we have to gather a lot of a lot of
experience from various different users
to see
um it's similar actually with uh build
packs right like Heroku and and I think
render as well use these use use the
same technique which is like you don't
have to learn exactly what script is
being run in order to build your project
and deploy your project um you can just
uh be largely ignorant of that or have a
tiny bit of configuration but if it gets
more complex you're going to have to dip
into to those build packs right um yes
but is your configuration still in Nyx
the language yes it is so there won't
come a time where I need to switch
language to actually use all the
features right that's right yeah yeah
and sort of having poking holes you know
or sort
of making that transition be nice is
something that like involves careful
design there's no sort of
uh you know let's let's say that you you
know you have you want to override a
particular version of a dependency um
maybe you have a field that does that
easily uh or maybe this is a time where
you have to learn about fetchgate
built-in fetch gate or something like
this right like you have to decide very
carefully when that happens and how it
is that the user experiences that
transition and how they learn about it
and whatnot and I think it's just a lot
like designing a library or a
programming language it's just something
that the nitty-gritty details have to
have to be considered and done with love
right yeah yeah and it's one of those
design decisions that will eventually
shape and limit the size of your user
base right right yeah are you are you
just going to appeal to Nick's experts
or are you going to try and take it to
the next level where anyone can use it
yeah exactly and we hope that the answer
is the latter right i think that's our
ambition yeah absolutely so I want to go
back and pick you up on three features
you said of using Nyx for um deployment
because I think this is worth you
unpacking
um atomic update like atomic deployments
yeah yeah why does Nyx enable that cuz
that sounds like a useful thing to move
everything to the new version all at
once yeah yeah yeah
uh yeah so so atomic uh deployments are
something that you can see in two ways
right like one one question is the zero
downtime question right like in this
this is something that's familiar to
everyone uh as soon as you have you know
something that's a little bit more than
your personal
website you probably worry about the
amount of downtime that you have if any
when you upgrade the version of of your
OS or of your dependencies or of your
application right um do you stop that
application and start a new version do
you have a gradual roll out as with
Kubernetes
um and
um and what we do um I think you know
the
the what I think is exciting that we do
is we we extend the idea of Nyx to the
cloud by using these hashbased
names we use them as uh domain names for
your web servers
this is a bit of a crazy
idea but when you deploy a web you know
I mentioned that when you build a
version of your of your package it gets
a hash name that uniquely identifies it
right and and if anything has that name
it's the same thing now when you have a
recipe for how to build an entire OS um
you can also hash that and all of its
inputs and that it also gives you a name
that uniquely identifies that behavior
modular you know state which we can talk
about later
the volumes that you have attached and
whatnot i think I see where you're going
with this so you would be able to build
the new version entirely get it up and
running under a new domain name hash and
then your atomic update is switch the
load balancer exactly exactly yeah yeah
yeah yeah okay so you switch the load
balancer and that gives you the atomic
part right yeah so then we have to talk
about state because that I can see that
working perfectly until my database
files also need to move over yeah yeah
yeah so let let's let's maybe just
elucidate a little bit more of the
picture so it's clearer what the
advantages are and how it works right so
we have these uh hashes and as you
mentioned we switch atomically the load
balancer but the way in which each
server is talking to one another is
using those hashes as well right um so
the really nice thing is when you have a
when you have an upgrade um and you only
change one server that's that's
uh that uh isn't talking to any other
servers but is receiving requests from
them
um then what happens is you know now in
theory all these servers that are
talking to it also uh also change
because they're talking to a new version
right and so their behavior is different
right like in the same way that if I
have a function fu and it calls a
function bar and bar changes then in
some sense the behavior of fu also
changed
so all of those get new hashes as well
and they all get deployed but if it's
the other way around where you have a
server that isn't being queried but it's
talking to various different servers you
just have to deploy that new version and
it can talk to all the old
infrastructure
yes so you when I deploy my new version
you can say for definite you haven't
changed the version of Postgress that
doesn't get a new hash so we just yeah
the web servers just keep talking to the
same old database exactly exactly so
this is a minimal upgrade right you you
you spin up only the things that really
changed but it's also atomic both in the
sense of zero downtime but just as
importantly and even more excitingly I
think uh the version upgrades happen
atomically you're never going to be
talking your new version of um of your
application is never going to be talking
to an old version of of your new version
of the front end is never going to be
talking to an old version of the back
end right
um or of server one versus server two
and so you never have to worry one one
thing that occupies you know occupies
developers a lot and is really annoying
to think about it's like oh like always
maintain backwards compatibility in all
of your APIs because nothing is ever
atomic right like you're always going to
have different version mismatches as you
upgrade and roll out things whereas here
they're not they're atomic everything's
atomic so you really can look at your
code as a point in time thing right you
don't have to worry about what what it
looked like yesterday before you made
this change um you can develop in a very
uh clean way so that's another big
advantage of this
hashbasedly this also makes it easy if I
do want to maintain two different
versions like if I promise to keep the
old JSON API running for that client
yeah yeah the one technique that we
haven't implemented yet but uh we're
excited about is you know
uh
uh leaving versions on for external
users so that they also don't have to
worry about this right like if they use
a if they use this hash domains um you
can just keep track of you can keep
upgrading without backward compatibility
changes u concerns um and then just keep
track um in the load balancer level of
how many requests are coming in from
from the external world for for those
old versions and and you know maybe you
have a threshold that says you know like
if there's fewer than one request a
month then you can then it's safe to
spin this down yeah unless that request
is coming from our biggest client in
which case we got to negotiate with them
bet that happens I bet you
right right uh or alternatively you know
like there are even weirder ways of
thinking right which is like a uh kind
of you can develop as
a AB testing sort of right like you can
do deployments and then just see uh see
what versions people like the mo the
most right like Yeah yeah uh maybe you
you know maybe you have a branch where
you're doing some work and you just
deploy that um and it lives as a fork or
as a separate branch for a long time um
we are getting into the world where this
one language which describes my
dependencies and my my language
dependencies and my out of language
dependencies and my deployment
infrastructure also describes my AB
testing
and my feature flags yeah yeah exactly
yeah that's exactly right and not having
separate languages and separate
configuration files for all those things
sounds like where we should be yeah yeah
i agree um
so this suggests that most of your
future is going to be figuring out
comfortable ways to describe this and
then building out all those tools that
introspect on these descriptions and
surface things like here's a here's a
CVE you've got to worry about yeah yeah
absolutely yeah you must be hiring UI
people
well you will be if you're not
currently uh yeah so far we've you know
because the majority of our customers
until two weeks ago all of our customers
were Nexus users i think they're already
kind of familiar with the way these ways
of thinking and so it's been relatively
easy but now as we sort of start start
to expand this it really um it really
does involve thinking very hard about
about how to how to present this in a
way that makes sense right that feels
intuitive
yeah yeah okay i'm probably not a great
barometer of this cuz I'm an existing
Nyx user who was who was forced/paid
into it but actually became a convert
but there are probably people listening
to this who are tempted to try Nyx and
perhaps they can become a small flood of
uh of test bed users for you so the
question is how do you get started where
would you recommend someone who's not
being paid for it to get started with
Nyx yeah so this is a bit self- serving
but I think you know our new modules
project garnix.io/modules
u can uh can help you know with rust or
hasll or u npm projects for instance can
can get you
um a lot of the way or the entire way
into having hopefully the entire way
into having a project that compiles and
builds with Nyx and CI um and obviously
the way I would like for this to work is
that this becomes independent of garnix
altogether um you know in some sense
you I think uh vendor lock in is a
terrible thing and so to some extent I I
I hope that you know people consider
this even if they don't want to use
carex for anything else for CI or uh
that they generate this file and then go
off and and you know build their project
in in themselves in different CI system
and deploy it however they want um but I
think that that's a very good way of
sort of you know seeing that initial
experience right like seeing Okay this
really works and I can sort of
understand the package uh infrastructure
and I can look at the syntax and then
see how it
reflects facts about my project that I
specified um and understand a little bit
about about Nyx and get a lot of the
benefits right like already get a dev
shell that works for my project um yeah
which languages do you support because
I've tried this with one of my Rust
projects and I thought okay if I'm a
Rust user this is pretty straightforward
yeah yeah yeah but presum you have to
write recipes for lots of different
languages to make this universal
yeah um it it's uh right now it's it's
only Node.js projects Haskell projects
uh Rust projects and then also uh you
know Postgress databases and Linux users
as configuration for your
uh for your web service if you choose to
deploy web servers as well
um but we want to um we want to expand
that a lot and I think you know if there
are people out there who are really
excited about trying this out and want
to reach out and say like this is the
project that I want i think for us it's
very uh very helpful to have that sort
of tight feedback loop so that we can
see okay like what what is working what
isn't working for you so do feel free to
reach out if if these aren't uh if what
you're looking for isn't supported yet
but so far it's it's those three text
acts right okay i'm I'm quite surprised
to hear Python isn't one of your early
adopting languages yeah I think uh I
think Python would is the natural next
one um and and yeah that raises a
question I haven't asked but I'm just
going to dip into it quickly what
language are you building this in
presumably it's one of those three
you've already mentioned you're ether
doing this in Node Haskell or Rust tell
me i reckon I can make a guess but tell
me
um actually you know the the full answer
is all three um our front end is you
know a nojs project and we have some DNS
servers and load balancers and whatnot
that are in Rust some small projects
that are in Rust but um but the majority
of the codebase is in Haskell um right
so what you actually need is a
dependency that's built in Python for
that script to get to production quality
yeah exactly and this is Why I say that
you know having having contact with
someone who is so useful at this stage
because so far it's been very easy
because we say okay like we let's try
this out for we're familiar with these
stacks let's try it out for our own
projects let's try it out for uh a
couple of French projects and whatnot
but as we move towards you know Ruby for
instance the language that I don't have
very much familiarity with um I think
it's good to to to to be talking to
people who do
Yeah yeah it's also I I'm not sure
you'll ever get there but Nyx is one of
the few languages that um at least makes
makes the environment of Pearl feel sane
cuz someone's had to go through all the
pain of writing Nick's recipes to build
Pearl reliably
that makes Pearl less of a pain you see
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah and that's
deploying Pearl anytime soon but you
could but I also think you know Zigg for
instance or Gleam or things like you
know these new languages that could also
be exciting right like none of that yeah
and those are ones that maybe haven't
got a fully realized infrastructure
story yet yeah yeah exactly yeah yeah
it's difficult to know whether you
should go after the biggest players or
the most hungry for new services players
right right um Yeah yeah and it's also
you know to some extent
uh not only are these technologies newer
uh and therefore maybe have less support
but also the projects in these languages
are themselves newer so it's more likely
that you haven't yet solved or that a
big proportion of those projects haven't
yet solved the question of how you're
going to get this deployed right whereas
if you're running a Java project those
those are mostly I would think you know
like proportionally more more legacy
projects might be more objectively but
they probably the majority of them have
already solved these questions in one
way or another yeah yeah if you're
spending serious money on Java you
probably already know what your
deployment stack is yeah yeah yeah well
in that case it sounds like you've got a
lot of work to do and a lot of market
research to do yes absolutely they
should probably leave you to go and do
it while hopefully a couple of the
listeners give you some more data to
play with and that more data will force
you to do a data mining project in
Python and we complete the loop
perfect and on that note Julian thank
you very much for joining me thank you
as well it was a pleasure cheers thank
you Julian so as always take a look in
the show notes for links uh I've put a
link to the Nyx getting started guide in
there if you're using one of the
languages that Julian mentioned Garnex
is actually looking to be a pretty good
way to get started with Nyx quickly so
you might want to try there before we go
I'm going to leave you with the single
most terrifying thing that Nyx has
taught me over the years so Nyx is a
tree of dependencies and it goes all the
way down to the kernel as we've
discussed and when you're building
something you can look at the logs and
see that what you're building depends on
these things and those things depend on
these things and so on all the way down
you get the whole dependency tree
staring back at you and I promise you no
matter what stack you're building no
matter what language you're using
somewhere in your dependency tree you're
depending on Pearl absolutely promise
you so huge respect to Larry Wall for
creating one of the foundation stones of
everything we use but also you might
want to take two Valium before
bedtime before you go and get that
prescription filled if you've enjoyed
this episode please take a moment to
like it rate it share it with a friend
make sure you're subscribed for the next
episode and if you're really enjoying
the episodes consider going to Patreon
and supporting us but for now I've been
your host Chris Jenkins this has been
developer voices with Julian Ariani
thanks for listening