thank you
hello my name is I'm on the internet
known as mig-92 and I'm here with Las
Luz I and we're gonna talk about a joint
project which is consisting of two
components that we will present because
we cannot take them in isolation on this
disco and the other one is Nexus
anywhere
um so what's the motivation for building
these things so we work with num type
um and we install Nexus on a lot of
machines we have a range of customers
then you get like two at some point you
have like went through all the providers
that exist and after some time it
becomes like a bit tedious to like adapt
to every of these platforms
and also installing Express takes some
time
um so in the beginning we were uploading
install images to the various platforms
and each platform is a little bit
different some of them don't even
provide you this method so we were
looking for something that allows us to
install Nexus anywhere in a more uniform
fashion and this is than what mixes
anywhere became
so to give you a little bit of a
background of what steps you could throw
if you install Nexus
first we need to boot into an access
install ideally
and this also depends highly on your
target so over to machine you maybe have
like a virtual machine image or
something like that or bare metal
servers you have something like PC board
on a laptop you put in a USB stick
then you need to partition the fast
disks that you have add some file
systems and then Mount these to location
and then you have to write some next
question configuration or you copied
over from a previous system and then you
run Nexus install and then you reboot so
stack five steps takes a lot of time if
you have to do it at scale
um and also something that this may be
error genius if you like do something
slightly different than you didn't
document it how you did
so let's take this and
simplify this and this is what we did
with two projects
how one is called disco and disco you
specify your this configuration in a
declarative way like we love to do so
this layout becomes uh next next code
and then Nexus anywhere is the second
tool it takes this Nexus configuration
attaches your Discord layout configured
and then it has a single command that
uses SSH to install excess
okay so I'm going to talk about disco
briefly so what is disco basically it's
like a Nexus module which takes like a
configuration with some strings and it
outputs two scripts one is to format
your disks one is to mount them and also
some Nexus configuration to actually
like configure the file systems and
stuff so your system actually boots and
also the rates
yeah it uses like some module magic like
evil modules like everybody knows best
feature of nexos
and so yeah one very I often asked
question is why don't we use systemd
report because it has basically no
features you can just specify a single
disk you can or you cannot use ZFS you
cannot do any lvm stuff with multi-discs
so yeah that's basically it's like very
limited to appliances and we love our
setup first we have it everywhere so I
don't really have said I said the first
time we get set yeah exactly if you
don't have CFS yeah nothing works but a
repart has some cool features which
disco doesn't have yet so there's like
disk image creation without a VM so they
do like cool stuff with this Auto resize
I still haven't implemented in Disco and
like also populate files like this goes
only for partitioning and mounting stuff
not population
so this is an example how disco looks
basically this is like just the
partition table slow oops
I can try to speak slower already so
there's like uh this is like the disc
here there's like canis my mouth
actually yeah cool okay so here's like
the main disk you can point it at some
random device like it should exist of
course if you want to format it
and then you say it's like a GPT
partition table in here so the device is
only used during the initial creation of
the partition table uh later it's not
going to be used anymore if you use the
new GPT type if you use the Legacy table
type stuff will break don't use that
anymore
so so the background here is that you
provide your device and then it will put
when it creates a GPT table it will make
a label so then when you have example we
have two nvmes and they get swapped
around for random reason and you might
have trying to mount the wrong one so
you want to have labels and this is what
this GPT TF is doing
basically yeah so yeah uh this is
basically the advanced feature of that
so because it's like Nexus config you
can split it over multiple files and
this is basically what the partition
table would look like so we have like a
AV partition there for 500 megabytes
with a
boot file system on there where you can
also specify the mount Point here then
you have the root
partition which is 100 and the content
is like an extended for file system
so yeah that's very basic I guess I
guess this everybody expected so it
should work in excess
yeah
the tricky part becomes then when you
then have a set of us for example with
multiple devices yeah yeah you built
your new shiny nixos.org binary cache
was like 25 hard drives and then fix
become a bit more a bit more longer
basically yeah other cool features that
have multiple devices the examples are a
bit too long to put them here rates with
mdadm lvm Lux encryption B cash FS you
can also create disk images with disco
which is quite nice so if you have like
a this configuration with multiple disks
you actually get multiple image files
out of it so you could maybe create a
ZFS rate from USB sticks and put this
yeah everything is possible like check
out the examples folder in the Disco
thing this is actually a link if you
would have the slide then they are my
pet to slide so you can click on them
later
uh yeah basically you sell all the cool
features
yeah but what what are the problems with
disco so basically because the options
are like recursive you can have like a
GPT partition table a lux partition in
there then like in a GPT partition table
again it's like hard to generate the
documentation for this in like the way
we do this now for modules because it's
like all over the place
also we use this weird type syntax so
everything is like polymorphic and
everything can be like different types
everywhere yesterday we tried to ask
Robert tensing because he's like a
magician when it comes to the next
module system and first of all first of
it you didn't believe that we built this
type so then this got me back here we're
still wondering how we can then generate
documentation for this because just now
you have to look at the examples uh but
it would be nice to have something
equivalent to the Nexus manual to the
reference menu after all the options to
find
and another problem is currently disco
only works by completely destroying your
partition table first and then
reinstalling it so something is like
State transition I want to add to it so
basically it would check what your
current setup would look like and only
do the non-destructive stuff or like do
it in a way that you keep your files
yeah we really don't try to like have a
Windows installation already there and
you need to run disco because it might
be a no longer present so it takes tries
to take control over the disk
um
it could be a feature for some people
before there's not okay okay so now we
have had have our politicians formatted
um but this is still something very
would you need to like um go in manually
for example this is a disco Library
called have the configuration on the
system and then run the format in the
politician formatting and mounting
um it's much nicer if you don't have to
do that and you can just form your
laptop or set up your new laptop for
example or some server
um so this is where Nexus anywhere came
in into play
it's a bit like um just imagine like
Nexus install has like a remote flag
where you can specify a remote server so
this is what makes us anywhere else
doing
um so you have your Nexus configuration
with the Disco configure configuration
in there that we just saw then you need
some SSH decimation and then yeah if you
run this command it will start doing the
excess installation
uh so how does this work internally
um so first we log on to the machine
then we do some checks we for example
check like what's are the architecture
there are we in the next installer SS
installer maybe already or not
um because if you're not in the Nexus
installer then we do a trick called cake
SEC which I will explain in a little bit
um but it allows us to load the Nexus
installer into uh the memory
then we run Disco
to do all the partitioning things that
you just saw run Nexus install and then
reboot and then it's done
so back to cake exec
um it's a feature that's already for
quite a while in in Linux but maybe not
everyone has used it so far but this
basically allows you if you have a Linux
kernel running you can instruct this
Linux kernel to take a new kernel and an
internet ID and then just boot that so
it's used for for example for kernel
development because you can quickly
without going through your
firmware you can just boot into a new
operating system because sometimes like
firmware they take like 10 minutes to
boot no kidding
and we use this to just load our next OS
installer into any Linux this has proven
to be like really generic and nice
because on every provider you get some
sort of Ubuntu and they already put your
SSH key in there so you can just use
this and as a starting base for an
excess configuration
um so what this is what the usage looks
like we can use next run if you don't
want to install it yourself on your
systems which if you just want to run as
a command
um then you provide with the flag
argument you provide what Nexus system
to install and then you specify the
hostname so simple as that
what we found like when you create a new
disk configuration sometimes you don't
get it right the first time and then if
you have to reboot the machine it takes
a while especially if you have not a
great cloud provider doesn't have like a
really slow web interface or something
like that so it's much easier and nicer
if you can just test locally that's
that's why there's a VM test option so
what this does is um it simulates the
whole installation in a nexo svm test
and then you can see if it already works
and it boots it's maybe not a perfect
for everything just now but um yeah it
often gives you like make sure that most
of the stuff work
enough of nice features secret support
so often when you install when you use
some of these tools like argonix or sub
snakes then you have this bootstrapping
problem that you need first the key to
decrypt all the other Secrets onto the
machine
and um with Nexus anywhere you can also
specify flag face just upload other keys
and then you can get all your other
secret tool management working
so next up
um let's just have a demo I think it's
way too small for the people here in the
room oh yeah but what you see is that it
runs the VM test so if you're already
familiar with yeah you know I see like a
mix first VM testing this locally but it
could be also a server as well
but you can see
um it won't take that much time after
all
so it's already done formatting
um
uh yeah not already booting so yeah yeah
if you get the slice later you can run
this on your computer and see how it
works or just try it right
um yourself
yeah so that's done pretty boring which
is good
um
so yeah like I said just now we use SSH
so we need some machine and some other
Linux that's already exist sometimes
it's not always true like if you have
like a bare middle server like we have
in uh the university
um then it's also nice if you can just
use something like a pxe boot which is
like a feature on your firmware that
where the computer is asking for uh
operating systems to boot so I have for
quite a while I have like a branch where
I implemented that but I never merged it
because I was still wanting to have some
Nexus test working as well so
yeah and this seems to be just now not a
not a working implementation of that
because you can also ask when you have
chemo you can also there's also a Peaks
e boot feature in there and this is what
I could use for testing
um and what would be also nice is um
just now you need
um to generate at some point the
hardware configuration of your target
system for example you need Sometimes
some special modules so it drives get
recognized and just know this is also
manually and it would be nice if you
could have something where it tries to
generate a software configuration copy
this somehow back and then use that to
install the system so that would be
something nice to have in the future
see
yeah to summarize what we talked about
today we had a disco that you're used to
configure this and we talked about mixes
anywhere to install your Nexus was that
so the project pages are following to
discuss the next Community
Nexus anywhere we are still a num tight
um
yeah that's it that's it if you've got
any questions uh time is now
[Applause]
how am I going to get that uh
thanks for the talk uh I have a question
about disco
um
I find that one of the most annoying
things what when what you do when you're
partition your disks is making sure that
your partitions are properly aligned uh
like it's things that you can
occasionally stumble on especially if
you're doing Zeta fast like if it's
slightly misaligned you get all kinds of
performance issues especially in ssds
does this could do any kind of specific
magic to make sure that your partitions
are aligned or at least warnings that
you are doing something very stupid no
but that could be a feature
I mean now you specify the sizes of each
partition right now you're basically
like
specify what SG should run and if
there's an sgdisk parameter to do this
automatically or one you then it would
do this yeah I think usually if you use
like a common sizes like one gigabyte or
something like that some then it's
already set of aligned yeah I think so
yeah but I'm not sure
yeah right okay yeah we could check that
but it's like yeah something we had to
implement right and the thing is that
sometimes there's actually use cases for
that I I know that some arm boards if
they want their bootloader really really
odd locations and then you need some
alignment
um yeah yeah yeah maybe open an issue
and I will think about it all right I
will open the issue
I'm all the way back here
okay all right great talk thank you
um I have a question so from I
understand that this works in an online
environment so both machines have access
to the internet I'm wondering if there
is a method to install Nexus if the
machine B the target doesn't have
internet access so sort of prepare the
install on machine a ship it and install
it on the machine B
um so if I mean we we can support it
offline because we have an access test
that also doesn't have internet
um so you would need the next rest
closure already on the target from a
start installation and then the machine
that you know from firmware is starting
yeah from where you start installation
and then Target you install too it
doesn't need to have any internet access
indeed when I when I use the pixie boot
I never actually got configured any
public internet on that it would just
copy everything from the installing
machine over
um so there's nothing special needed if
you have internet that's maybe faster if
the machine can use the binary cache to
download something from you from the
binary cache rather than you having to
upload everything but this is something
that is automatically said
now I'm literally all the way in the
front
thank you for your chunk I've uh already
used disco and Android it's a great deal
um
I'm wondering if you if you have any
ideas on how nixos anywhere could
support systems that have very little
Ram which can be an issue for the
sometimes quite sizable internet mfs's
that are used for kxx sort of stuff
yeah so yeah that's okay exec
um needs to load the whole install into
memory which is a tough call if you only
have one gigabyte of ram
um because Nexus has some size to the
various reason
um so the current recommendation is
either you find a way to actually boot
an exhaust installer because if it
detects in exist installer will not try
to kicks that it will just continuous
installation which is also nice if your
cakes if you install a failed because
you the machine doesn't actually reboot
you can just like retry
um uh yeah but then there's also there
was also another approach where we tried
to like uh someone try to use some as a
tool called mixed up by yeah as the
installer image so that was uh an
attempt to like reduce the inexor since
data and it uses this uh clever trick
that um we actually now use systemd and
also in in it ID so it would not
actually uh switch to a Nexus a normal
mix size it would just stay in this and
then use the smaller initiative and that
also helps to like bring down it to like
I don't know what the minimum size was I
think 50 megabytes yeah so that's quite
small I think if you have a machine that
is smaller than that you may be worried
about that all Unix workload might not
work either anyway
yeah
hey thanks for tools I really love them
um I know you had at a point a bit of
terraform configuration but you never
mentioned it here uh and I thought it
was a really cool integration uh that
makes Nexus anywhere spin up things
really easily but have you sort of given
up on that or are you still using it no
the I actually just updated the
terraform module last week I was adding
a secret support to that
um yeah I think it's like mainly I need
to like I mean we already tried to
document it everything quite well with
like a quick start guide and even if
you've not used Nexus that much that you
can get started using it over the
telephone code I haven't gotten a route
to like make a proper example what's
indeed quite nice it's just like one
module if you know if you're familiar
with terraform
um where you can just pass in all the
arguments that you would specify on the
command line you specify to the module
and then it will run Nexus anywhere and
remember that
and it's quite also nice if you just
want to like have a quick installation
that you maybe kill later also because
you're just trying something out
um but so yeah it will stay supported uh
we have uses of that and yeah not not
going away
okay
hi
um is there a plan to support something
like uh using disco on a running system
at the moment it's for installing only
for example for CFS to deploy a kind of
data sets with special options or
something like that to have it in a
declarative way
on my system
so just go I will configure your file
systems and stuff but it won't create
new data sets right now but it's on the
agenda so I want to like implement the
stage transitions so if you have like if
your disco config changes and the up the
changes are non-destructive like it
would do those but it's not done yet
it's like end of the year thing it's
super hard to have this problem because
at the end this course also just uh
shell script generator sort of uh so
it's like the rest of Nick's
is just bash scripts here basically best
script templating yeah the power of Nyx
any more questions
foreign
you sure
what would it take to get it into next
West as the default installer
what would it take to get it into nixos
as a default installer first we have to
merge disco I guess yeah getting to yeah
we would first need to get this code
into it because uh you're you're making
this part of an access configuration and
you have like an exhaust module where it
learns about the descriptions
um I think next was anywhere I could
package actually that's even the
independently of that uh it's just a
long Sales Group yeah
it would be not even a particular of
complex package I don't know what I have
not done yet
first I'm gonna
you said you already have
um luck support in Disco is it like full
support for all the options or just
basic support could I like for example
use a UB key to unlock my disk and yeah
you can like Define all the Nexus
options in there so whatever Nexus
supports okay it's also like extra
format arcs which gets passed to the
command line so you can do whatever you
want but you can also shoot yourself in
the foot so perfect okay you also you
also have you also have performed after
hook so you can even check your own
shell script code into that if you need
something really really special I don't
know even
uh hello thanks for the talk
um to react back on adding discos and
express we have a report module in nixos
in the next release that you can use uh
we added that but it would be nice if we
could collaborate make be making a
uniform module interface that they use
the same options all right and then
people can choose whatever they want
okay yeah the question is does repot
actually support everything we have
because otherwise no yeah it's a subset
of what you support I think yeah
yeah
so yeah if like repot only does this
stuff
or if you're doing disco only the stuff
that repart you support we could like
generate a report config out of it I
guess but it's hard like to detect what
what if you have a feature that's repot
doesn't support but it's also on the
agenda not very high priority because it
works right now over here
um it seems you're in favor of set FS
did you also try a butterfs butterfs oh
yes yeah I use this on my root partition
yeah you use a yeah I use it everywhere
oh
you're praying man yeah
[Laughter]
is like somehow got a host hosts like
the pad for like a lot of people in
Linux Community for like meeting notes
and stuff it was only like last week
when I actually wrote him a backup
module so that database would get picked
up so nowadays are safe yeah whoever
uses my pad like knows I don't have any
backups hello you have no way and I
monitor them
yeah
if I know this yeah that's better for
supporters also supports for creating
sub volumes as far as I remember
better
first is what what's the question about
yeah for better first we support us the
subway the volume snapshots snapshots
and stuff yeah
and
yeah
no I don't think I don't think raid 5
works in Big better fast in the first
place so maybe we should actually
yeah yeah
yeah
it's just thought in memory and so for
the best but the Battle of s only works
with one single disk right now it's like
no no multi-disc type so because no one
I know uses that yeah you shouldn't I
think yeah but we could allow it like
no no I'm the best script developer oh
yeah okay
[Laughter]
um any more questions
I have a question uh did you guys like
arrange that the speakers would speak
faster so you guys can ask more
questions so that I have to distribute
more Parks yes that's the case okay
round
but that's good
I wanted to start by saying thank you
for the awesome tool talk and also the
weekly merge meetings you guys hold you
might recognize my voice
I was wondering of course you have real
life considerations outside of just
Nick's interests what would be a
somewhat expected time scale for more
CFS features and the
disco not having to recreate this from
scratch every time
I think we got like a thread for setup
first where people like propose a lot of
things you need to add uh has like an
issue where people are like talking
about the schema we want to Define like
we just have to implement it now this is
schema already know I think it is but
people people should take a look do you
use Advanced database features yeah so
they said for set of us there's like a
thread where you can see what option uh
What uh what people want to have and if
we have the next configuration then
let's just make it a purchase script
somehow and yeah and for the other thing
was first incremental stuff yeah I I
have some there's also an issue about
that where I talked about the ideas so
it would be like a check face where you
like check the current state and do the
stuff if that's like okay to do without
destroying anything
I haven't put deep thought into it yet
hi so um
you configure your disk labels with the
Disco is there any integration with the
Nyx OS configuration to make sure that
the disk labels you configure for the
file systems match up with what you've
configured in Disco yes if you use the
new GPT table type it also it also
generates a labels also for you already
are we talking about the sacrifices
like it's like part labels yes yeah yeah
so actually we interpret here we use a
feature of GPT of the and put the labels
there and there's also file system
labels yeah but we don't use that we
don't use labels
uniform yeah then we don't need to check
for the first systems which was easier
to implement
it's the second time I had to go back to
get more Parks so can it can work off
the calories from drinking all the club
matter oh that that's good I don't mind
that
uh hi so in general installing next to
us on anything but not x86 so like onto
arm boards especially if nexo has
installed if one decides to mount the SD
card onto the main computer and then try
to use bin fmd breaks almost every
single time uh so with next OS anywhere
because you mentioned disk images does
that work nicely from an x86 machine
creating a disk image for a arm machine
and then putting that on the SD card
I haven't tested it yet I think well I
guess either you have like native cross
compilation with pin fmt with all before
you use the benefits I think bin fmt
might be actually fine because you're
only copying stuff uh yeah if you have a
binary cache yeah yeah but we do expose
all the options that you need to like
change uh
I haven't tested this yet I have a
Raspberry Pi on my desk so also clear
maybe yes I have the experience that
next to us install really likes because
so you have to put bin fmt if I remember
correctly in slash run and then next to
us install likes to just kind of clean
Flash run up and break with empty
halfway uh so it's something I've
experienced So currently I think
currently it spawns a virtual machine
anyway for creating this
yes yes
so I think the best way would be if you
would just like make sure we actually
like if you if you're doing a cross
build that we then it's been armed 64.
Linux I think it's not I don't think it
works quite well yet just now probably
not but we we should check that yeah I
think it's feasible it's not like out of
yeah that's something
probably yeah
okay
oh I guess
anyone else we still have time
all right yep
fill up this time
um is it possible to uh for the CFS
Fanboys to
start or to have two disk mirrored disk
and booting if without grub with
something like system deepwood
and have an encrypted CFS that should be
possible yeah I set this up just
recently like uh the problem is the boot
partition because you need the API
partition and you would either put this
in the into an ad and the ADM rate with
metadata 1.0 so but then system Depot it
doesn't work because it doesn't like to
install to this yeah so it's a hard part
is actually convincing system do you put
if I have a rate system so like actually
like uh you cannot really install it
like like two uh put politicians it
doesn't like if you have to put
politicians like on different discs it
doesn't like if like the wood partition
is like on the red because it says it's
not a real file system yeah it's also
this and recruit crab works with that so
you I would say crop is currently the
better option for this setup uh so I'm
actually using the mirror boot option uh
for that crop house and I think there
was someone that tried to implement it
for system Depot as well yeah right to
set we should use this magic parameter
but this magic parameter also didn't
work it didn't work I know the other
magic parameter so I tried both it
didn't work it's the right to lie so
assistant yes you can tell assistant
dude often to try to install it
anyway but it didn't it wouldn't do it
so like it has some checks and it's
really picky about you have to follow
the if you spec you only have like one
iffy politician on the whole uh system
and it doesn't like multitasks and stuff
um but I guess you can have multiple
boot partitions or something yeah so I
think there was a next packages per
request but this needs to be merged
first because then episode is not really
a feature of Discord it's a feature of
Nexus to have to bootload uh being
installed into this at the same time so
that's the ideal thing I think yeah
you're right because this option is
missing at the moment yeah to have a
system debuted on mirrored disk or
multiple discs yeah that's basically a
feature which is missing okay
we didn't fix that yet yeah yeah
it just gave up on your scrub again in
this case
anyone else
no let's give it up for the speakers
Mick 92 and lazulus
[Applause]