this week has been a crazy decade Google
quietly crushed every open AI model on
the market with the release of Gemini
2.5 Pro meanwhile deeps 10cent and quen
All released Banger Chinese models but
nobody's talking about it instead every
eyeball in the tech world right now is
hypnotized by open ai's brand new GPT 40
image generator which has transformed
the internet into a gbi anime cartoon
nightmare this is exactly the AI
dystopia that Senpai Miyazaki creator of
the GBL Animation Studio tried to warn
us about years ago when he said quote I
am utterly disgusted if you really want
to make creepy stuff you can go ahead
and do it I would never wish to
incorporate this technology into my work
at all I strongly feel that this is an
insult to life itself that was years ago
but now this nightmare is in full effect
if you make the mistake of going on
Twitter today you'll find that all your
favorite memes have been ruined by GPT
40 in today's video we'll take a closer
look at open ai's latest toy along with
a few other awesome tools that just put
us one step closer to the singularity it
is March 28th 2025 and you're watching
the code report when I read the
newspaper that GPT 40 added an image
generator my expectations were extremely
low especially after the disappointments
of Sora and GPT 4.5 low
expect however open AI just went out and
totally redeemed Itself by shipping some
actual fire this tool has allowed me to
throw graphic design software like canva
in the garbage because now I can create
infographics and marketing material with
near perfect text rendering it even
produced an almost Good comic strip for
me and it can even handle transparency
like players unlike most other image
generators but everybody's talking about
its ability to transform images into
specific art styles that's pretty cool
but the significant thing here is that
it gives us the ability to render our AI
girlfriends in ways that were previously
Impossible by maintaining character
continuity like now I can upgrade her
with new poses new outfits or even add
her to photos of those lonely family
dinners that's impressive but how does
it work this is closed AI we're talking
about so there's no paper or code to
look at but apparently they use an auto
regressive approach instead of diffusion
a diffusion algorithm in models like
stable diffusion and mid Journey
generate an entire image all at once but
GPT 4 takes a different approach
generating the image pixel by pixel from
left to right top to bottom it almost
doesn't even look artificial but it
actually contains a controversial
Watermark provided by the Coalition for
Content Providence and authenticity in
fact if you take this image and upload
it to the ctpa tool you can see it was
generated by open AI along with a
history of any modifications to it a
camera manufacturers and software
developers like Adobe are implementing
this into their soft Ware with the goal
of tracking every change that happens to
a digital asset like an image and that
of course is to keep you safe from
misinformation at the expense of your
privacy and freedom and platforms like
YouTube and steam are now requiring
people to disclose that they use AI
Assets in their work and that brings up
a big philosophical question that was
first posed by someone with an anime
profile picture on the internet with
slops razor you ask can you tell it's AI
generated by looking at it if the answer
is no then it's indistinguishable from
Human work thus no disclosure is needed
but if you answer yes then it's visibly
slop and again no AI disclosure is
needed c2p is just deep State bloatware
but I digress if you're poor the other
thing you need to know about is Gemini
2.5 Pro this new state-of-the-art model
from Google actually slaps not only is
it arguably just as good for programming
as Claude 3.7 with a bigger context
window but it's also better than
reasoning models like open ai3 and you
can actually use it for free right now
instead of paying $200 a month for open
AI Pro but the problem for Google is
that the Chinese are ruining their plans
for World AI dominance deep seek just
released version 3.1 and it two slaps
Alibaba released quen 2.5 Omni which can
see here talk and write thanks to its
new thinker talker architecture then
10cent released T1 to compete with deep
seek and bite dance the company behind
Tik Tok released Dapo an open- Source
reinforcement learning system for
building large scale large language
models we currently living in a Vibe
coder's Paradise where anyone can pick
up an open source Chinese model and
generate more code than they could ever
possibly need and that means real
programmers are going to have a lot of
code to fix and refactor and an awesome
tool that can help you review all that
code is code rabbit the sponsor of
today's video an AI co-pilot for code
reviews that gives you instant feedback
on every pool request unlike basic
linters it understands your entire code
base so it can catch more subtle issues
like bad code style or missing test
coverage then it will suggest simple
one-click fixes to help you get things
cleaned up quickly code rabbit keeps
learning from your PRS over time so the
more you use it the smarter it gets it's
100% free for open source project
but you can get one month free for your
team using the code fireship with the
link below this has been the code report
thanks for watching and I will see you
in the next one