we'll get started um so uh a few sort of
words of introduction before we we start
um so that's me I'm Richard Eisenberg um
uh and I spend quite a bit of time uh
thinking about dependent types and tasal
we'll talk more about that actually
toward the end of the talk um the the
other stuff it surprisingly uh didn't
doesn't have as many dependent types um
uh also if any of you were at zurah
Haack this
this spring um this is the same talk
that I gave there you were welcome to
get up and go to some something else I
was just asked this morning this as as
as we heard this morning right the
original speaker for this this slot was
is unwell today and so I I sort of
jumped in at the last minute so that
that means one it is a recycle talk but
two um uh I have not rehearsed this
since June um and so if I get a little
confused at my slides please forgive me
um and and sort of as as it's not it's
not quite a workshop it's more more of a
talk I I very much want questions but I
don't have like exercises for you all to
get out your laptops and do as I would
if I had sort of preed this as a
workshop so that's just a few
disclaimers but please do ask questions
so the talk is is shorter than the time
that we have a lot is so there's plenty
of plenty of time for questions um so
you'll see here um a link can someone
has someone has anyone actually tried
this link yes does it
work no it
404s that's very interesting um that's
really too
bad what can I do about that very
quickly give the talk just give the talk
I think I I think that's probably a good
idea okay um I will if there's if
there's a dry moment somewhere toward
the end I will make that available I
don't know why that would happen um okay
so um when whenever I get a chance to to
actually get some some feedback so Simon
talked this morning about there's no
Telemetry right so we don't know how
people use hll so I love to get a little
feedback when whenever I get a chance to
give a a talk um so how many of you use
hascal to make money in some
way wow that's amazing um so uh so I
assume uh most of you I maybe I won't
call out to to ask for raises of hands
here but um that um that you you're
working for someone else or or you're
working for yourself you sort of have a
business but it's not just sort of um
something that you do in your spare time
if you're using it to make money so
that's that's pretty cool um so one of
the things I find really fun about these
about these kinds of events is is is is
seeing people who you know use hasle to
to write web services and use hascal you
know I'm I'm I'm fascinated by the fact
that every now and then I see habito
advertise on television right and I know
that there's like hascal powering that
but sort of behind the scenes probably
not the ad but um so so very exciting um
edit to to to do something like that so
I want us to start off with um sort of a
history of of hasc's type
system um so uh actually this is before
hasell hasal was 1990 but this is sort
of along with the birth of hasell so we
have you know Haso started out with well
there's there's type classes right we
wanted some way to be able to use a plus
sign um and and have it mean different
things depending on what types of
numbers we're using and so it's like oh
okay so we can do that in a more
principled way say than than you know
Java or C++ does it that we can have
this this this type class approach um
and and then we we got up to to
functional dependency so I realized
there's a long gap between these um and
and then and then we realized that once
we wanted to have multi-parameter type
classes that would sort of go in between
these that you want to have some way of
one uh type parameter or one parameter
to the type class affecting another and
so that gives us um uh functional
dependency
and and that I think in my opinion that
was sort of the genie first starting to
crawl out of the bottle right once we
could do this then suddenly we could do
some level of computation in types um so
this got uh explored more deeply um with
data families so data families actually
were invented as a way to make programs
run faster um that we wanted to have
specialized representations for say
arrays of inss right we can do that
really fast um if we have an array of
some other type maybe we can't do it as
fast so data families are a way to do
that um then these got generalized a
little bit further to type family so now
we really had things that acted as
functions on types um and and so this
was in some ways a competitor to
functional dependencies and the two are
still sort of fighting it out today
actually um uh from these then we have
generalized algebraic data types um so
uh generalized algebraic data types
allow us to sort of control the the um
uh the type of an algebraic data type
depending on what Constructor we use or
conversely when we pattern match on a
Constructor we get to learn something
about the type so with gads in my
opinion the genie crawled a little bit
further out of the bottle here right now
we can have programs that when they take
a runtime action they cause um sort of
compile time information
uh to to to become available and so that
means different parts of a case
statement can have different
types um so that was you know three big
papers all right in a row and then
there's this Gap here and and so lots of
stuff happened in that time uh one of
them being a complete reimplementation
of the type Checker in in GHC to
accommodate these these new Innovations
um so then this is about where I started
studying hasell uh it was in 2011 um so
data type promot motion came along and
now what that means is that we can use
data Constructors in types and we can
use sort of types in kinds and that
opened up better expressivity better uh
checking of all this type level
programming um so then we have uh uh
right after that we we had Singletons
which isn't really a hasal feature but
it's something that's used to sort of
pretend that we have dependent types so
there was a lot of this that that was
sort of out there in the folklore and I
tried to sort of pull it together in in
this paper in
2012 um so then another big step forward
in my opinion is the idea of type in
type um so previously there were terms
and there were types and there were
kinds and they were all sort of separate
um now since GHC 8.0 took some years to
implement this um since GHC 8.0 we've
had types and kinds being the same thing
and so that means not only can we have
functions on types but we can have
functions on kinds um and and as Simon
likes to remind me we're still sort of
recovering from this Big C change inside
of GHC this made things a bit more
complicated but a lot more expressive um
so we also now have closed type families
so open type families are sort of like
um a class methods almost Clos type
families are more like proper functions
um and so we can do a little bit more
computation in types um all of this led
to problems because now that we had all
of these fun types we wanted to be able
to Do complete pattern matches so as
Simon explained explained to us this
morning this is hard um and so here was
nice paper that that refined the pattern
match warning Checker we're still
clearly working on that as as Simon
explained this morning um not only do we
want uh closed type families but we
sometimes want to be able to propagate
information from results of type
families back to uh back to the argument
so we have injective type families um
sometimes these all these implicits are
hard to work with so we want type
application uh we want to be able to to
tell GHC how we're specializing some
function instead of having it infer um
all of these tools can be used quite
usefully to to have type reflection so
there's this typable mechanism which
allows us essentially to do Dynamic
typing in a statically typed language um
and so that's built on a bunch of the
previous extensions we have pattern
synonyms now so we can abstract over
patterns and they have their own complex
relationships with types we recently
have Quantified class constraints
meaning not only do we have a class
constraint but we can then say that this
is true for for any type A not just for
a specific type a um uh more recently
this this one is is not yet implemented
it's in progress um we we we have the
idea of type abstractions so that way we
can have a a part of our code that is
generalized over a certain type variable
so a few things to comment here first
off I could make another whole slide
this dense with more papers about hasal
and has Cy system um the other
observation is I mean how wonderful it
is that we have this language that that
sort of every major step is accompanied
by peer-reviewed uh research um I I just
think that's so fantastic because it
means that we have long form
documentation of of our decisions and um
and it allows us to really uh sort of
understand where we are and and where
we're going going and we we have a
little bit more faith that things are
right when when everything is sort of
goes through the the peer review process
so what this talk is really about is
with all of this explosion how can we
make use of it where where does all of
this go to how how can we make use of it
so uh just a quick question how many
people here were in Marco's talk this
morning about keeping hascal
simple okay wow not a big overlap
between that and this I that something
something to be said about that actually
so I want to I want to return to that
um because there there's well not many
many people were there but I'll return
to that um so this this talk is really
about Stitch uh so Stitch stands for the
sound type indexed type Checker um and
it's um it's it's an application of all
this technology to something fairly
typical so the idea is that we I've
implemented a uh a simply typed Lambda
calculus so you know a criticism at this
point is well you you know you type
system researchers why do you always
just implement the simply type Lambda
calculus right why don't you do
something useful um so I would I would I
would argue first off implementing the
simply type Lambda calculus is really
useful right large systems all have
implementations of some sort of
scripting language right whether it's a
productivity Suite right we you know we
we know Microsoft Word Microsoft Excel
are all scriptable um whether it's it's
um something you know any text editor
you have a way of scripting that game
have a way of scripting them there's
been several talks today about build
systems those are run by scripts right
so having you know implementing a
language is actually a fairly common
phenomenon um and the other nice thing
about this example is it's something
that we're all familiar with we know the
Lambda calculus even if you've even if
you've never heard of the Lambda
calculus before if you've programmed
high school you know the Lambda calculus
um it's just it's a way of defining
these these Anonymous functions and
applying them um so let me sort of go
over and show you what this looks like
and going to have to CL a little bit
with the display here does that there we
go that's what it should look like okay
um I can make that
bigger okay
so hopefully this does something yes
good um so so here it is um the one
point I'd like to make is we're going to
see a lot of fancy code but this is
actually just an application that runs
right anyone can download this and run
it and I've actually used this to teach
undergrads about the Lambda calculus
I've not shown them the Code the code is
rather is a little bit more intricate
but the end application is just an
application um and so you know it it can
evaluate four that's not a big surprise
it can evaluate 4 plus 6 um so we see
here that it knows the types of things
right we can see that that it gives a
type to everything um and it's a Lambda
calculus so I can do something like
this
um right so I can write a little l a
function I do have to annotate the type
of the bound variable there is no type
inference in this yet Al though I think
it would be quite possible to do and and
fun uh so that may happen someday um and
and it's higher order so I can do things
so here um I can take a function from in
to int and then an argument and apply
that function to that argument twice and
then I can have a function that adds two
and then apply all of that eight and I
get 12 right um so so this is all sort
of like ghci it's not all that exciting
um but one fun thing it can do is I can
ask for how this
steps uh so here we can see using sort
of a small step reduction so again this
is used in an academic environment to
teach students about Lambic calculus is
we can see how this would reduce from
the beginning to the end um so one thing
that we see in the output now is that
there's these funny hash signs right so
my my my initial input has fs and x's in
it but that's all gone for these um
these indices how many people in here
know what a de brone IND index is wow
okay I just like to to to reflect on the
fact that we have a room full of people
many of whom raise their hands for they
use hasal for money so your your actual
developers um and who know de brown
indices this is very cool um so um so
we'll return to that in in a moment but
the the bottom line is is that you can
you can just sort of guide Yourself by
the colors so when you see a yellow hash
sign that's going to match up with the
yellow variable and and the green hash
sign matches up with the green variable
and so on so so we can see how this
reduces so so that's sort of what this
looks like on the outside um but but the
evidence here the reason I'm showing
this is that there's a parser there's an
evaluator there's a pretty printer it's
all the stuff that you
want um okay so now we have to fuss with
displays again for a moment
and hopefully it ends up the right way
yes okay cool um okay so so for those of
you that don't know about debrown
indices it's a way of keeping track of
variables um so we don't have to worry
about their names right of course in my
example there I chose F and I chose X
but those names are irrelevant um and
and when I'm Computing I don't really
want to have these extra irrelevant
things um cluttering up my my my data
structure and so instead what we do is
we want to a de brown index count counts
the number of intervening binders
between a variable binding and its
occurrence So What on earth does that
mean so that means that
here we have zero and we see that it's
yellow and that means that it looks for
the thing that's bound with no lambdas
in between so that's this one zero
lambdas in between the usage site and
The Binding
site um for one here there is one Lambda
that appears between the usage site and
the in site um so uh so the the zero and
the one indicate that but um the one of
the challenges with the brown indices is
that they're hard to keep track of and
so I've used colors in the output here
um and and that's sort of a small
Innovation but I've actually gotten a
bunch of people to say that that just
makes a whole lot more sense when
there's colors involved um okay so I I
guess I did that with my finger but the
slides have it as well so and we can see
that the structure in the de brown
indices matches the structure uh that I
wrote in my uh my initial code
okay uh let me just pause here are there
are there questions so
far okay we're good um so why do I use
de brown indices why don't I just use
names so one is I don't have to worry
about things like shadowing right
shadowing would be if I B if I bind the
same variable X twice then there's a lot
of fussing to do it's not very fun um
these names as I said are meaningless
anyway and the real reason is is that
it's much easier to build a system in
the way that I have using debrown
indices
um uh one could contemplate doing other
things but that would take even more
pyot Technics than than we have here um
the the real reason in my opinion not to
use debr indes is that they're hard for
humans um but uh My Hope Is that the
colors helps that a little bit they're
really much better for computers um okay
so this is an interpreter right there's
many phases that we have to go through
the first phase in any interpreter is
Lexing so let's see how we do Lexing
actually let's not see how we do Lexing
Lexing is boring it's the same in this
interpreter as it is in anywhere else
that's skip let's go to parsing um
parsing actually does turn out to be
more interesting here um so we might we
might imagine what is the type of my
parse function so my lexer is going to
produce a list of tokens actually
they're L tokens the L stands for
located um because I want to know where
my tokens have come from so I can report
errors to to the user so we get this
list of tokens and I'm going to produce
a ux um U here stands for unchecked
we'll see that there's an X Type later
that has been checked um but that's
that's where you com from but it's it's
this expression type we'll see it quite
shortly um this is no good as as the
type for for my parse um because it
doesn't it doesn't accommodate errors
right we might we might have a parse
failure and I don't want to just call
the error function that would be really
bad um so instead I might try this so
it's going to be a list of tokens and it
returns either um an error string or an
expression and you know some people
might stop there and be content with
this but but I'm never content with that
um because I don't want to just say that
it should be any expression if the user
types in x + one on the on the on the
input line there well that's not quite
right we don't know what x is so I want
to specifically say that we want closed
Expressions we don't want any free
variables every variable that gets
mentioned has to be bound and so what I
want is
is that um and I apologize the green is
a little dim up here it's it's quite a
bit brighter up here so hopefully
everyone can still read that it's a
little dimmer than I'd like um but um uh
I want this type so this is the real
type of of my parser um is that it takes
this list of tokens and it either
produces an error or a ux zero so let's
talk about what what that is that's
going to be the number of variables in
scope that were sort of in scope before
I started parsing so we start out with
no variables in scope so that's why it's
zero
um okay so what is this ux thing um so
here's here's the definition of of part
of ux um so first off like every good
talk with lots and lots of types I have
my unary natural numbers um here so we
have a a natural number is either zero
or one plus another natural number um
and then I use that to index um my my ux
type so once again this index tells me
the number of variables that are in
scope in this
ux um here and we'll get back to Finn in
in just a moment but so if I have a
variable so this is when I write an X in
my program that's going to be this de
brown index so this is going to be you
know a number zero or one or two
something like that
um and um when I have a Lambda then I
need to know the type of the bound
variable so that's this this AR type
here so I going to have a type tie that
we'll meet later on um and then the
function body is going to be another
expression but this has one more bound
variable than than sort of the the
outside right so in my recursive use of
ux I say suck n here right because
there's one more bound variable inside
of a Lambda than
outside um I have let in my language we
didn't see an example of that but we do
have let um and so the you know we have
let x equals some expression in some
other expression so the first expression
is over here that has the same number of
bound variables my let is not recursive
if my let were recursive then this would
have the suck here um but then in the
body of the let I do have one more
variable so I have the suck
there um it's it's also worth at this
point just sort of calling out my my
coloring convention here so we have um
keywords in blue um we have types in
green we have data Constructors and I
think that's burnt umber or something
like that um we have local variables in
purple and then there's one or two other
colors that that will will pop up um but
one thing that I'm I'm careful about
here is to distinguish between um
between types and data so here zero and
suck those are data it so happens that
hasell now allows us to mix data with
types so I can write suck here in the
middle of what would otherwise be a type
but it's actually a piece of data it
just happens to be compile time data so
this disagrees with the way a lot of
people describe what's going on but it's
the language that that I I I find is a
little clearer around this than talking
about promotion and things like that um
okay so I want to go back and describe
oh yes please is the application saying
that the ends must be the
same application of one to
another the natural number should be the
same number yes exactly that's exactly
what it's saying so right because when
we have F applied to X both F and X are
are are in the same context there the
same variables that are in scope for
both uh a function and and its argument
so that's why we have the same end later
we'll see that there's some typy stuff
and and we're not but we're not getting
to types
yet other questions thank you for
interrupting me by the way
okay um okay so Finn I said that this is
some storage of these de brown indices
so Finn stands for finite set the type
Fin n contains exactly n values so what
that means is if we if we just go back
here right so uar um uh takes a Fin n so
I know if my index N is a two then my
Fin n must be either zero or one it
can't be anything else if n is zero then
my Finn can't be anything at
all was there a question no okay okay um
okay so now I have to go through all of
these extra words that appear okay um so
anyone who's paying close attention this
morning would realize oh but Finn zero
still has bottom yes it does let's just
ignore that we're just going to pretend
that that's not going to happen um it
turns out in the code some of these
strange pattern match things this
morning happened and so I have to
reverse the order of arguments to some
functions to get the left to right order
to work out to get better completeness
mornings very sad um okay so so here's
the definition of fin um of all I I I
spend a fair amount of time looking at
these fancy types Finn always does my
head in so um let's just try to
understand it by example instead of
trying to sort of pull apart the
definition there um so so let's say I
want something of type fin
five well FS FS FZ in other words two
has Type fin five right two is less than
five is sort of what I'm saying here um
and so the way that we can understand
this is is by sort of following the
types so here by the way I've written
five I really should have written suck
suck suck suck suck zero but that's
annoying so I just wrote five
um so uh let's see how is how is this
working um we we we follow the types so
if FS of something has fin five we see
that FS has ends in type with fin of su
so that means that the n in this outer
FS has to be a four right because it
produces a five so that means that this
inner FS has to produce a four so that
means that this n in the inner FS has to
be a three
which means that the fs the FZ which
also produces a su well that n has to be
a
two has to be a two there we go um so um
so here we can see that if we start out
with FZ having nb2 well then suck of two
is going to be three and then FS will
take something with a three here and it
will produce a four and then the other
FS takes something with a four and
produces a five everyone's
happy um so so now we can wonder about
does two have type fin 3 well sure it
does here the N for f for FZ can be zero
and then it gets incremented three times
and we get up to three but if we try to
figure out if two has Type fin two
there's just no way we can get it to
work
out right there's nothing that we can
put here such that when we increment it
three times ends up with two um so so
that's how this type in captures the
idea of this finite set so let me just
pause here for questions we're not we're
not going to be building a ton on top of
fin other than the fact that it's a
finite
set but I'm happy to take
questions
okay
um okay so going back to this definition
here um so we see because the de brown
index is a Fin n then we know that
everything has to be well scoped I can't
have um the brown index of two in a
context where I'm expecting no variables
at all that will just be ill
typed um and so once I've produced one
of these uxs I know that there can be no
out of scope errors it is
impossible or or I would need to have
bottom somewhere but I said we were just
going to ignore
that um okay so now that we know the
type that we're parsing into let's just
return back to the challenge of parsing
so I said that parex is um is going to
take a list of of these tokens and
produce if there's no errors a ux zero a
closed expression with no free
variables um now parse X is is going to
be you know some some bunch of
combinators around a I'm using a a
monatic parser combinator I think it was
parseek um and so I'm going to have this
expert somewhere in here and there's run
parsec t or something like that in there
um and exper is going to have type
parser
ux0 um well that's not really going to
work out because I need to be able to
recursively parse sub Expressions that
are not closed so I don't want exper
just to be able to parse closed
Expressions I need to be able to parse
open ones as well so that's no good um
so then I might think oh let me just
generalize this and I want exper to be a
parser that can that can parse um uh an
expression with any number of variables
n the problem is that's not really good
either I'm never going to be able to
implement that kind of expert because I
don't know how many variables um uh are
in that output right this is it's a it's
um if if you just try to implement it
you you won't be able to um uh we sort
of don't have enough information to be
able to do it instead what we need to do
is now instead of just having parser not
only do we need to have a par that
produces a an output but we need to have
our parser monad needs to be indexed
with the number of variables that are in
scope okay so what do I mean by
that um so uh so I think we'll
understand this better by looking at
what what is this parser thing
anyway so um it's going to be a type
synonym so a parser na this is
describing a parser that produces
something of type A and N vars are in
scope
and here's its definition um so this is
based on on Park T so that's the parseek
monad Transformer uh it has four indices
so the first is the type of the input
that one's fairly straightforward that's
just our list of located tokens um Parc
allows us to carry around a state turns
that we don't need that to do our
parsing so we just give it a trivial
State um and then a par T wraps around
another monad so the other monad that
I'm wrapping around is a reader
monad that stores a VEC of n
strings so those of you who haven't met
it before ve is another type that
appears in every single one of these
kinds of talks um that it's just like a
list except the length of the list
appears in the type so it's not just any
list of strings but it's a list
specifically of n strings right these of
course are
the variables that are in scope so when
I after I've said back slf and then a
little later back SLX to bring F and X
into scope my Vector is going to contain
F and x and it allows me when I uh when
I parse a variable usage it allows me to
look up which index should should be um
assigned to that variable um but the key
thing here is is that the length of the
vector must match the number of
variables that I know I have in scope so
here's the N that comes in from the the
index dep
pars um
okay
okay U so here's a quick introduction to
to vectors uh for those of you actually
how many people have seen this
before okay most but not all um so this
is another one of these gads right so if
I have an empty uh Vector that's length
is zero that that vector's length is
zero otherwise I have some other Vector
of length n and then the result has one
more element in it but otherwise um
right if if I sort of you know in
different syntax and such this does look
quite like um the list
[Music]
type uh okay
so where are we going from here we're
going to this slide um so here's here's
our definition of parser with our Varn
and and and our
vac okay um okay so so let's just let's
just recap so if that if you got lost
there if it's afternoon let this is this
is sort of the one of my my summary
slides um okay so what we've just seen
is that I wanted to have well scoped
Expressions my ux type I wanted to know
that as soon as I have a ux that it was
always well scoped there could be no out
of scope variables in other words no de
brown indices that are too high and so I
did that by um oh by by index ing my my
my ux but then we needed to index the
parser monad so that I could parse into
these expressions and I had to use a
length index vector and that was built
on top of my fin and and all this other
stuff right so my first idea was just oh
I just want to make sure that there's
nothing out of scope around here but
then in order to do that I needed to do
all of these other things too so one of
the
takeaways types are social creatures
right and as soon as we start with some
types we want more of them I don't know
if anyone here has tried doing fancy
type stuff in Java so before before I
met hascal um I was actually a high
school teacher for a while and so in in
the American High School curriculum Java
is sort of the language of choice and um
I was always trying to sneak more types
in uh because because I like types um
and and if you've ever done fancy type
things in in in languages that don't
have a rich type system like hascal you
end end up hitting the these walls
things that you want to be able to say
but you can't um and this always makes
us want to have more and more sort of
power in our type system um so here's
something to think about sometimes these
talks can go on for a long time if you
define yourself getting bored I have a
task for you so uh those of you who
aren't native English speakers maybe
don't know that English has a great deal
of fun coming up with fun collective
nouns um so uh so for example we we
might have a herd of geese herd isn't
all that exciting but we also have a
murder of crows and a shrewdness of apes
and the reason we do this is just
because it's fun so I propose here that
we might have a closure of haskers but I
I'm unable to come up with a good one
for for Collective uh noun for types so
if you want to just sort of ponder that
while you're daydreaming go ahead maybe
a paradox a paradox of types but they're
no no no they're not a par correct a COR
yes I thought about that a correctness
of types or a sness of types I guess
univ ah a universe of types that that uh
somehow sounds too mathematical that's
not fun enough um okay so um so we have
types of social creatures so let's talk
more about
them um so uh how do we then type check
our language so I didn't show any
examples but of course this is all type
checked if I had written a type
incorrect expression uh we would have
gotten errors so the first step is I
need to know what my types are um so
here's my data type to to describe types
very simple we have ins we have booleans
and we have
functions um I didn't show any booleans
but there's if and there's booleans and
there's comparisons all that's fun stuff
um okay so the way that that I'm doing
this after type checking is I have what
I'm calling a type index abstract syntax
tree um so just like my unchecked
Expressions were always scope correct my
type checked Expressions will always be
type correct I do not want to permit the
possibility of having um say you know
true plus one right I don't want to be
able to express that in my language
because if I can express that then maybe
there's some transformation that I have
in my in my interpreter that then
violates type safety whereas if I know
every expression is type correct then I
can't violate type safety so so here's
how it's going to look like so first um
I'm going to need to know what the types
are of all of my variables that are in
scope so that's a typing context or CTX
and I'm just using that as a type
synonym for a vector uh of n types right
I'm going to have n variables in scope
each one is going to have a type so
everything has to work with respect to
this context so this might just list
sort of int and bu an INT arrow in for
the three variables I have in
scope um so here's my my expression Type
X so my expression type it uh it works
for any n right I can have any number of
variable in scope and it is going to be
indexed by a context a typ in context so
I need to know again all of the types of
my of my encope variables and every
expression itself has a type and then of
course an expression itself is a type so
this is perhaps a little confusing Tai
here is referring to this in orb stuff
whereas type is a hasal type sort of
some levels crossing a little bit here
um okay so here's a way understand this
an X CTX tii is an expression of type
tii in a context
CTX um for those of you who have seen
this kind of notation right we can say
that if if e has the Type X CTX tii then
we have this typing judgment right this
is this is exactly what it means if
you're familiar with that notation if
you're not I'm not using that notation
again this in this
talk um Okay so again every expression
is well typed in this system so let's
see how we're going to build that up so
we have variables so here a variable is
going to take this Lum so LM is another
way of expressing a de brown
index um so what's what's LM it's
essentially we could think of LM as a
proof that a certain element is in a
list or in a vector in this case um so
what we really want to say is is that
every variable here has to have the type
of some element in our in our context
right I describ this context as this
Vector of the types of the ins scope
variables um and so I want to pluck one
out and say that this variable is that
particular type so that's what this Elm
type
does um so there's two different
possibilities for LM this one what we
can call here right it's saying that X
is in the Type X con X's right we see
here's X there and there's X there so X
is in the Type X cons X's it's right
here it's the first element it's at
index
zero so this is my representation for
the de brown index zero saying it's the
first thing in my
context or we have another Constructor
which we can call there right an element
is either here or it's there which says
that if x is in X's somewhere then
surely X is in y cons X right we can add
another element to our context and we
can still find that X in
there um but what that's saying is that
that's actually means look one step
further or thinking of it as as a
debrown index that's plus one right so
this is this is another sort of
representation of these unary Naturals
um but it has all this fancy type
stuff if this is going over your head a
little bit that's okay we're not
building on top of LM here we just just
need to know that it's sort of a
representation for debrown
indices um so here we have lamb so this
is our representation for for
lambdas
um uh so it needs to know the type of
the
argument then we have an expression now
this expression in here um is in an
expanded context right so the expression
inside of the Lambda it has one more
type it has one more variable in scope
the type of that variable will be ARG so
we add ARG to the
context and then the result of of this
Lambda the type of the overall Lambda is
going to be a function that takes ARG
and produces res where res was the type
of the inner
expression um okay so this thing here
this is a
Singleton so what a Singleton is is it's
a piece of data that's available both at
compile time and
runtime so in this case we need this
this type at compile time because that's
the type of the bound variable in my
inner expression and we needed it
runtime so that we can print the thing
um it turns out that we only need it for
printing which I found quite interesting
when I first implemented this um that we
can do all the evaluation everything
else without that because this language
supports type erer um there's no typ
directed operations at runtime um but uh
but we still do want to be able to print
it so so it's a
single um okay so what do I mean by that
let's let's look at the definition of
this s ti so the idea is that if our
types are either ins or bulls or arrows
we need Singletons for each of these so
we have Sint which relates to TT and we
have SB which relates to TB and we have
this double colon arrow thing which
relates to the single colon arrow thing
um the idea here is that
once I know a term then I know the type
right after I pattern match and I get S
in then I know that the type has to be T
int after I pattern match on SB I know
that the type has to be TB and so it
allows this information to sort of flow
back and forth between run time and
compile
time um for applications this one's more
interesting than it was for unchecked
expressions
right so here I have the function
expression which has a function type
from ARG to
Res I have another expression of type
ARG and that's going to produce an
expression of type
res right sort of all the pieces connect
now if I have an ill typed uh function
application this is going to be no good
if I have a function that expects an INT
but I pass it a then this these two args
aren't going to agree and I'm not going
to be able to build my my app
um okay this is I think the last we're
going to see of this exp type before we
go on to how this how we actually type
check this thing are there questions
here before we we go
on it's probably worth saying at this
point I am not expecting everyone to
leave this room knowing how to do all of
this my goal here is to is to sort of
show that this stuff is possible that it
works that it it's it's actually Fair
clean um and and you know and then
there's pointers I will make sure that
that code becomes available um so that
you can access it access it later but
but this is supposed to be sort of an
overview I'm not expecting the full
details to get absorbed I don't think
that would be fair um okay so one
interesting thing about this is that of
course this we can even produce this
this this data type um so uh sometimes
you know this example of how having a um
an indexed abstract expression or
abstract syntax tree this has been
around for a long time uh but one common
criticism of this is oh but you could
never actually use that in a real
compiler because how do you know that
everything is correct by construction um
and so one of the interesting things
here is yes you can use it in a real
interpreter right so remember this was
this is a real interpreter I can just
sort of type into it it's a normal
application that does all the parsing
and the type checking stuff um and the
reason it can can do that is no we don't
know that it's correct by construction
but we have a type Checker that checks
that it's correct and then as it checks
it produces the uh the
output um so uh we might imagine what
that that checking function is so here
I'm just going to leave the monad
abstract we can imagine a monad that has
error reporting and um and I think the
ability to produce unique uh identifiers
and things like that or no I guess it
wouldn't need that um I forget exactly
what the Monet has in it but it's it's
it's it's not very interesting um so so
we can imagine a check function that
takes one of these uxs and produces an
X um the problem is is that once again
we can't really just have this CTX and
this tie appear in the output because
maybe my input is an INT maybe it's a bu
um we don't know yet we're going to
discover that in the course of type
checking and depending on uh what we
find that tie has to be different so so
this type doesn't really work what we
really want is this
type right that we know the context
coming in because we we've seen all the
variables up until this point then we
have some Expression A ux and then we're
going to produce an output type checked
expression um for some tie so this works
for any um uh length of context and any
input context but it produces some type
out but we don't know what it is um this
would actually work work quite well
except that exists
doesn't um so um this is that's actually
an interesting area of research that
that that that I'm working on right now
um uh with a a researcher at University
of Cambridge Neil Krishna Swami uh has
and and and a co-author Joshua dunfield
have some very interesting ideas for how
to get existent hasco but we're not
there yet um so instead we might have to
write it in in continuation passing
style um which is it does your head in a
little bit the first time but actually
not nearly so much as Finn does at least
not for me um by which I'm saying Finn
is is ah I don't like Finn um okay so
here in check the idea here is that we
have a bunch of variables being brought
into the scope but then we have one of
these unchecked
Expressions um and then what we're going
to do is we're going to pass our result
into some continuation so here now I can
sort of use this magic trick and turn
exists into for all because hascal has
for all um and so if I pass this into
some function that that runs in my monad
and produces a result R then I can
produce that result R um and so this is
continuation passing style and it's just
a trick to get around the fact that
exists doesn't um I could also use
existential data types that would work
just as well I found um when writing
this I actually tried it both ways I
found that doing this continuation
passing thing to work a little bit
better um it's just sort of syntax
syntactic stuff it would everything
would work just fine with existential
types if you're more familiar with those
um so this is almost the type but not
quite um because there's not exactly
enough information at runtime to be able
to do this in particular um you'll see
that the input to this function is
really just the unchecked
expression um I also need to know at
runtime the types of all the bound
variables so I need to have information
about my context CTS X so to do that um
I use this type so this really is the
type um
and let's see so this sctx thing that's
the that's a Singleton for my Vector
right I need to know the CTX at compile
time to to sort of know that everything
is well formed and I need to know it at
runtime so I can be able to look up
variables in the context at run time um
I also need um over here in my
continuation so as essentially as a
result of typ cheing I need to get out
the type um so so again I can use that
in things like Printing and error
messages and such um okay so let me show
sort of an example of all of this in
action instead of trying to render it in
slides let's look at some code oh but
you can't see anything can
you let
me do that there we go that looks pretty
good okay um probably want a little
bigger I
think there we go is that is that big
enough okay
um so here's here's my check function um
you can see that there's a bunch of of
monad stuff but actually here um I've
generalized this a little bit to use
sing instead of sctx but this is very
much the type that we just saw on the
slots um the the outer one uh is um uh
specialized just to work over Clos
Expressions but of course internally we
need to generalize them um so I think
it's instructive to look at the
application case because that's where a
lot of type errors really surface so
coming in right we have this U app so
this is unchecked we know it's scope
correct but maybe this is true applied
to
one right that would
parse um so we that could be the input
um and then this K here uh
you know people in this room might think
that's a kind no it's k for
continuation um so and we also have the
the context so this is the this gives us
information about the types of all the
variables that are in scope so what I
want to do is first I'm going to check
E1 and when I check E1 that's going to
get me the functions type E1 is my
function as well as the checked type E1
Prime so if E1 internally Were Somehow
bad this step would
fail then we're going to check E2 in the
same context right because both a
function and an argument are in the same
uh lexical context in in this language
um and that's going to produce the
argument type arai and a type checked
type or a type checked term E2 Prime so
we know at this point that E1 Prime is
has no type errors and E2 Prime has no
type errors but we still have to make
sure that E1 Prime can be applied to E2
Prime
um so I have to look I let's look at
that
funai well I really hope it's a function
right not an INT so I'm going to check
I'm going to check for it being a
function and then if it is a function
now I have to check does the argument
type that's the type of E2 does that
match the expected argument type of my
function right if I have a function from
int to BU but I give it a bu I want that
to be an error also so and so there's
sort of two checks here on two separate
lines right the first is is it a
function and do the argument types match
if so then I can
continue the type of the of E1 applied
to E2 is resti the result of my
function and then my type checked term
is an application of E1 Prime to E2
Prime otherwise if any of these checks
fail then I issue a type error and so
here I have this very general you know
bad function application I could have of
course split this up into that really
should have been a function but it isn't
and then a separate error this is a
function but you have the wrong type of
argument be easy to do that I just
didn't
bother um okay so this is sort of where
where where the heart of it is now these
checks and my type Checker must be
correct let's say I'm silly and I forget
this
right so now I've forgotten to check so
now I have checked that it's a function
but I forgot to check that the argument
type um uh matches the expected type so
if I save this and then now go over here
let's quit and cabal
build could not deduce that the argument
um was
T1 when if T equals ARG and let's see is
there some other stuff there should be
one other thing
here oh here expected
type having T1 here but actual type is T
no there's something else funny around
here oh that's right T equals ARG Arrow
res so right so if we if we sort of
Imagine replacing this ARG aror reses
into this error message then we'll see
that um the actual type is ARG Arrow res
but we were expecting T1 Arrow res and
that's because we haven't proved that T1
equals AR right because my type Checker
is broken I've forgotten to do a check
now my code doesn't compile so I've just
eliminated the possibility of a bug in
my interpreter right if I wasn't doing
all this fancy type stuff type stuff I
might have forgotten this and if I did
so then I would produce bad code I would
accept programs from the user that don't
make any sense
right if I went into GHC and deleted the
line of code that does this and of
course there is just a line of code GHC
that does basically this um you know GHC
would still compile but now it would
accept bad programs right so we don't
want to do that
um okay so the the the reason again of
showing that is that this is really
where the rubber is hitting the road
this is why we do all this fancy type
stuff okay um
so I'm going to try to go a little bit
faster because I want to leave time for
for questions um okay so that was the
code so um so step four uh evaluation
right so we've type checked now we need
to evaluate the
thing well actually this one's really
easy um at this point we have this this
well this this um uh this
index and so as I'm transforming it from
one thing to another if I make any
mistakes at all I'm going to get type
errors um and so maybe easy as an
overstatement but um it turns out that
that doing evaluation with to Brown
indices is very easy to get wrong but
every kind of mistake I could think of
and I thought of many while implementing
this I was told nice type errors to to
sort of guide me in the right direction
right when I transform the from one form
to another I always need to make sure to
be preserving types and even with just
int and bu functions that's enough for
for it to sort of know when I've done
something wrong it' be very hard to get
the evaluation wrong but still get still
get my code to
compile um so after I got all of this
working I wanted to see is this actually
realistic can we do things that a proper
compiler or interpreter might want to do
um so I implemented common sub
expression
elimination um so so we can actually um
oh no I'm not going to I'm not going to
bother with it um we can we can imagine
um uh not imagine there there's a
command colon csse in The Interpreter
that will take an expression with
multiple common sub expressions and
optimize it um and even with all of
these types we can do
this um and again there were various
pitfalls but I was saved from all the
pitfalls I didn't have to worry about
shadowing I didn't have to worry about
substitution all of that stuff because
anytime I made a mistake I got type
errors um much easier to just get type
errors up front than having to think of
oh 50 programs to build up a test Suite
to see if my common sub expression
elimination is working um one
interesting part of this is is that as
you might imagine so we're processing
this this expression and I I need to
build up some structure which Maps
Expressions to um uh to names right so I
can see oh I've seen this expression
before so we need to have this mapping
um so there's a uh in in the unordered
containers Library we have this hashmap
type well I generalized it to be to map
from uh keys to values where the keys
and the values were indexed by some
other uh type I right so this is going
to be the type of of of expression and
so this was this meant that it was rich
enough that once I identified ah this
expression is the same as this one not
only do I know that the expressions are
the same but the types are the same and
so I could sort of merge them together
otherwise I need to use an unsafe coer
somewhere um so the way I did this is I
I literally took the code from unordered
containers and I just sort of downloaded
it from GitHub and changed the def of
the data type from that to that and then
just kept trying to compile and getting
and getting an error and then just sort
of adding what was obviously should what
obviously should have gone there um this
was really quite fun it was 2,000 lines
of code that I had no familiarity with
at all and it took me about an hour to
do all of this um which which was which
was great and the type errors were
really quite
nice um okay so pulling out of the weeds
a little bit so again if you fallen
asleep maybe now is a time to tune tune
in again um uh so what have I done here
so in my compiler now this isn't just
even about Lambda calculus but um what I
wanted to do is I wanted to identify a
data invariant the invariant was that my
expressions are well typed I want to be
able to to to know that that must be
true then I I think up a way of of
adding more types to my program to check
that data invariant so now I can be sure
that that invariant is always true even
as my even as my data evolves
um so once I add that to my data type
now I have to prove that my code
respects the invariant so what I mean by
this is um is like in my parer so
originally my my ux my invariant was
it's well scoped but then I had to do
all sorts of stuff to the parser to get
that to work then once my um internal
expression with my type checked
expression was well typed then I had to
make sure that my type checker was was
absolutely correct so that's what I mean
by prove my code respects the
invariant um and my common sub
expression Eliminator had to make sure
not to combine expressions of different
type from different areas of the
code um and then we can repeat we can
look for more properties that we might
want to add um so for example we I have
not you know done any invariance in in
my program that shows that evaluation is
correct right if I have this big
expression of type in I might
accidentally replace that with five
and and nothing bad would happen but
maybe I want to go through and and add
more types to be able to do that um okay
so this worked this was actually quite
uh bu building this the type errors some
of them were long but for the most part
they were really quite helpful there was
a few dark Corners that I could I could
describe if someone wants um of areas
that I think GHC really needs to improve
although I realize GHC has improved
since I since I wrote this since I wrote
stitch in in in one particular way that
really got me we now have Standalone
kind signatures which really really got
me at one point while doing this um so
we're we're ready for this now I will
say I want to connect this back I
mentioned there was this talk earlier
from um Marco um who whose last name
escapes me unfortunately but uh he's a
he's a s can you can you say that loud I
don't want s San Pelini thank you yes
okay um so uh so Marco is a developer at
habo
and and and his talk was about how it's
good to avoid fancy types um and I agree
with that too so I spend a lot of my
time hacking on GHC um g in the code of
GHC we use very few GHC extensions right
because it's actually easier to program
sometimes without all of these fancy
types but sometimes it's really
important that we we have something
right or sometimes we want to express
something that's hard to express so for
example uh typable that's that's a
component of GC that has a ton of type
extensions to be able to power uh
typable and type rep to enable Dynamic
typing um there's uh and there's a few
data structures within GHC that we sort
of want to have a little bit more
protection around that we use some extra
typing stuff um so we the idea here is
that it's good to be fancy but only when
you really care about something right in
my interpreter um if I wanted to sort of
change the way information flowed
through it it might be quite challenging
to do that at this Point um so it's
definitely better to write the thing
first make sure you know that it's it's
sort of working and then add the types
later um if you really want to
verify um okay so so I said at the
beginning that I spent a lot of time uh
uh thinking about uh dependent types and
hascal so that's sort of the M my main
driver is is that um I I believe
dependent types are the future um and
and that that it's something that you
know when we start teaching everyone to
program at age 10 they should be
learning dependent types
we are a long way from that now but once
upon a time I'm sure people would have
thought it was absolutely crazy to think
about teaching calculus to high
schoolers and yet that's quite common
now right so maybe there will be a day
that we teach dependent types to
10-year-olds I hope that happens um so
uh so dependent types so this has grown
to a team effort really started I I was
sort of pushing uh Stephanie wrick my my
thesis adviser uh was sort of the the
force behind me pushing but but it's
it's it's grown so so here's here's sort
of a a small constellation of people who
who have contributed this is all just in
the in the last year um so people sort
of toward the top and more code people
toward the bottom uh uh more more Theory
um several of these people are in
attendance um in this room at the moment
I see two of them right now uh uh
changor and Simon ning ning is is is
here at hll exchange um I think
Stephanie talked about dependent types
here last year um so uh just one one
thing I would like to comment while this
slide is is up so uh we see here on the
slide uh three women um and that ratio
of of women to men in the dependent
types work seems to be much much higher
than in attendance here at hascal
exchange um so in in in in software you
know we like to we we we always like to
think when there's a when there's a bug
there has to be there's there's
something that causes that it doesn't
just happen on its own right so uh I I I
don't have any Grand theories of exactly
why this is happened there's many
theories out there I'm not going to I'm
not going to go into that and I have
every belief that that everyone is is
always wants to be as inclusive as
possible I I really do believe that but
clearly there's something wrong
somewhere um and even if it's not us it
it sort of incomp upon us to do what we
can to make it not wrong um and and I I
I I again I don't I don't know exactly
what even what I mean by that other than
I just want to sort of raise awareness
around
this um okay so uh so grown to a team
effort um interestingly dependent types
aren't really weren't really that much
needed uh uh for Stitch um so uh we had
to use a few Singleton Singletons are
sort of uh a mockup of dependent types
um uh but uh it was only in a few places
it wasn't really so bad um so there's
lots of activity with GHC proposals that
are working in this direction some are
under discussion right now um so I
strongly encourage you if you're
interested in this uh to go here and
look at some of these proposals and and
we do want Community feedback because uh
you know GHC is is something we all use
here um and as new features come in they
will affect all of us and so we really
do want feedback there's this proposals
process it's very active uh I I think
it's been supremely helpful in figuring
out what's good and what what what's
maybe not as good for for inclusion in
GHC um so this coming uh uh school year
um I will be working on GHC full-time so
I'm normally based outside of
Philadelphia uh this year I've moved to
to Cambridge UK um uh uh Cambridge is a
lovely place but in particular um it's
it's where Simon works and so Simon and
I are s of spending a lot of time
confabbing about about you know
improving GHC uh and and you know I will
start be start start to bug him more and
more about dependent types as time goes
on um and and so and I expect the past
couple of years have been a little slow
flow in in this regard um I've had a lot
of teaching responsibilities I expect
that to to lessen considerably uh thanks
to some support from
tweo um so um uh I'd love to have more
people coming and contributing to to
this dependent types effort um
commenting on the proposals is a really
great way to start you don't need to
know type Theory to be able to do that
um H you don't need to know GHC
internals to be able to do that right
you're all users of hcll these proposals
are sort of you're facing so please
participate um so my goal so the so so
in type Theory we use pi to talk about
dependent types so my My Hope Is that we
will have dependent Types on Pi Day of
2021 um so that's that's still a year
and a half away so so right in America
Pi Day is is March 14th because we write
three and then 14 in the date um so um
so that's that's the hope we'll we'll
we'll see if we get there um uh uh I I
am hoping I'll say it publicly so now
now Simon has to has to respect this or
or or or put it down publicly my get I
know I know my My Hope Is by midwinter
to to have a dependently typed core
language inside of GHC that won't
actually affect users at all and then to
sort of work my way up from there um
okay and that's all I've got thanks very
much I'm happy for any questions
[Applause]
the function check the function check um
there was no guarantee that the checked
expression had any relation to the
unchecked expression that's true I was
wondering if you could also index on the
unchecked expressions and if that would
be easy so not without dependent types
um yes so so so just to sort of broaden
that out a little bit so in in the check
function um of course I could have just
ignored the input and then produced any
old properly typed thing as output and
that would still be accepted that would
still compile in in GHC and that's bad
right I would want to have some
relationship between them um doing that
I think would require much more power um
so I could probably mock it up with
Singletons maybe um actually probably
could I'd be surprised if I couldn't but
it would it would be ugly and painful
and so once we have dependent types be
able to do
that other
question okay thanks all for coming
[Applause]