[Music]
all right we're gonna go ahead and get
started welcome everyone my name is
Michael Simon welcome to this FP
complete webinar today we are going to
be talking about real a standard library
for Haskell I'm going to be shotgunning
this I'm going to be reviewing the text
chat and answering the Q&A section and
bringing up any questions live at
appropriate times this webinar is going
to be presented by alexei Cola Shevek
one of our senior Haskell developers
here at FB complete at this point I'm
gonna hand the floor over to Alexei
Alexei please take it away
hi everybody good time over to you
my name is Lexi as Michael said I will
be talking about Rio library I will be
talking about it from the perspective of
a user of the library thanks to Michael
who one of the main contributors and
authors of this library so I'm gonna
mention a little bit about the concerts
it's it introduces and I'll talk about
what does have what sort of promises or
souls and how we going to be using it I
will the second half of the talk will be
an application demo application that
I've created just for this webinar so we
can actually see some classical examples
so where does the real name come from
it's a not from Rio de Janeiro although
the picture on github is nice to look at
the name actually comes from a reader
design pattern with T in IO there is a
bitter ambiguity which is coloring half
cup packages there is a real package
there is a real module and there is a
real data table but it's very
unambiguous whenever you bring some
context in there
so what is the real first of all it is a
prelude replacement as you already heard
it exports a lot of functionality
from prelude it's doesn't try to
re-implement everything like some other
problems do well what it does it tries
to hide everything that is not that good
or safe for instance partial functions
there is no functions that interact with
the terminal or handles important by
default I'll talk about a little bit
about it later there is a lot of imports
of the functions that I normally have to
be imported manually if you deal with
just regular Perley and they imported by
default like strict fault and proxy and
stuff like that there is a whole
collection of functions that are not
available in base this is just a very
short list just to give you an idea
something like not worth that will do
efficient removal of duplicates broken
fixes some broken functions and it also
lifts all of their iOS are your actions
from restricting to IO to monitor lift
IO or mod modded IO or monitored lift IO
and there is a little bit of tension I
want to bring to durable atomic rights
check very cool functions police check
mark but I'm not gonna be talking about
those in particular in this webinar also
Rio is a collection of vetted libraries
that were well known in the community
they've known to be fast safe and they
work very well together
they this is a full list of dependencies
over your library and most of the
functionality in this libraries will be
exported by Rio some with slight
modifications some directly what sort of
problems does view yourself besides the
prelude replaced in the collection of
libraries it brings together best
practices that we found over the years
to work very well for develop in-house
programs
and libraries and also design patterns
and I will touch upon each one of those
points in more detail in a little bit so
first we'll start with consistent
imports I'm sure a lot of you written
code like that where you import by
string you import the type and then you
call if I import all the functions and
then same with containers or an order
containers who lists or what have you
now you can do important directly from
real and it doesn't provide lazy stuff
like lazy by strings or lazy maps just
because if you want to write efficient
programs usually don't need those and as
such you can still import this not
re-exported style by Rio but you will
end up editing an independancy to your
COBOL file package demo file and you'll
have to do it manually so as I said by
string map set stuff like that is
imported by default from if you do it
for real
all these re-exports do not export
partial functions or anything unsafe if
you want to use that it have to be
imported manually so for example if you
want to use an indexing function from
vector that will throw a runtime
exception from your code this is
considered partial it will have to be
imported many and I will say you know
try to avoid it at all times
Oh cast there of the time safe
counterparts for all functions there is
also concept of I said and they have to
be imported explicitly as well for
modules in ton checked and what this
means is these functions will have
certain preconditions to them that you
violated they will behave very
dangerously and will unsafe functions I
even worse
that they if you violate the
preconditions you you can break a fridge
with transparency costs egg falls so you
better really be sure that you don't
violate these preconditions whenever you
use that safe right for instance you got
to make sure that the bounds are correct
I mean why would we even export them if
they're not that safe well for
performance reasons sometimes if you're
sure your code is correct you can switch
to unsafe variants and use those for
performance here's a list of extensions
jigs and extensions that we consider
safe you can find always an updated list
and you have patients read B you can
include him globally in a cabal file or
if you prefer turn them on turn them on
manually at the top of the file it's up
to you that's all I have to say about
those now there is also GC flags which
are good to turn on by default these
will prevent you from shooting yourself
in the foot and help with compatibility
across GHC versions and for production
and continuous integration it's also a
good idea to enable W error if you want
to start using real it's very easy there
is even a template for a stack and can
run and it will create a skeleton for
you with all the structure that you
might need this test the application for
having a quick start the application of
our library fuse all by some other means
whatever you prefer just at every you as
a dependency to you package the yellow
or cabal file and as well as extension
if you wish the reason why I bring this
slide up is also to point out that real
works with
GT version 8 and up
zero and up so 710 and below an
unsupported another design that now I
want to switch the design patterns and
first one is going to be exceptions
which is very touching and very
excessive not sensitive but very
important topic in half code because it
can be complicated the example I have
over here is not has nothing nothing to
do with reordan it just one of my
favorite examples of how Haskell can
programs can fail either silently with
just overflows or with pure exceptions
for reason so what do we say just
whenever you write applications is if
you're at a pure function and it has to
fail fail it purely with a explicit type
level limitation that it may be or
either if you want to be more general
you could go with the throw throw M
which will unify with either and maybe
as well
avoid error this should be reserved for
something truly impossible that can
never happen
throwing pure exceptions
I mean throw an exception from pure code
is also frowned upon
try try to avoid it and the fine can be
used as a temporary placeholder but it's
way too easy to just forget about it
avoid it as well some like to use except
for exception handling and these can be
dangerous so there is a very few blog
posts also written by Michael and some
other material on mind that hopefully
can convince you better than I can but
if you're dealing with the exception in
[Music]
you know yo chill then just stick to our
because except he can give you an
expected results and it also doesn't
show you all the exceptions that can be
thrown because there's always a
synchronous exceptions and there is also
such demons mask is
cannot be cannot be represented with
type of so the next thing is catching
exceptions this was how we throw
exceptions catching exceptions is if you
do that just just a nail i like michael
says bite the bullet and I should do
build a beautiful state or dealing with
kitchen exceptions it's better to stick
with a or something like I Oh which can
be reader the or real you never recover
from a synchronous exceptions in fact
Rio does not provide it doesn't export
any functions that can allow you
catching synchronous exceptions so for
good reason because you should never
cover for them or they suggest ways to
use bracket pattern finally footing with
resources and catch and handle which
will ignore the asynchronous exceptions
and communications exceptions always use
their we've the style pattern which is
only seen which means they will be
exported from the Rio whenever there is
some sort or resource allocation and you
will see two throughout the examples
there's also this new thing you might
not haven't seen with modern least i/o
it's fairly new just as a real library
is burning you a couple years old there
is a blog post that goes into a little
bit more detail I'm gonna show you how
to use the matter going to explain what
actually does but to give you an a just
a feel for it it's it helps you deal
with the exceptions and with this with
style actions under lift your provides a
lot of functions gathers together quite
a few libraries like a sink
STM and it provides this
functions that they have except in the
lifted fashion they will have a
restriction on a tie oh come on I had
looked at you instead of being
restricted to IO this allows us to use
this functions for all of the things
I've described before like real for real
reader team email and so these modules
they are all imported by default
whenever you do import real this will be
all available to you together with real
directory angry or directory can be
imported explicitly if you need it but
the point is all of this functionality
that you normally need for writing
applications will be available for you
right away and they're all very very
good libraries so it provides a really
good start so what is the reader design
pattern first of all it allows you to
specify a global immutable environment a
global variables if you come from sea
world you will have just you know Const
variable whatever in there somewhere
at top module these we can do the same
in haskell by using unsafe perform a oh
but that's pretty ugly and you don't
want to change this you don't want to
recompile everything if you want to just
change it at some point there is also a
way to do it with compile flags that
becomes very complicated and I will
start with as much as possible good way
to do it is with the video pattern so
whenever you have more restriction on
your function you can always access this
in this environment and if you thread it
through all of your functions this will
become a global environment for you so
how do we pass this this environment
again with the bonnet reader this solves
this problem very well if you follow
your functions have this then you have
access to this global and global
environment there is a star
of how to do it otherwise you know
double implicit primaries they have a
very surprising consequences and I don't
recommend using that also you can pass
it as an extra argument to every single
function but that becomes very
complicated for refactoring and not very
composable if you wish so something
really works we found is reader T used
all the time and let us down yet
I could thing we can ryokan generalize
to monitor and if you want to just stick
to REO you can absolutely do that and
I'll give you a couple examples when
it's one versus another we also have a
global mutable state that we have to
deal somehow with a game radio pattern
helps us with it all we're gonna do is
just use explicit mutable variables so
they can live in our environment we try
to avoid state T and writer and stuff
like that because first of all
efficiency tends to slow things slow
things down
nested stack of transformers can be
confusing to a lot of people and also
gives you an impression that it's pure
we didn't when it's really not I'm gonna
do all too much on this topic but the
point I want to make is that reader T
solves our global mutable state problem
very well and I'll have a very nice
example there showing that so now we get
to the actual example which is the fun
stuff I like to look at the slides and
bullet points this is the applications
that we can use for demo in real this is
a web show
probably trying to solve is we have a
web server that can spawn off shells
like a bash
Sh what have you and using WebSockets it
can communicate over all that traffic to
to the terminal that is terminal
emulated the leads net users web browser
so you can open your favorite explore my
browser in going to your your private
web server and if you have a minute
authentication you can just go ahead and
log in through the web so how do we do
that the first thing we need to do is
create a Sulha terminal in order for for
it to work this will work only on unix
but that's okay we don't care about
windows just getting really works with
windows as well but this particular
example is not here i want to bring up
the first usership of real it's a fairly
straightforward function it takes an
epoch token that we used that we will
use to identify a terminal in in our
global state our global staple the wedge
state which is just my RF and you can
see that it is our environment in the
real model so we can access this state
by getting the the ref and we can modify
it as we please so what do you want to
do is we want to create a terminal which
essentially what it does it cause a
system call that will give us back to
file handles
or to file scriptures that will turn
handles that's not terribly important
the important part is that whatever we
get these two handles we need to make
sure that we close them otherwise you're
going to be a little resource so we have
to use this bracket pattern which we
acquire resources the term
that contains two handles and then we
close it the you notice here we close
these handles and at the same time we
also modify Lin global state we and our
terminal to our global state and then
once we're done whatever there might be
caused by an exception or by user type
in exit we delete that the terminal from
our state great this should work fine
we have properly resource cleanup we
it's all accepted safe there is a little
bit problem that not were well component
if this function will be called only
once with this particular environment
that'll be okay but we gonna be coming
with a different environment so what we
can do in order to resolve that is
switch to monad reader just an example
show here real wish state is essentially
same as a reader th state mail because
Rio is just a wrapper around so if we go
further we can go ahead and make it more
general in particularly switch as I said
to monad reader but normally we wouldn't
be able to do that because we using a
bracket pad this is where Mona on leaf
that you all comes into play it allows
us to to use a functions like bracket
and catch and we can use it for more
like real for readers now here's
something funny happens we have to
define has where state class which is a
micro lens gather which that we can
instantiate for any other environment
and do it will allow us to get the state
from whatever environment we have there
is a little bit of difference here we
can store you call a square
using you is unnatural it does add a
little bit of boilerplate but we with
this approach we get our function to be
more general very composable and we see
what our function does by looking just
other types of know that it exceeds
their state from the environment namely
here and nothing else which is really
cool so why is this has a pattern
simpler I'll try to convince you all
although this example looks like it
makes it more complicated but let's look
at this we have two data types we can be
using in our example it's a session that
we can create for every terminal session
that will be spawned off and we have a
global environment that we will be using
throughout our web server which has the
state and a log function and a session
will have a context and a connection
which the web socket wrench with this
general approach that we have here with
to the terminal we know that it's not
gonna these functions will still eternal
does not access any of these any of
these variables which is which is great
it proves our safety and making
instances of this this class is fairly
straight code use use a little bit of a
lens magic here's a little bit more
complicated example which uses our
previous function we see the terminal
this with shell will actually spun out
the actual process so how does that
gonna happen we create a terminal to the
terminal which which doesn't have any
processor on it all it does gives us two
handles
we can do it for communication and
recall Prats which will create a process
context so we can use it to adjust our
environment variables and our current
directory for the process of invoke we
can also use that process configuration
that trail to adjust our standard
input/output create a session and group
which is required for if you want to
emulate the emulate terminal and
obviously CMD narks is what we used it's
this example it's only gonna be batch
with empty arguments now and actually we
get to the point where we call the
process it will spawn out of the process
and now because we have imported by
default with real async library we can
call race which is an amazing function
and allows us to wait for the process to
finish and at the same time do something
else with that terminal so basically
what it translates to is either our
process exit or dies or something else
or we stop dealing with this terminal
for example a user closes the browser
tab you know this actions will cause
this action to either terminate properly
on with an exception but at this point
the other one will be also terminating
and all of the functions with Prats
which internal will clean up their
resources properly not gonna memory
resources great and it returns back if
you see either exit status how our
process actually or whatever our on
terminal function returns which is again
be unit all right we can almost done to
our terminal
LM emulator they want you know
is why did we need that global state in
the first place and particularly we
needed for resizing determine imagine
the user resizes the browser or the tab
itself and the size of it changes so we
need to change make the terminal
emulator or now web server where is it
so what do we do we get new size we get
the our global state by using the same
same bearing has by state we read the
state from our by reference we look it
up if we have that state for this opaque
token great we can go ahead and issue a
system call for changing this size of
this particular terminal that's why we
needed to keep around the found
scripture inside water and this is the
the cold makes this is the the function
that will be doing the resize a uses
some epiphyte called ioctl which is not
terribly important here they you know
wanna bring up is this function log
debug this is how we do logging a
unified login with wheel on the next
slide I'll go a little bit more detail
about it but I want to point out here
this display and how we easily
structures log messages so they besides
log debug their wrestling's like logging
full of boring like Earth and other
whatever and there's this scary type
signature for these log functions
reality is not too scary we can dissect
it's a listener because it has to do
some printing he has a monorail
environment that has a lot function and
it has a call stack because at some
point we might want to report the
location of the source where they this
login actually was invoked and it takes
a utf-8 builder which is the message
that we trying to log and underneath it
is simple Li the new type wrapper around
the body builder and using class display
we can instantiate for our custom
datatypes a construction of this manager
sweetie pie builder
here's an example for that terminal size
pretty the previous slide where we had a
width and a height and here we just use
a helper function display show that use
the show instance for the your like with
the height and combine them together
with a non-oil any great thing about
this whole thing is be it is very
efficient and it is also thread safe so
you're not gonna have any message that
jump on each other this is the reason
why we don't have any scope functions
that deal with standard output and
standard error whatever it seems like
praying to put through because these are
not rape and is they would interleave
with login now some people ask what if I
have to design a tui I don't know editor
or when terminal male program whatever
you can still use all of your natural
you think dealing with their handles
that used to we just create a logger
function that goes to test has to be a
and done you have proper very important
to the using logger print whatever to
you you want there is a local things
with the logger that we have available
is lock sticky if your blogger is the
terminal having if you are in a terminal
you can
I keep logging at the bottom while other
long messages will continue going
upwards it does which is useful for for
progress reporting let's say you
uploading the file and you want to show
how what's the percentage Co supports
colors and it's terminal aware so if
it's a terminal it will turn out
calories and blocks ticking stop in
order to use these what functions we
have the highest log funk class which we
can instantiate and all know is how do
we get to our log function the better
question is how do we create this log
function lot options handle is a
function that allows us to create
options for the log function which takes
handle which as an example here we pass
has to be out and a boolean which means
birbal's now and then we can modify
these options with a few modifiers
available in view here we just update
the log level info and then we create
the actual log function with this option
this creates a log function again the
same with our pattern because there is
some resources it needs to be cleaned up
once we done log in we create our state
then we create our environment and then
go ahead and run real on our environment
logging function state and whatever that
action action might be doing so this is
pretty much and I'll show how you deal
with a simple application in real
there's gonna have a helper data type
simple app that you can use if you just
want to really quickly start using
logging stuff the cooling about what
from its composable because it has no
notes you can combine loggers together
as a consequence if you don't
using login you can just pass me empty
and done there's not gonna be any
logging and all the log debug like very
other functions what we just ignored so
there is something I made it back when I
was talking about the terminal emulator
do wanna mention it
we can use that we do use conduit in
order to do communication with the
terminal that we created it spawned off
if you don't know countries that's
that's fine it's fairly straightforward
here this is just a way to throw by
strings at the terminal that we spawned
off basically is how we feed it with the
input the commands and then whatever
comes back from the terminal we can pull
it out we using this and this makes two
terminologies I essentially calls the to
determine of communiques package and all
the Scriptures determine their handles
this is not particularly important but I
wanted to add it as a complete for
complaints the the important part about
this is that we were able to create
within one module in under hundred lines
of code at terminal and later that we
would be able to put in the suit
contained package in foolish and reuse
it for other purposes like whatever you
need the terminal emulator and in fact
this we never used real if we really
wanted to we could just drop off the job
log in and use the just that process and
like a zombie style and actually the
same function but I mean we already used
real which what I would suggest anyways
now there is more to it because we need
to talk about the web part of this web
web shell if you don't know yet yes or
I'm just gonna run really quickly
because this is not really a vehicle to
talk but so you can hear how this all
works
how eventually the only thing that we
use from Rio here is this ETF egg
builder for creating a text token hex
encoded token so we create an app app
which has our brush environment we have
a few routes this is our home yes have
static files and this is how we do
website communication of the terminal
and this is going to be a restful post
to post request to resize the terminal
and for the front-end how I may point
out that we can be using H term which
developed at Google which is JavaScript
application for terminal emulation only
going to be doing is piping all the
communication to and from it from our
process running on server and this is
the whole HTML that we could have this
is going to be our communication with
WebSockets I'm going to talk about this
function in a little bit this is our
post resize and here how we can call
real from yesterday and Michael is
working on making it a little bit more
friendlier and if I log in with with
years old and at some point they'll be
even working better together but at this
point what we do is we pull out
environment from your application and we
drown Rio and in this we can use login
we log in and call the resize terminal
that we've seen before
here's the attempt communication other
reason why it's called attempt because
say it might not be a WebSocket and
which case it will fail but if it is
great we create a process context which
we can modify if we need to for spawn
enough how we create our session with
the process context and environment now
we need to call WebSockets from a yes or
WebSockets but if is a type signature
reroute the connection that's what I was
mentioning earlier whenever you restrict
the environment it makes a little bit
less composable so we have to do a
little bit of trickery here in order to
make real work or any other reader for
that matter - to get to deal with this
environment so all we do is just use
with a we reader and lift wheel and we
can use our real action together with
the the WebSockets that has a real
career connection nothing too
particularly crazy here also we need to
do communication with our web browser
with WebSockets here is the function
that we have available the count dates
which is a source in the sink again same
problem the environment is restricted to
connection that's all right we can go
ahead and create this class highest
connection which would be a good idea to
push it upstream as well into website
into your web sockets which would
simplify least 11 and again with reality
and transpired function from conduit
allows us to change the reader T into
the the monorail connection they will
play around with you if you don't
understand right now it's
but not important if you do great a
party
the point is we have two candidates now
once they became a useful getting
information from the web browser and one
that we can type your information to the
web and remember we had the same thing
from the our suet terminal so all we got
to do really now is connect them
together and this is what this
communicate function is gonna do which
is get called right here communicate
[Music]
this is our with shell function that we
so before all it does cause our bash it
gets the terminal back that we can use
to get our conduits for communication we
add them together with the ones from the
WebSockets mystic in the middle at the
boundaries there we can use to look at
what's going on what's being moved back
and forth which is function right here
it does a little bit of person just so
it control sequences that are readable
by humans but that's not important and
then what it does it runs this countries
there is one country for going
downstream and one going upstream that
has to be working concurrently and if
one of them dies the other one was
supposed to that as well which is what a
race is going to do for us we also catch
an exception
the WebSockets exceptionally in case so
we have a graceful termination and we
use our logger in order to record that
as well and of course
so we don't get these 500 errors in our
in our browser we catch all exceptions
and
and except of course they're synchronous
exceptions which is important and we
recorded a record that as well over here
and all of these runs inside of the REO
in the his environment web shell web
session which has all of the stuff that
we've talked about before it has a lock
function it has our global mutable
environment a has configuration and
terminal handles and so basically this
is the the meat of our web shop
so before we go any further I want to
also show you how we initialize all this
stuff how do you want to stick it all on
the slide so I'm gonna drop into beam
and we'll look at a main function this
is the part that gives everything
together
we can parse our command line arguments
like port
log level host basically this is how we
customize our environment and this is
what we do in name again this is
basically configuration however you
wanna do it such as top of the parcel
applicative as well as a choice of
dealing with configuration file if you
want to go that route we use those
settings for setting up the warp server
the port the host and then as we saw
before we create our log function we
create our global state environment we
put it into the ESL app and we start our
server and that's pretty much the whole
WebGL application that we have we'll be
good to thing to have a demo of this
application I would assume you a seed
and in fact
this whole time we were using this web
shell because this thing is actually
running instead of the browser which is
really need and I don't ask what can we
do well we can then go deeper as Leonard
DiCaprio said we can do a stack run rush
verbose and
log alive well save the bug and port
3000 won because we already have run out
of 8,000 and we can just open another
tab 3,000 won and we have eruption which
is really cool I think
and there's many instances of it will be
supported and here was what I was
mentioned too if we resize it it needs
to let the server know that the size has
changed so I will go ahead come back go
ahead and kill our server
well actually we go like here and we
graceful exit we will see here that the
Prats function told us logged how long
this process was running which process
was and you'll see this logger in action
he was logging everything that we
communicated this is the exit and how
the process fixed okay let's go slides
everyone's very impressed with the twist
by the way before I sum up I want to say
a little bit about the package called
the orphans this provides orphans
instances for their for real data type
monitor logger is one thing that is used
extensively if throught some tools we
share REO has an instance of a few if
you need
when a resource have you successful that
which is comes very very handy this in
particular I didn't find useful but some
some people mine
yeah the demo you seen that and so I
want to sum it up so we have a little
bit of time of questions first of all
Rio is an amazing package I want to
thank Michael very much for it we use it
lately extensively on projects in that
epoch complete and think not only to
Michael but other contributors of course
it is very well established patterns and
it's very easy to get started with them
documentation is very good and they
follows the also the pattern if it
doesn't compile it's most likely it's
broken
there is also questions sometimes that I
mean there are dependencies I don't want
to depend on all those packages like
back to package and containers I'm gonna
be using them well let's find it say you
your library doesn't you can select
selectively choose for instance only if
they are in that process which could
potentially down to the terminal example
but then why not to not to use Rio
depends not that expensive and most of
those dependencies are already wired in
base so why not one example I will say
that we will not gonna shine is if
you're not doing much concurrent so
exception so you not doing any
side-effects period it's some pure
category theory library then library we
was different not for you but you can
still use the concepts that describes
you really describe with that I think
one lastly now definitely mention is it
works very well for teams because
working on a large project it provides a
consistent way for all of your
co-workers to follow the same pattern
and not step in each other's toes smooth
them with different classes I'd like so
well thank you very much I think that's
it for me anybody has any questions two
people wanted to confirm whether the
source for the project and the slides
themselves will be available for
download after the presentation slides I
can make them available the source for
the demo application is right here I can
go ahead and clone and improve it if you
wish cars do whatever you the slides if
you if like I mean you have available as
well and this presentation is also
recorded I believe it will be okay so a
question is how much effort would you
guess would it be for a 100 module
Haskell code base to use Rio instead of
Prelude how much effort well they would
actually simplify it would reduce your
number of modules the number of code and
how much effort it would be very simple
I think first because it will import
everything that Prelude has and if it
breaks a compilation that means it
probably fix some bug for you so you
definitely because they will point out
all your partial functions it will force
you to use unified logging a lot of
times it will enforce good patterns on
you what refactoring is in in Haskell I
mean we have type system which is
amazing you'll tell you everywhere it's
broken I would never dare you do
something like that in Python what kind
of adoption by community or industry do
you have how big do you count on it to
be
I don't expect the real of Rio to be
growing it's that's the question but how
how popular will hope to become
definitely extremely popular I don't see
any reason why you should use anything
else if you fried in an application it's
just so straightforward and today and so
on the numbers front I don't have any
kind of numbers to back up how many
people are using it we definitely aren't
pushing it for a library dependency well
we may start using it as a library
dependency but many things on has on you
know uploaded the hackage wouldn't be
depending on Rio just by design right
now so it's hard to tell how popular it
is at the moment I would adapt a little
bit as a rock looked up there are a few
packages they already depend on Rio and
there is a there brings a lot of things
together like servant and I forgot the
name wood and a few standard things
based on Rio as well and in fact I've
used the servant and amazon co with
three or four weeks absolutely fine do
you have any working application online
or on github that uses Rio yeah it's
there is one selector right here I don't
personally for now we've used in close
source projects which plan to be open
source in the future so there will be
definitely project at the complain
worked on whether it will be open source
the there are few that are already
available that develop other people all
you can do is just go to this
documentation and look up the reverse
dependencies and you'll see packages
that usually you for newbies does it
make sense to go to Rio from the Rio
wrap from the beginning or would you
suggest to come by this library after
experiencing some of the problems and
intends to circumvent mitre you might
have to learn a little bit up front but
it'll be definitely worth it namely the
reader pattern
and dealing with with io if you can deal
with that then just go with with real if
you if this is totally new before and
you don't know how to do with the
recursion release and yet really a
little bit too early to motivate Rio as
a new type the reason is type classes
like monad lager define their instances
on Reader T to defer to the underlying
monad can you explain why this force is
a new type it seems like monad lager
should just default to IO Michael you
want to answer that because you are the
author of those I think I actually wrote
that sentence so yeah I can probably so
I don't quite understand the end of it's
all just explained what I was talking
about you you end up having the what we
call the the N by n problem with a
Cartesian explosion problem when you
start dealing with MPL style type
classes when you're defining the type
classes on the monad itself as opposed
to an environment contained within the
monad every time you define a new
capability you want to define a new
monad transformer which is usually the
new type I think that's where the new
type concept is coming from so you
define a new monad transformer and they
need to find a new type class to go
along with it let's say that you
introduced the new transformer foo T and
then you define it Mona type class monad
foo what you're going to end up doing is
defining a monad food type class inste
type class instance for reader t @
writer T and all these others that defer
to an underline instance of monad foo
and if you look in the MTL that's
exactly how it defines all of those
instances for the core type classes this
all works fine if you add a single
package on top of them TL the problem is
if you have a food package in a bar
packaged in a bad package each defining
their own mono transformer and their own
mono transformer and in their own MTL
style type class now you've added three
different combinations and now the
combination of these different things
needs to be defined and pulled together
in one place you start getting into
orphan instances if in place of all of
that you just define the these type
classes on
inside a reader tee and said a monad
reader you bypassed that problem
entirely and if that seems a little bit
vague feel free to hit me up on Twitter
or somewhere else afterwards and I can
give you some more examples I hope that
was clear cool thank you
sure let me see so far everything we
have seen in the default logging pattern
looks like we'll be very compatible by
default to serve as a base for something
like open tracing implementations that's
cool I think s'tel X of one what are
your thoughts on using this as a default
Lib for something like this don't fully
understand the question could you yeah
I'm also having a little trouble
understanding so Xavier if you could
type it and type in a clarification I'll
read it again though so far everything
we have seen in the default logging
pattern looks like it will be very
compatible by default to serve as a base
for something like open tracing
implementations what are your thoughts
about using it as a default Lib for
something something like this I guess I
part of it I'm confused about is open
tracing yeah I'm not familiar with open
tracing myself either
again let's follow up on that one
afterwards so follow up on currently
being answered which topics do you need
to understand to use real exceptions
reader pattern and that's pretty much it
and everything else that you want to use
you know you get back true containers by
strings it actually simplifies a lot of
things for you one thing I'll just throw
in is that it depends on which subset of
the REO package you want to use if you
just want to use it as a prelude
replacement you don't have to really
know anything you can just start using
it yeah do you want to start using the
logging capabilities you're gonna have
to understand a little bit about
alternative monads as an using REO
instead of i/o that's where I want to
follow up the REO doesn't provide any
put-put strong printing so you sort of
need to know a little bit about logging
if you want to debug your application or
you want to
with it yeah unless you important the
regular print statement yep and one
other thing ever in Genoa if they want
to play around with this library you can
use this function that we've got in
there called runs simple app which is a
nice easy way to get started with Rio
very quickly and I'll type that into the
chat okay are there any good tutorials
for exceptions and for the reader T
pattern I can provide the links to those
if you want Alexi yeah I'll just be
completely as clear there's a few of
them yeah and I think we have them
linked from the new Haskell dot F P
complete calm as well I'm still in the
process of updating that website and
definitely Rio is gonna be front and
center on the new syllabus on that site
so I'll provide some links in the text
read in a second all right well we're at
the top of the hour
anyone have any last questions before we
call the end oh hold on there were two
others probably a question for Michael
recommendations for current users of
classy prelude ooh this one popped up
recently
well classy prelude be rework to build
on top of Rio or do you recommend moving
off of classy prelude okay yeah
definitely Lexi you mind if I take this
one from what I've heard
classic prelude might get the deprecated
in the future and we receded I think
that's a very good decision choice
spider doubt like classic polluted I
also like classy prelude but the fact is
it's it just it's true opinionated it's
too far off the beaten path of the way
things typically work in the Haskell
ecosystem if people I don't have I am
thinking of you know starting to
deprecate it at some point in the future
but if people have alternative ideas of
what they'd like to do with it I'm
definitely happy to discuss classy
Prelude as it stands right now is
already built on top of unlived IO so
the biggest hurdle to a dog you know the
biggest migration that we need to happen
has already been done if people have
some ideas on what they'd like to see
come out of classy prelude hit me up on
the issue tracker and
I don't have any solid answer yet on
what's gonna happen with it okay and
about with resource approach
what if usage of resources overlapping
so with resource cannot just be nested
you can use if you cannot describe your
pattern with the with the with pattern
you can use resource resource T that's
no fallback but that complicates a
little bit end I think my goals are
gonna blog post about that probably
somewhere okay not seeing any more
questions so I think we're gonna stop
here I'm gonna I'll go ahead and post on
my Twitter account links to the relevant
blog posts on I think it was exception
handling and the reader T design pattern
since I'm gonna be shutting down this
webinar and you won't be able to see the
text track so go ahead and check out
there for those links and if you don't
see it there just check out Haskell das
gold at Ft complete calm and poke around
until you find something but it'll be on
Twitter in like five minutes okay
awesome
alexei thank you very much for the
wonderful presentation audience thank
you very much for the group
participation and have a great rest of
the day everyone