hey y'all thought I'd show you what I've
been working on recently which is
managing and installing nyos using nyos
anywhere and terraform so vijoy made a
video on nexos anywhere a couple weeks
ago and uh one of the cool features that
they have is a terraform module so I'll
kind of go over how it works here and
what to do so we have a couple modules
we have the all-in-one the install the
rebuild and the build the install as
soon as terraform starts to manage a
resource it will go ahead and uh
completely wipe it and reinstall it um
using disco and nyos anywhere and
everything nyos rebuild we'll go ahead
and do updates using just the nyos
rebuild setup so if you just wanted to
update your systems using terraform and
manually install them that's a that's a
good approach but sometimes n OS
anywhere with terraform can kind of be a
little finicky so uh NYX build is their
helper function to actually build the
resource um like the system
closure the allinone is just those
combined so let me show you how that
works
so uh they just kind of go over a little
bit about how it works here and a basic
kind of setup that will work for pretty
much anyone except these parts usually
you don't need those um but some scripts
they got the how the NX OS Wiki is set
up on hetner cloud using terraform and
uh they kind of go over just how you
should do some stuff uh get
Ops sort of and uh just the modules they
provide here as well as the uh the
settings that you you can configure let
me show you how I have it set up first
of all the module actually requires a
custom uh version of terraform that you
set up here with plugins so because NYX
is immutable you actually need to
provide the plugins themselves and I
also needed JQ uh for some reason I
believe so as you can see with this
terraform in it commit so uh yeah so you
just say terraform with plugins in your
shell and then in this case you have you
I do p. n because otherwise it gets
interpreted as a raw
object uh from NYX so yeah we say
packages null so that's the null
provider and this is the external
provider so that's all you really need
um just to get started for just
completely raw networking no cloud
provisioning like hetner or vulture or
uh AWS nothing like that or any VPS like
Len node um those are all this is just a
complete default you would need to
provide those providers um plugins in
there which you can use the nxo search
to find um so next I'm going to go over
my actual terraform file so I just have
this directory here deployment nios and
these are a bunch of State files and
stuff uh doesn't matter too much what
really matters is the main.tf so this is
the only file I have here for this
deployment and in this case we have
these local variables and locals are
just yeah they're just variables just
for this file rather than variables
across files and and modules so we have
two variables here we have host files
and hosts so this will return a bunch of
Json files which I'll show you their
contents and hosts will take each one of
the Json files in the directory and
we'll go ahead and decode the Json and
variables so if we go here the path goes
up to directories into systems and then
searches down recursively a couple
directories until it finds a host so it
searches down two exactly so it finds
this file here and we go ahead and I'll
um use this so ipv4 is the address we're
going to override Um this can be public
public or private doesn't really matter
as long as it's accessible by you and
you have SSH keys to access it and the
host name is what we use to graft into
the actual build attribute so if we go
back into
main.tf um here we go ahead and do this
module and I'll kind of explain how it
works so in terraform there is a 4 each
block and this for each block goes ahead
and will do the same action on each host
that is defined by each file so I can
have 100 of these files and they will it
will run one deploy for each one in
parallel so that's how that works and
then we get the source which this is the
actual what the module like is built
upon so in this case we get the repo and
then this double slash says end of URL
into the file system of the repo cloned
and then this says Hey SL terraform SL
allinone um the system and the
partitioner Adder these are the the
build so this system Adder is the actual
implicit build that happens when you do
nixos rebuild switch with a flake uh it
just uses your host name uh environment
variable and graphs it into this this
configuration build top level and in
this case when you do a for each block
you can access the values in the keys
which the key is the current uh host
file path that we're accessing and the
values is the decoded version of that so
this each here is the value and the host
name so we go ahead and grab that host
name from that Json and we say build
that nexos configuration uh top level
and then the partitioner is just saying
hey do that for the Disco script so it
knows what script to run to format the
system next we do Target host which this
is just what system to run on and
instance ID we set to the same so if we
change the IP address it'll go ahead and
overwrite the system and completely just
install to a new system the same host
name so it just lets uh perform know
that we changed uh the IP address that
we want to deploy to so it'll completely
recreate everything and then finally we
actually get the key which in this case
is the path from the
main.tf uh relative all the way back to
the host. TF we cut off the host. TF so
that leaves us with systems slash you
know dot dot
slash um dos systems slash
this Equinox host. TF we get rid of
host. TF and we append Hardware config
and that is the path that ends up being
passed to um to this and that says we
can overwrite the generate config path
here so when we install the system the
system we're installing its Hardware
config will get overridden so you don't
need to do any manual cloning of that or
don't worry about that you can also do
it with nios Factor but I'm not using
that right now so that's a basic summary
of how it works let me show you how we
actually deploy so you go ahead and you
say terraform apply and here it is
running I only have one file that's why
the git is there because I didn't want
to override a second system that I don't
want to override so we have there's the
relative path running module on this it
uses nyx's build to build the system
closure as well as the um the setup so
it'll it'll create two resources when
you first create it it will create a NX
remote resource which this is saying do
the install as you can see the instance
ID is the uh is the IP address so we're
going to use no resource to create a
remote resource that will go ahead and
Destroy and install using nyos anywhere
and it will create a second resource
called nyos rebuild and this resource
has the store path of the system closure
but like I said when we go ahead and
cover the store path um if this changes
which when you run terraform apply it'll
do a rebuild which can take between 20
and 40 seconds on average for me um it
will go ahead and say hey this store
path is Tainted so it will destroy and
recreate the rebuild now if you destroy
the remote and you recreate it that'll
reinstall but if you destroy the rebuild
it'll actually just update so that's
what it does it says it's tainted and
must be replaced and it will replace it
with a brand new rebuild with a new
store path so it'll reinstall or it it
it'll update so if we say yes here it's
going to go ahead and it's going to SSH
onto the local network system and it's
then going to a
the image so it's downloading the KAC
right now and once it gets copied over
that's going to reboot the system into
the installer so it's as if you plugged
in a USB for a uh just a regular install
so here it is doing a k exac it waits
about 6 seconds and it will
reboot so it also copies special keys
specifically for this install to that
system and it's now going to wait
and it's going to start building the
system as soon as it's reachable
again okay so my router's been acting a
little bit weird recently so um yeah it
did not hand out the same IP address
that it had before that I was expecting
so I went ahead and changed the IP
address in the host. TF uh. Json file
and as you can see it triggered the
remote to be replaced because it started
the creation but in this case it's going
to do this destroy and then create
create replacement and it still hasn't
done the rebuild because that is the
actual bootstrap after the install so it
needs to create it so we say yes and
this is going to finish it and in this
case it's on the remote system and now
what it's going to do is it's going to
start copying all the paths now it's
formatting all the drives using the
Disco configuration which in this case
is an impermanent setup with uh butter
fs and it went ahead and built the
system closure and because I changed I
set it up so it automatically forces the
IP add address it's now going to just
set it uh to that IP address so I'll be
back when this is done copying all this
because this takes quite a minute but uh
yeah it'll do it all in parallel if you
have multiple systems at the same time
it'll just start new threads and do
multiple installs concurrently so it
should take roughly the same time for
the same number of machines as long as
you it's around 10 machines is is what
terraform tries to do at a time but you
can override this to be as many as you
want so I'll be right
back okay so now that it's finished
copying all of that um it goes ahead and
runs an actual deployment uh on the
remote so in this case here it copied uh
all the extra stuff it needed and it
said installation finished as you can
see here so now it went ahead and added
the IP address to the system and now
that it rebooted again and it's fully
installed it's now performing the nyos
rebuilt so in this case it's executing
the with all these flags and setup it's
just doing ni copy and it's copying the
closure and then executing that closure
there which when nexos rebuild actually
runs it just generates a bash script
that goes ahead and does all the changes
so now I ran it and in this case it
failed because I actually did not copy
my Sops Keys however it doesn't really
matter because it's still set up and it
still is finished deploying it just
failed that so uh if I copy my keys I
can reapply to show you what an update
looks like and I'll show you that in a
second okay so my router closed off
access but uh the install itself did
function and it is a system running on
on my network it's just uh acting a
little weird but if I if I were to go
ahead and just copy the keys over to the
system and I ran terraform apply it
would go ahead and build the system and
uh update so yeah I hope that was
helpful and I hope that you start using
terraform uh it's it's a good way to
deploy stuff and if you let's say in the
future had a kubernetes cluster that you
were going to add using k3s or proxmox
for an example which I do want to make
some videos kind of covering how those
work uh you can use terraform to set up
prox MOX
automatically um on the system so you
can use NYX OS to install prox Mox and
generate a a template VM and then use
terraform to copy that VM and have uh
just just infrastructure is code set up
and for kubernetes you can set up the
kubernetes cluster on NX OS systems and
then you can use terraform to uh
bootstrap Argo CD for giops yeah I hope
that helped and I hope you have a great
day bye