a few weeks ago my television crashed it
just completely froze up and the only
thing I could do was to physically
unplug it and plug it back into the wall
and in that moment of frustration I
shook my fist at the sky and said why
are televisions like that these days TVs
never used to crash they used to be
completely
reliable but In fairness they also used
to just show half a dozen channels and
expect you to show up when they were
ready to broadcast
yeah old televisions were rubbish we're
far better off in this modern world
where you can watch whatever you want
whenever you want it because your TV is
now basically a
computer even though they're less
reliable because your TV is now
basically a computer computers bring
possibilities and problems we know this
and it's the problems we're going to
look at this week because how do you
test television software I mean if you
thought making things work across
different browsers or across different
smartphones got complicated imagine
testing across a field of 50in plasma
TVs the solution to that problem is
actually one of the most interesting
practical engineering stories I've heard
in a long time this week I'm joined by
Dave Luchia and he works on a television
software testing Fleet that needs
realtime video processing geni web RTC
some lure scripting and a large fault
tolerant distributed erlang system for
scheduling and a few more things
besides sometimes solving a problem
needs one big idea this is the story of
many interesting interlocking pieces
that fit together all in the hope that
in future my television won't crash I'm
your host Chris Jenkins this is
developer voices and today's voice is
Dave Luchia
[Music]
joining me today is Dave Luchia Dave how
are you I'm doing great thank you for
having me on Chris oh pleasure you're
just off the um back of organizing an
llang conference is that right that's
right not just llang but ear langang
Elixir uh in gleam it was called code
beam light NYC we had it in Brooklyn New
York work this past Friday uh and it was
wonderful it was uh 10 talks half hour
each uh we had the creator of Sonic pie
Sam Aaron on to give her a keynote and
it was it was really a wonderful day
that sounds really cool uh yeah I I'm
looking for an excuse to get to New York
sometime so next year if you need some
to give someone a press party let me
know well this is wonderful marketing
cuz now we're going to have to you have
to have you on next
December I look forward to it
okay enough enough me pitching for uh
Free Conference passes the re I actually
heard about you cuz I was looking at a
similar conference over in Berlin and
you were talking about lure on erlang
and I thought well how did you get into
that and it turns out the answer is
absolutely fascinating through
television
software tell me the story of how you
got into TV software
development w okay well it's a little
bit of a a convoluted path uh and it
involves uh I guess a decade of building
relationships uh in the technology world
uh but I started out my career at
Bloomberg and Bloomberg is a financial
services company you might be familiar
with the Bloomberg terminal or maybe
Bloomberg News um I started out on the
Bloomberg terminal uh building trading
software um and about halfway through my
5 years at Bloomberg I moved over to
bloomberg.com um and back in 2014 we
rebuilt Bloomberg business week and
Bloomberg politics uh and it was just a
really fun time this was like kind of
right when react was starting to get
popular we built we built a an open
source framework that no one else used
called Bloomberg brisket which was one
of the first single page app Frameworks
uh in
JavaScript um sorry I this is convoluted
but I promise we'll get there um I
believe uh I met someone by the name of
Steph Baldwin who uh was Consulting for
Bloomberg um and we stayed friends uh
throughout the years I had since left uh
Bloomberg to do a bunch of media
startups I worked in sports betting for
a while um and after my most recent
startup I was looking to do something
new and reconnected with my friend
Stephen and in the uh eight odd years
that we had not and working together he
had started uh working at his
consultancy with a number of different
um media companies who built Smart TV
apps and while they were building these
smart TV apps um the pandemic hit and
they were having this challenge with
their their clients of um I'm building
an app I need to test it on an LG
television uh sometimes the simulators
are not so good and so we need to make
adjustments uh based on how it works on
the physical hardware and so what they
started doing is they were taking their
office space and they were sticking you
know a bunch of TVs in it building a
literal TV lab and uh you know they
would have someone go in they they point
a webcam at it and someone would go in
sideload a build onto the TV and go
ahead and test it and after a certain
point in time they're running into all
these challenges with making this work
and realized hm this could really help
our clients it seems like there's a
product here um and so ultimately you
know kind of stars aligned where um my
friend Steph was looking to to take this
idea and build it as its own company as
a product and I was kind of leaving a a
startup that I was at for maybe about a
year and looking for something new and
so we joined forces to to build what we
were calling TV Labs okay I can see I
remember going to Google's offices years
back this is right right in the Boom the
early boom of the smartphone thing and
they had walls of smartphones like every
model in a kind of library and you could
go and pick one off the shelf I can't
quite imagine that working with a 48 in
plasma
television that's right is is that what
we're talking about like just having to
have access to every kind of
Television pretty much yeah so uh if
you're a big enough Media Company you
probably have the budget to have a
warehouse somewhere that's just filled
with televisions a TV lab uh where it's
exactly for this purpose you have a QA
team and before a lease a release goes
out they certifying the release
internally by physically going to
televisions uploading a build using the
remote control to to test the television
and make sure that everything that uh
was built and is working correctly you
know on my machine also works on the the
physical you know LG TVs Panasonics uh
Samsung the Tien platform but not just
that we've got Apple TVs we have Roku we
got of course yeah the Fire Sticks and
all the Fire Sticks yeah there's so much
fragmentation Chris yeah yeah this this
instantly sounds worse than the multiple
browser problem of the early 2000s
that's right okay but okay so before we
get into what sounds like either a
nightmare or a fantastic source of QA
employment just if we can step back cuz
I don't know much about development for
televisions I'd always kind of assumed
they just wrapped a crummy browser but
what's give me a bit of an insight into
the world of this of a television app
developer what are they working with so
luckily uh most of it is web technology
and most of it is wrapping chromium and
and putting it into a t ision um the
problem is which crappy browser are they
putting into the television is the
question and uh you know these things I
you know I I wish I had more of a depth
of knowledge on you know the specifics
of every platform what I can tell you is
that most of these platforms are
wrapping something like chromium or
spider monkey uh they're shipping you
know a set of their own sdks um onto the
device but then each device is going to
have its own apis for um uploading
builds getting you know different uh
Hardware controls on the television you
know permissions access oh yeah because
it's not just that
like every television has a unique way
of talking to it and yeah yeah okay
sorry carry on that's right no that's
right every every TV has a its own
unique way of of talking to it some
televisions run the uh Android stack so
there's uh Android TVs there's also
Google TVs there's also the you know
chomecast uh there's also a new platform
that I believe is coming out uh might
have already come out or it's coming out
early next year I forgot um that's built
on top of Android which is the whole you
know Java stack and all that fun stuff
and app presumably is a flavor of iOS oh
yes they've got
tvos um then we've got the tyen platform
which is uh built in Java the apps I
think are also web apps um I'm blanking
on that right now but but the thing I
think you could take away here is that
every single manufacturer for the most
part unless we're dealing with the
android-based televisions and that's a
you know decent part of the market um
all are a different fundamental platform
for working and shipping on and so you
can imagine that there's Frameworks out
there that try to normalize you know how
standardized how you might interact with
each television but the devils in the
details and so as you start to you know
build out features and you know have
maybe more complex interaction or even
just simple things like your use of
flexbox it might you know behave in
surprising ways because it's this old
version of spider monkey running on this
one particular uh 2017 you know Samsung
taen platform and that has 8% of your
market share and that's you know hurting
your you know your bottom line revenue
these problems actually matter and so
what's interesting I think for us is
that it's not always necessarily the
newer televisions are the problem
because that's the first thing you think
is oh you must be having to keep up with
all these new televisions and new
devices every day no the the problems
that we hear from our clients the most
are can you Source this very specific
2017 Panasonic uh television for us
that's based out of Asia or based out of
South America or this one feature only
works uh in the UK um and we want to
test that you know can can you make sure
that we have a UK television that's
physically located somewhere in the UK
these are the types of problems do you I
mean we're kind of getting ahead of
ourselves but do you end up scrolling
through eBay looking for particular
model of
Television uh you can imagine there's a
a multitude of of places where we might
be procuring devices okay okay sometimes
it's uh you know if we're trying to get
something really fast it's friends and
family hey does anyone have this in
their basement that we can borrow for a
few days yeah Craigslist and that kind
of thing that's right okay okay so let
me see
I one other question before we get into
your solution is how large is this
Market because I'm instantly thinking
okay Apple have to have an app for every
kind of television Netflix have to um
but how many players are there there
aren't that many television channels
that have an app for every television
out there how large is your potential
customer base here uh I mean it's pretty
large when you when you consider it
globally so um I think in you in the the
tech world in the US we we tend to be
very us-centric but uh you know globally
everyone is consuming uh you know
whether it's television via broadcast or
television via uh you know streaming um
there's many different ways to consume
uh media on a television um the market
is is quite large and there's some
really big players the the Netflix's the
Amazon the NBCS the Warner Brothers of
the world uh there you know medium
players you know uh in Europe you have
you know Channel or the UK specifically
you know Channel 4 and ITV and and all
of those uh but then there's you know
South America which has a very different
Market uh so globally we have this kind
of massive market and uh each one of
them has different constraints and needs
and hardware and all these different
challenges and not all of them will have
the budget of apple or Netflix that's
right that makes sense okay so there are
I am a mediumsized television it
executive who doesn't have the budget to
have or even perhaps the physical space
to have a warehouse full of televisions
to test on certainly doesn't want to
hire QA Engineers who are sitting there
wandering around with a USB stick and a
controller you've been trying to
automate this process take me through
how you possibly automate this problem
away okay uh well there's 's many layers
uh to to go through here
um it might make sense actually to go
bottom up rather than top down if that's
okay okay yeah sure we can build up the
stat so let's start at the very uh at
the very bottom which is I have a
television and this television um it has
a screen uh it's got HDMI inputs for you
know plugging in different your your PS5
or maybe your your Fire TV Apple TV
whatever it is uh it doesn't have an
HDMI out right so getting video high
quality video out of the television is
not actually the easiest thing yes yeah
yeah
I okay we're right at the very first
hurdle and that sounds horrible what do
you do do you crack them open and try
and solder in an HDMI
output well I think you probably could
you probably could uh find a way to you
know do a hardware hack and you
know fiddle some wires I'm imagining
kind of like an action movie where uh
you you're trying to diffuse a bomb uh
Tom Cruz do it in a reasonable time
frame we tried to hire Tom Cruz to to
hack our hardware and it just uh it
wasn't economically viable let's say
that fair enough um you know or maybe
you got a little flipper zero here I
don't know
anyways the solution that we came up
with um is well twofold one there's
certain devices where we do have HDMI
out and for that uh an HDMI capture card
you can easily capture the stream in HD
you need to have um a particular license
not just anyone could be capturing HDMI
out because there's DRM on the devices
that prevents you from capturing it in
high quality so you need to be you have
to have a license uh to be able to do
this um and so for devices like set toop
boxes you know I'm talking about the
fire TVs Apple sticks of the world I I
feel like I'm repeating myself a lot
we're going to be hearing about set TP
boxes for the next
hour uh HDMI capture cards are the way
that we get the video out okay but for
televisions it's a little bit of a a
bigger challenge because televisions we
don't have that luxury and so for that
we use
cameras
now this imposes its own in and of
itself as its own challenge of how do
you get the um how do you get the screen
you know which is a you know nice uh you
know 1600 by 1280 rectangle um how do
you get that and flatten it because you
know a camera's lens is always going to
be slightly curved even for the you know
the flattest you know camera so you're
going to have you're going to have
radial Distortion around the camera
right yeah um you're also going to have
all that really white light from the TV
saturating all of the color um and
distorting the image and so if you
naively did what um my co-founders did
you know before form TV Labs you're
pointing a TV a webcam at a TV and
you've got this horrible you know very
saturated image that doesn't look very
nice it's not quite a rectangle around
the TV but kind of this weird distorted
rectangle um and so what we did is we
found you know cameras that were were
going to be really good for the type of
of light and image that we're trying to
capture and our goal always was you
should be able to stream a 4K movie
and for it to show up in your browser as
if it was um you didn't know the
difference it was just ship shipping
your television screen right into your
browser um so we're taking cameras we're
pointing them at televisions we're then
uh taking that video stream and uh we
actually have four cameras on our boxes
so we're stitching them together we're
applying different undistortion
techniques to uh flatten out the image
Stitch it together into that rectangle
why for cameras is this a resolution
issue it's not a resolution issue we
could do it with one um and I think this
is an early optimization that we made
that that maybe we we would change now
but uh our goal was to always have a box
a very tiny box that we could stack many
many many of them next to each other and
on top of each other so that we can have
a warehouse full of hundreds or
thousands of televisions okay and in
order to do that you know there's a
certain point where uh space becomes you
know a limiting factor for how many you
can have in your Warehouse unless you
have a lot of vertical
space that's his challengeing of itself
so what we wanted was to get the cameras
nice and close to the television so the
depth of our boxes could be very narrow
oh right yeah so you've got for you've
got to have a camera a certain distance
away from the television to be able to
see the whole thing like a parent
shouting at their child to sit back from
the TV that's right so you've got four
up close yeah okay so now I see why
you've got a stitching four video
streams back together problem right and
then we need to make all these different
uh you know you have four video streams
but they're overlapping uh they're going
beyond the you know the edges of the
television stream and so we apply
different computer vision techniques to
get that back to that nice rectangle we
apply uh an undistortion to flatten it
uh uh and and color correct it and then
what what ends up happening is that we
have this video stream that we can then
strip to your browser over web RTC
that's nice and flat and you couldn't
tell the difference that there were four
cameras there's no seam it it looks
perfect do you have the luxury of that
being repeatable like can you set those
settings once for the four cameras and
expect it to work with every television
that you've got a box for thereafter or
do you have to hand tweak each each
quartet
so there is some amount of hand tweaking
that um we did early on uh now we
actually have a pretty nice process for
um each one of our cameras um goes
through a um a tuning process before it
even goes into a box and then it's all
calibrated nicely and then when it's put
into the box is great but even with a
calibrated camera it's not going to be
pointed you know you know perfectly uh
you know head on to the television
there's always going to be a slight
angle and the TV might not be on the
mount perfectly U so we have this
calibration process where we cook a
button in our platform uh it shows a
special image that it uses to you know
calculate what's called homography with
a television um find that that perfect
calibration and then it uses that math
um the math that it deres from the
calibration image to find that perfect
uh point of reference yeah yeah yeah so
it's basically automa the test card of
old that's right that's right okay I'm
already getting a sense that we're going
to be solving so many micro problems
along the journey to getting this whole
thing working there a lot of mic
problems yeah that that is basically my
life yes so you asked you asked a
question that you know we're on a
journey to get there which is how do you
automate testing televisions but you
know it's like building an apple pie
from scratch you know we first must
invent the universe we first must invent
every single possible way to automate
interacting with the television
otherwise it will consistently break in
new and spectacular ways every day yeah
I guess that's a competitive Advantage
as well right so in the long run that's
right but yeah keep your life
interesting okay so you've reached the
point where you can stream web
RTC out of a televis
effectively but Chris wouldn't you
wouldn't you agree that it's pretty
boring to stream at television that's
not on you'd probably want to be able to
turn it on too okay yeah yeah yeah so
okay we have a problem of input now
which is okay we've got a we've got
these cameras pointing at a television
in a a dark box um you know in order to
do something useful with it we're not
even getting to the problem of uploading
you know your your build to the
television uh and we'll get to there
later uh how do I turn the thing on and
how do I navigate to a channel how do I
change the settings how do I do all
these things
um so we have um an IR diode in there
we've got something called CC which uh
allows you to interact over HTMI uh for
you know each individual platform we've
got web-based and grpc based protocols
for uh sending messages back and forth
to the television um you got all of
these different ways uh to interact with
the television that we have to solve
through hardware and we have to solve
through uh different types of apis right
on the box so I'm imagining the you say
the two main control two ways you can s
controls of the television are CC you
called it that's the one over HDMI right
that's right that I would guess is
fairly
standardized infrared are you are you
having to manually
train the specific remote control do is
someone sitting there when they buy a
new television going okay this is the up
but
record
that well I showed you my my flipper
zero for a reason which is this is uh
pretty useful for intercepting IR
commands and reverse engineering how
they work now some of them are published
right so every single television uh is
going to have slightly different IR
protocols for how you might send
commands uh so there's the basic stuff
like turn on Channel Down Channel up
there's more complicated things like
I've held down the the volume down
button uh that's now a long press uh
each television manufacturer might have
slightly different ways of implementing
that IR yeah that didn't surprise me so
we have a a PCB a printed circuit board
which has an IR actually multiple IR
diodes connected to it and we'll send
those uh IR signals over the IR diode
and that will communicate with the
television just how your very basic
remote would um you said that CC you
know that must be a very uh ubiquitous
standard and and you can imagine cc is
like uh again set up boxes we're going
to keep saying it Fire TV you turn on
the Fire TV that turns on your
television the way that that works is
that the Fire TV is sending a cc standby
command to the television saying hey
turn on um the unfortunate thing is that
while they are standard quote unquote uh
all behave uh slightly differently with
each manufacturer and not everything
always works as expected so we have many
different things on our platform that's
really tuned for the particular platform
to work most
reliably um and this actually goes with
communication in general we have to make
sure
that on any one platform not only can we
provide all the capabilities you know
ircc whatever um but also be able to
choose you know in certain situations
you might want to test IR but you also
might want to test the Roku specific API
for example so we have to provide all of
them um and we'll usually choose the
standard one for when you're uh trying
to interact through our web platform uh
the most reliable for that right I I I I
feel like this is going to be a
disappointing answer but I have to ask
the question do we at any point do we
get a robot arm pushing the buttons on
the
television so our first prototype was a
severed hand that would poke around at
the television uh sing from the Adam
family that's right again you know just
like Tom Cruz we didn't think that was
going to scale so we had to decommission
that that particular
path damn I was I was I was hoping that
in just a few cases you'd have something
like okay
so there's that makes me think of one
other big input that you haven't
mentioned to the television which is
power do you have some kind of power
control so you can hard read boot the
television when it
crashes uh we do not we have I think
five different uh Power controls for
five okay me that so okay um why is one
good
enough man
so okay I come from a a background of
LLG and elixir and the beam and the
philosophy is let it crash um the
problem is that with when you're
managing Hardware where uh things don't
always crash in a clean way they clean
they they crash in uh dirty and weird
ways and uh they'll manifest in just
things will crash Loop and generate a
terabyte and a half of logs or um uh
your cameras will just you know die and
and stop working and so there's all
these different little mechanisms that
we have that are monitoring the state of
our system and trying to uh detect the
uh degradation in quality um and
depending on what fails we might want to
power cycle the device at a different
level um so the first level is the
device itself so you can through the
remote you know turn it on and turn it
off yeah uh the thing that you might
know owning a television is that turning
it on and off might not actually turn it
off it might turn the screen off but it
might just go into a standby and then
it's just ready to go back on and so
that standby is not you know useful
enough when you have like some weird
state that you're in and you want to
power
cycle
so the next level on the hardware
is power cycle the actual uh Power going
directly to the television itself and
for that we have uh a power relay in our
boxes that is able to turn the device on
and off um kind of sibling to that is
our software that is running next to
these devices um sometimes that goes WR
and so we have Docker containers running
uh we might recycle those Docker
containers so that's another way of
turning it off and on um we might the
compute that's on the device itself we
might need to turn that on and off and
then if all else fails we have a relay
going to the actual wall and we'll turn
off the entire power going to the entire
box off wait a few seconds and back on
again so you've mentioned there we
haven't really looked at it there is is
some kind of computer inside this box
that so the cameras aren't trailing a
wire out to some Central server the
camera there's local processing inside
the container that's right so every sing
so every single one of our devices has
um basically a beefy uh G GPU uh driven
uh computer that's sitting on the device
itself that's running our specialized
software uh and bundling up a bunch of
um a vendor specific uh software that
allows us to communicate with the
television you know they're all
connecting up to our web web platform uh
which is you know saying hey someone
wants to use an LG and you've been uh
selected because you're available you
know start this session and initiate
this web RTC connection uh with this uh
particular user um so all of that is
running you know elixir on our um on our
devices but we're doing doing a lot more
than just um you know taking frames off
of cameras and audio and shipping it you
know we're also doing machine learning
on every frame we're also doing uh
computer vision and audio processing and
uh you know recording the video and
shipping it out to the cloud so that you
can watch you know your sessions after
uh you know you've interacted with it um
so all of that is happening on this uh
specialized piece of Hardware that's
connected to our printed circuit boards
that has all these different referrals
that we can control through our
software
um we also have you know our own power
relay we have a display on the device
that's driven uh by um you know little
C++ program we have that can tell you
the temperature of inside of the box and
can send an alert up to our web platform
if it's crossing a certain threshold uh
there's all these little little things
that we need to be monitoring at all
points in time to make sure that our
boxes are healthy and safe and all that
fun stuff do you also have I mean this
is slight aside but do you also have
like Cooling and how does that interfere
with capturing the
audio that's a very good question uh we
do have cooling we have um kind of the
ambient cooling of the room we have you
know air conditioning that's pumping in
um but we also have on either side of
the Box we've got um two fans that are
uh blowing air in and out of the box uh
to provide circulation so uh not blowing
air in they're blowing air through the
box which provides um yeah enough
cooling to keep the the boxes uh at the
right
temperature so and you as about audio
yeah you asked about audio so
um audio is not the the the noise of the
fans um isn't necessarily a problem
because we don't have a microphone in
there you know we do have the we don't
have HDMI out but we do have audio out
um so we are able to always cuz I would
have thought in for a lot of televisions
you do and for some you
don't um for every device that we're
working with I I believe we do have the
audio out that's e okay yeah I guess I
would have noticed if we didn't because
you'd hear uh you know quite a bit of
noisy chatter of uh you whatever else
anyone is any one of our clients is
testing at any uh point in time yeah
actually that raises the thought that if
you walk into that room at any point it
must be a cacophony different television
channels uh yes okay it is but but it's
you wouldn't see them because they're in
contained in these boxes there's like um
the vent where the fan is you know you
can actually see a little bit into the
box but for the most part it's it's very
much enclosed and um you you you'd be
none the wiser and it's actually pretty
quiet U we do have two fans um but
they're not making a ton of noise
they're um it's a surprisingly quiet
operation
Okay Okay so we've got hor these boxes
that was that was one thing I wanted to
pick you up on you're controlling this
your central controlling software is
erlang right you're running the beam on
the box that's right why Docker as well
they seem to be slightly overlapping in
what they do they do um so
we we've tried many many many different
approaches here um
so this can go into a whole side
conversation and and I I do need to
remember that you asked me about how we
automate working with these televisions
so we have to work our way back to up
yeah there we've got
long
um when we first started out um you know
we we basically just shipping code
directly onto our compute and you know
running it on there natively um which is
U very easy and a lot of ways the
problem that we ran into we're we're
building on top of Nvidia hardware and
the Nvidia Hardware poses a lot of
challenges especially when you're
working with Native libraries um so
we're working with open CV we're working
with um a technology called gstreamer
for our multimedia pipeline we're
working with
um uh what's some other native stuff
we're doing I mean kind of the machine
learn learning stacks and uh you know a
bunch of Nvidia specific uh you know GPU
stuff uh camera drivers all of this um
it becomes very difficult to be able to
uh ship your software to all these
different places and have it run
reliably and to make version upgrades
and changes uh doing it natively on the
box I'm not saying it can't be done um
but what we found is that Docker just be
became a lot simpler for us to be able
to deploy new software we have a build
box that's running on uh an Nvidia
Jetson uh somewhere in our office it's
hooked up as a a GitHub action CI Runner
and we're able to build an image push it
to our local Docker registry all of our
devices uh when they're done with the
session pull it down uh you know power
cycle themselves and it just becomes a
very simple way of uh deploying our
software the other challenge that we
have is that we're running a bunch of
third party software not all of it is uh
designed to be run on arm so we have the
problem of how do you emulate certain
software so we've got quu running quu I
don't know how you say that correctly
but we have I've always wondered q m
that one right the Q emulator Q yeah so
we have some someone will tell us in the
comments how to pronounce it correctly I
hope so um because I've been wondering
for for some time now so we have the
prob of like how do you run this
esoteric uh version of of java 7 or 8 uh
that's you know way too old and has all
these issues how do you make that safe
and run it on the box um if any of these
fail um we do have things that Segall um
need to restart them so Docker is kind
of like maybe bloated and uh way more
than uh necessary but it does uh give us
these really nice way of of releasing
and packing packaging up our software
and allowing us to really rapidly
release new versions to our software uh
without having to think too much about
the
orchestration right right so are you
then not using the kind of hot
deployment um features of the llang beam
are you just doing through Docker okay
we're not there's I mean we're not
really keeping at least in our you know
our Edge compute let's call it we're not
really keeping so much um state that
needs to be maintained between one
session to the next a lot of that is
managed by our web platform that uh you
know keeps cues of you know user a wants
uh you know this particular device and
you know user B wants you know something
slightly different uh but there's one
device that matches both of their
criteria who gets it first uh that kind
of state is uh kind of distributed in
our web platform in a whole different
set of challenges um and that maybe
would be useful to use the hot code
reloading features of the beam but we
don't actually use that anywhere we try
and have other different techniques to
to make sure that that's reliable and
and works well okay in that case it is
time to zoom out of the box you've now
built a box in which you can shove a
television you can tell it things and
you can see what it's showing
back and that that box is now on the
network
what do I do next to build out this
service well um the first thing I think
before you automate televisions is that
to know what you're automating it's
often very helpful to be able to run
through it yourself so and imagine I'm
sitting here with my remote control look
at this I have one right here you know
so I turn it on I go to the you know the
page I want to navigate I go to the
thing and while I'm doing so in my
platform I'm taking screen shots of this
um so we call this our access platform
and how this works is our system you say
I want give me any LG and it will pair
you with the first available LG it
doesn't care um you know what year it is
or whatever um whatever constraints you
can make a very broad request just say
give me the first thing that's available
okay I can go and test on it take those
screenshots uh and now I have a good
sense of the path for which I want to
test then I go into our automation uh
product um this is um a very visual uh
tool for interacting with the system and
we allow you to basically take those
screenshots that you just took in your
your access session and mark them up so
um imagine that you wanted to go
to
um let's make up an example here um
there's there's some um some apps where
you might have like a channel guide um
I'm think of one very particular uh app
developer but I don't want to use their
name uh so imagine you have like a a
channel guide where there's all these
different shows that you could watch on
their app um and so you want to navigate
over to that you want to pick a
particular show you want to watch it you
then want to pause it and test that when
you scrub back and forward that it
actually moves you back through content
and then when you hit play it serves you
an ad that seems like a very reasonable
thing to want test yes so the way that
this works in our platform um because
we're trying to Target across all these
different devices using something like
you know HTML you know hooking into your
code or using you know the structure of
HTML to test semantic things um in the
Dom it just doesn't work well for this
type of testing um and so we've taken
this very visual based approach where um
you kind of tell the system you give it
visual cues
for you know if this um this logo if it
appears on this Pace on the on the this
place on the page and there's this text
that says uh you know home in this
particular part of the screen and this
thing is uh dominantly you know this
particular color of yellow over here I
have a pretty good idea that I'm on the
homepage so right so
you where you are right so our system
can then take that and uh
it will be able to to you know process
every frame and then look in those
rectangles that you drew and say what am
I seeing here am I seeing you know this
particular piece of text so I'll be
running you know different types of
machine learning to pull this
information out you know pulling
bounding boxes and uh you know using OCR
to grab
text um from that you can build a
workflow so we have just drag and drop
tool and you'll do something like open
this app wait for the homepage to load
check am I logged in or am I logged out
based on the presence of you know the
the login model yeah if I'm if I'm
logged out go through this workflow if
I'm logged out go for this other
workflow okay now I'm logged in now I
need to go to that channel page that we
talked about so issue these set of
commands um use you know generative AI
to you know navigate around the screen
uh because now maybe there's some
complex menu that I need to navigate and
the content change es dynamically so you
know we'll grab a frame we'll generate
the series of the sequence of up down
left rights and enters to get to where
you need to go um then we'll use our uh
Vision based system to the video starts
playing we're grabbing frames and um our
system can kind of understand the
content that's playing and be able to
draw some certain types of information
from it and then you know we can detect
the ad based on maybe some content or
the presence of you know some text on
the screen uh or maybe we know the ad or
we can fake it by you know intercepting
the network uh and so you can do
assertions in our platform based on that
um so this whole visual system is kind
of how we can pose these tests together
right pause there for a second right
yeah
so so I I do this markup stage first
before I manually against one known
television and then I can script out the
whole thing which you will then compile
down and send to the individual
container so you found me because of Lua
on the beam and this is where this
enters the picture right okay
so uh I'm trying to describe this to you
uh without a visual aid but we have this
drag and drop workflow Builder right and
as I said open app wait for the screen
enter these series of commands maybe use
the keyboard to enter some text to
search for a particular piece of content
you could do it all through this visual
tool that's designed for QA who are
maybe not necessarily uh
developers that workflow that you see
visually compiles into Lua code this Lua
code um is using our our DSL that we've
built um and that gets shipped down to
our physical device that physical device
implements that DSL which is using
computer vision and machine learning
behind the hood uh but also interacting
with our hardware apis and maybe some of
these vendor specific apis to actually
run through the test run through that
workflow make certain assertions um you
know run Loops do whatever it needs to
do um and then adid events back up to
our web platform that then get
visualized for you and you have this
like really um interesting visual way of
seeing not just the recorded video of
your test being run but the state of the
system as it's running through that so
the system will be like okay right now I
know that we're on the homepage based on
what you've told me about the homepage
uh these are this is the network uh
activity while this is happening this is
the Audio Level while this is happening
uh these are the you know elements on
the screen that you've told me about I
recognize the presence of this thing
this thing is not here and from this you
could build this really um powerful way
of navigating and making assertions
about content and then reporting it and
being able to see changes between
different
runs okay so if I then go to test this
against a dozen different kinds of
Television am I going to be able to step
through and say okay they all made it to
the login page they all made it to the
CH channel guide page but one of them
didn't make it past the channel gu guide
page and got stuck and that's the one I
need to do testing on so when you when
you write a test on our platform you can
then schedule it and say I want this to
run on these five different devices and
because it's Visual and because most of
the time uh the look and feel of these
apps is pretty consistent across devices
this becomes pretty powerful for writing
these um endtoend tests uh in that are
implemented in completely different
Technologies and so what you're pointing
out is that you can find inconsistencies
in implementation or bugs or maybe
slowness or buffering or just some issue
that you weren't expecting on one
particular device um and so you might
run this test and you might run it
against you know I make a code change in
my app I'm G to sideload a build uh
through the tvls platform on my CI it
then runs on these devices and it
reports back to you it worked great on
Panasonic it worked great on Sony it
worked great on Samsung but on Fire TV
you had this issue
and then you can go in see the recording
see what the system was doing as it was
navigating through your test and then
you have all this information including
you know the device logs and kind of all
the Telemetry that we're collecting also
networking Network calls and things like
that that you can go and inspect and
figure out what went wrong and maybe go
into your logs and correlate some sort
of issue yeah cuz remembering the the
bad old days of the browser Wars I my
expectation would be that it fails on
something most of the time for some dumb
reason mhm right and you
yeah okay
so I've
never I've never really been happy with
this kind of front end testing because
it's always fiddly and messy but that
doesn't
sound if if if it doesn't sound ideal it
at least sounds like we're approaching
the best that can be
done is that fair to say I I think so I
think the ideal experience is that you
have um something akin to you know open
Telemetry running inside of your actual
app and you have all the traces and um
you know everything that you might need
uh to be able to debug the issue and you
might actually have that um and you
might have that in production you'll
have you know your analytic systems that
can do measurements um but we're talking
about uh many different stages in the
software development life cycle um and
you also have to think of the uh volume
of changes and the audience and the
fragmentation of where all these apps
are going you know they might be going
on uh I don't I actually don't even know
the count but it could be hundreds or
you know I don't think thousands but
maybe hundreds of different Target
platforms with slightly different
versions and things like this we have
the same problem in browsers but the the
tech techology is more consistent um
yeah yeah so solving these problems um
is very challenging and the point that
we're trying to come in is that we can
help you in any different part of the
software development life cycle uh and
we're trying to provide you tools that
provide all this different Telemetry
where when things are flaky which they
will be um we can give you more
indication for why they're flaky was it
because the network was um being finicky
we couldn't load the content from this
particular uh CDN pop or uh maybe it's
because on this one particular platform
you actually do have a legitimate bug
that you need to fix um we're trying to
help you isolate those and to be able to
run it on these different platforms so
that you can find these inconsistencies
and be able to fix them without having
to manage this massive Fleet of hardware
and have uh you know an operations team
to manage it we we try to do that solve
all those problems for you yeah yeah I I
see that as the as the business pitch
yeah and it makes sense right because
that's that would be hard to do inhouse
unless you're one of the huge players in
which case you're probably going to end
up trying to solve the same problems
that you're solving or just thr at it
yeah and even if you have you know the
budget to throw a lot of money at it
these are really challenging uh
technology problems and it's not just
like one there's one big problem it's
like many many many different all to
medium and large siiz follows let me ask
you about one specific one cuz it's like
a devil's in the detail type thing that
comes up in these I have found as a user
of like TV apps that sometimes you're
trying to navigate around a 2d space
that wants a mouse but you've only got
up down left and right on the remote
control so getting the cursor from where
it currently is highlighting to the
thing you actually would like to click
on is sometimes really counter ative
right some sometimes you click left and
the the highlighted button jumps to a
place you didn't expect right how on
Earth does machine learning get around
the potential craziness of navigation
you get in
televisions well we have the luxury of
being able to view many many many many
different sessions of interactions with
televisions okay um so um and I'm not
trying to claim that we've solved this
problem I think this is kind of one of
our biggest challenges that we have to
overcome which is can we really you know
build an agent that can truly understand
what you're seeing on a TV understand
what is navigatable and what's not
what's clickable and what's not and be
able to infer um any different one of
these things um there's a feedback loop
there which is if I press left what
changes on the screen am I able to
recognize what is actually you know
currently highlighted on the screen uh
to some extent we're able to do that to
other extent it's really specific to the
app and the platform you're on this
might be uh as you said I'm imagining
these like uh kind of like sidebar
navigation things where these things
like pop into existence that you didn't
expect and you know jump over uh or
sometimes you hit left and it just stays
exactly in in the same place and it's
only when you hit the back button does
it jump you back to the menu yeah crazy
navigation and TV app it's definitely a
thing yes so I I think this problem is
solved um over time by being able to
train on um an agent that is able to
um be anchored at any one point in the
screen make a change observe what
changes on the screen and then uh if it
has the ability to infer uh what are the
pieces of content that are navigatable
clickable uh you can sort of build like
a graph of understanding of this is how
I move across the app um and if you can
do this with enough uh time and enough
uh examples you can actually build a
whole map of how to get from point A to
point B uh through enough of these
iterations so I think that's kind of the
goal is if we can automate that then we
have a really powerful system that could
actually probably crawl your your TV app
and find your issues for you but we're
not not quite there yet today I can see
how you've got the training data if not
yet the solution that's right okay so I
think we should then get into uh
scheduling because this is clearly a
problem how many different kinds of TV
you actually have in in the
warehouse what kind of are we talking
about um I don't want to reveal too many
numbers I would say give power of
10 we'll be in the hundreds um hundreds
okay the challenge that we have
is it's not just about like different
typ YP of device because for any given
manufacturer they probably have a
low-end
television medium and uh you know
high-end device at all different price
points they also have them at all
different sizes and then different
capabilities maybe some are built
for uh something called like uh oh man
I'm blanking on this there's a new
standard for streaming that has kind of
GNA disrupt App Stores um and there's
something called 3.0 atsc 3 3.0 which is
a combination of broadcast and you know
Internet Protocol coming together so you
might have certain devices that have
these capabilities that I think are
called NextGen televisions you'll
probably be hearing about this in the
next few years right
um we need to have kind of all of those
but we what's actually really key is we
don't have to have all the different
sizes it that tends to not matter so
much what matters is the lowend versus
the highend are going to have very
different capabilities and have
different performance capabilities but
the 42 in versus the 65 in probably
going to be about the same and so we've
optimized our Fleet to be able to carry
55 inch televisions because most
manufacturers have that size it's pretty
popular
size um now I mentioned much earlier
that the problem that we tend to hear
from our clients is not do you have this
latest and greatest um device it's do
you have this like device from seven
years ago that's you know eight% of my
audience is still on that we having this
one bug on that's breaking all all all
streaming you know maybe a you know a
very old boxer is uh you know fighting
some YouTuber and uh yeah
yeah you know we we have to solve that
problem yeah because I imagine most
people only change their television once
a decade so you've got to support the
old stuff that's right so so we have I
think going back like uh it's like six
or seven model years uh for most devices
and you know our inventory tends to be
smaller around the older stuff and you
know more volume around the the newer
types of devices um but then you we have
these uh shelves of of set top boxes
that we keep talking about where those
are really easy because they're small
and uh you know in a small volume you
can have a lot of them yeah um but it's
the the televisions that that pose our
biggest challenge okay
so I'm imagining that you've gone
through this Warehouse of hundreds of
sep toop boxes and televisions and
you've tagged them with metadata like
I'm an LG device I'm 55 in wide I come
from this year and I'm running this
operating system right that's right and
then I as an app developer say I want to
test on one of each of the major brands
now you have have a classic scheduling
and queuing
problem right you've got to ship that
test to the available TVs that match
those criteria tell me about that
sure um so we have we called our demand
system uh and it's it it's a very boring
name but it takes demand for particular
devices and it matches a user uh based
on a priority cue of um you know do I
have a license so we we charge uh for
our product based on concurrent access
to televisions so depending on the
number of licenses that you have um we
will allow you to to connect to that
many televisions at once so if you have
three licenses then you can run a test
and at the same time we could run it on
three different devices um but you are
also competing with your teammates who
uh you know might not like that yeah so
we will um each each one of our clients
um sits on a different queue and so if
you uh ceue up uh I know 100 different
tests we will try to run all those 100
tests for you there is a Max time for
how long we'll let something sit in the
queue uh but you can schedule up all
this different demand and we will serve
it to you based on the number of
concurrent licenses but we will
prioritize uh those requests uh globally
uh across all the different
organizations who might be using our
devices uh in sort of a round robin
fashion so uh what this does is it it
minimizes the amount of contention
between uh you know different
organizations who might be competing for
the same devices um and we'll we'll
prioritize based on time but if you
haven't had uh a request recently and
someone is uh putting in a lot of volume
that will over time uh start to Decay a
little bit and get prioritized a little
bit lower than the person who's just
like hey I'm here to test today and you
know I'm not sending so much volume
through our
system so so this is optimizing for
throughput there that's right individual
yeah okay that's right uh so we want our
system to be utilized and we want it to
be um you know as high we want to be
able to use our capacity to uh its full
extent as much as possible yeah um and
so to order to do this we keep um
I guess you can kind of think of it as
like a distributed database but we keep
an inmemory uh database that uses crdts
to track um the current state of each
device in our
Fleet okay that's interesting I wouldn't
have thought crdt is come into this tell
me tell me more tell me more okay so our
web platform needs to be able to serve
uh many different geographic regions
because we have uh customers who are in
the US we also have customers who are in
Europe and the UK we have customers who
are uh working in Asia and you know
places like India you know Tokyo things
like that so our web platform uh you
know is running different uh Edge
compute all over the place uh to be able
to to have a nice experience for those
customers because it's a very
interactive uh platform that we offer um
the problem here is that each individual
device can only be used uh you know by a
single user at a time yeah yeah yeah um
so um in that sense each of one of our
devices is its own source of Truth for
uh am I available or am I
not um however sending a request to
every single device and being like hey
are you available um to take take on a
new session is you know not very
efficient um and also those devices I
mentioned they you know connect up to
our web platform they might not be
connected to the same node that you're
currently interacting with you know I
I'm connecting to our web platform I'm
using Phoenix live view to to interact
with with the web platform um I'm in I'm
sitting in London whereas we have a
server sitting in uh New Jersey uh so
our device actually might be connected
up to that uh device in New Jersey now
someone some other user in San Francisco
might have just use that and now it
becomes available how do you know about
it uh this is where the crdt comes into
play so the crd is uh keeping track of
the current state of each television is
it available is it online is it in use
is it healthy um is it available for
connection um and we basically use that
our our demand system is querying that
thing as kind of like the first uh check
for uh can I serve this this user
request right now or do I need to keep
them waiting and well we'll let them
know that you know there's nothing
available and that we expect something
to come online soon or that their
teammate is currently using it and all
this information is tracked by the crdt
right um but when it comes time to okay
we now think that this device is
available uh We've selected you to pair
with it will then initiate a session the
way that this works is that even if
you're sitting in London but the device
is in New Jersey uh through our Pub
subsystem it will send the uh request
for the session down to that device and
now because that device is a source of
Truth it will either accept it and by
sending a message back and saying let's
initiate a web RTC connection uh or
we'll direct it and say hey I'm actually
unhealthy or you know it reported my
session as available and I'm actually
unavailable due to some bug um but
that's that ends up being the source of
Truth the crdt is the thing that keeps
it fast and is kind of like this like in
memory database for um knowing who's
available in
online okay so it's kind of like um
you're connecting to a central server to
find out which peer-to-peer connections
you're allowed to make that's right of
yeah yeah yeah sort of yeah uh and the
demand server is connecting to the local
database which replicates the actual
source of Truth which is the individual
container that's right I think I have
that in my head okay that's right and
and when we say server we're talking
about you know we just have our
um Elixir uh apps running the cloud
there's not like all these different
microservices that are responsible for
one thing it's just one web platform
that has all these different
responsibilities managed by gen servers
that use things like hash rings to
distribute the the load uh across all
the different servers globally right I
was going to say is the is this does
this actually end up just being a bunch
of erlang actors and is that the reason
for choosing
llang well there's many different
reasons for choosing
erlang so okay there's a lot of problems
that
um that we're trying to solve that I
think erlang and elixir and and the beam
VM the bur beam virtual machine are very
good at so the beam virtual machine is
really good at fault tolerance you know
let it crash we'll restart it for you if
it goes down yeah um it's good at uh low
latency and and you know decently High
throughput systems um and it's really
good with um Building Systems that are
relatively simple due to a mutable data
and functional
programming um and then there's the
whole distribution aspect which is being
able to connect nodes that are globally
distributed and have them communicate to
each other and send messages back and
forth and uh subscribe to different
topics of interest and not really have
to worry about the orchestration of that
all yeah and what's really bread and
butter programming inl right it's not a
weird thing yeah that's right and so
what's what's so interesting I think
about Elixir uh for this particular
solution is in any other programming
language you'll probably have to have a
constellation of other services that are
just for doing the communication um like
if we take websockets for an example all
of our different um devices TVs and sets
up boxes the way that they communicate
up to our web platform is that they make
a websocket connection for most other
systems you'll have to have a separate
service just for holding on to those
websocket connections and then using
something like uh rabbit mq or something
else to do uh you know venting to all
your other systems we could just do that
in Elixir and llang and that that's
really easy but the part the thing that
that enables is so interesting is you
can now do distributed Pub sub where I
can click a button in the UI that emits
an event and that is just Pub subed
directly down to the device that's
listening to a particular topic and it
acts as this like giant distributed
system that's heterogeneous that's
actually running very different code but
it can um you know communicate with all
the other nodes in the system with very
little effort and there's this term that
I think that's been going around in the
beam community that I really like and
that I think is comes to the core of why
I like it so much which is operational
Simplicity in order to do this it takes
a very little effort it takes very
little effort to build these kind of
tools and to network it together is just
through DNS um to do the the websocket
connection is like these standard tools
through the Phoenix framework that um
are just very available and easy to use
and would require uh quite a lot of
specialized knowledge and uh operational
complexity in order to deliver in most
other platforms yeah now that's not to
say that we don't use a lot of other
Technologies we've got rust we've got go
we've got C++ we have Lua we have
JavaScript uh but Elixir sits at the
core and kind of solves these uh
fundamental data distribution and
communication problems for us yeah yeah
I can see if I would just taking this on
paper I
Would by the time you've got to obvious
complex failure
modes interesting networking protocols
web sockets web RTC lots of scheduling
stuff and queuing I'd be surprised if
elix if um at least erlang in one of its
flavors wasn't on the short list of
Technologies you use can I ask why
Elixir rather than pure Lang or maybe
gleam um well the reason I left
Bloomberg back in 2016 was that u a
manager of mine um I was kind of
interested in Elm at the time I had oh
yeah done a little bit of a stint of a
hasal uh in my programming languages
class in in college and when I joined
Bloomberg I was doing uh quite a bit of
C++ and Fortran and that's a whole other
conversation um I then dipped my toes
into JavaScript and I mentioned that
whole uh single page app framework um
but I was kind of like itching for
something else and I got into this uh
functional programming kick with Elm and
I'm like this is so cool my my manager
was like you like Elm you'd probably
really like this uh this thing that this
guy in the Ruby Community uh has been
talking about called
Elixir and so I was like oh let me try
that and what I found with Elixir was
this idea of pattern matching which is
something i' never seen in any other
programming language um and that was the
thing that got me hooked and so I left
Bloomberg to go do uh a media startup
called the outline back in 2016 and I
basically have never looked back because
once I found Elixir um I just found the
way of solving problems um just so uh
approachable and um it just made things
that I thought were really hard and the
other languages I've used before really
elegant and simple um and I was able to
approach um really interesting problems
you know I I was at a sports betting
company for four years and we're doing a
lot of real-time data processing um and
we built almost the entire platform in a
Elixir
um it's just something that I think is I
don't want to say it's part of my
identity but I I have um built you know
a lot of knowledge and and uh expertise
in it and I find that um you know I'm
able to do a lot with very little
relative Resources with the beam and
elixir has just been my tool of choice
uh now I know you've had Louie uh pfold
on the on the podcast him and I were uh
we sat for dinner at code bmeu last
month in Berlin um he's been working on
gleam for the last four or five years
now I'm not sure and I've been
sponsoring him since close to the very
beginning because I think it's just so
great the beam is this amazing piece of
technology that's in my opinion very
underutilized um and it's great to have
more players and more ways to onboard
people into the ecosystem so um you know
if there's something better that that
comes out than a looker I I would
certainly try it you know I've got my uh
my rewrited and rust uh poster right
here
uh I I love technology and I I love
trying new things but um Elixir is just
kind of this um this Hammer that I find
it it's it's useful in so many different
contexts and is uh so capable um and
allows me to you know to with just very
few people build a a product like TV
Labs U with with relative ease and kind
of like a straightforward path so that's
why I'm really excited about it I can
see both the natural fit with the domain
given the amount of networking and
queuing and reliability and even the
people I know who like have the broadest
tastes and pallets for programming
languages they usually have a favorite
one too which is just the place you go
to get stuff done right it's home yeah
yeah yeah I think mine at the moment is
pure script but I'm always tempted away
slightly I love P script and it's my
it's my language I choose when I don't
want to think about which language to
use wow you know I haven't heard of Pur
script being used in in quite some time
the one that does keep popping up is um
is it reason
ml oh yeah yeah there's a very is that
the one that's very uh frontend focused
and is kind of like uh has a really
tight integration with the react uh it's
um oh no we did the whole episode on
this and I wasn't expecting a test but
yeah it's like if you want to take o
camel to the browser that's where you go
I think is rescript I don't they might
be related I my o camel is
um I need to dabble in O camel there
there's some cool things happening in
that community over there me too me too
yeah um I need to spend more time with o
camel there are only so many hours in
the day that leads me to ask perhaps to
to wrap up hours in the day where are
you where are you spending yours in the
coming months what's left to solve in
this
space so we're uh we've been in business
now for about a year and a half and
we're we've been working with customers
and clients uh but we're very much in
our go to market phase and so a lot of
this is taking these fundamental uh
uh products and features and making them
very usable really dialing in the ux I
think we've spent most most of our time
making the system
reliable and you know the five different
ways of restarting our system is kind of
goes into it where we've had to dog food
our our platform and use it over and
over and over again and run into all
these stumbling blocks and it's only
until recently where we feel that our
platform is so reliable that it's it's
really useful for other people too um
and so what we're spending most of our
time on is in JavaScript land and and
spelt and is in polishing these tools
and uh building these features for
introspecting state and really being
able to visualize what's happening in
our system so that it's really easy to
go and diagnose a problem um and this is
kind of like the very top layer of our
system where all of that lowlevel stuff
underneath it uh is kind of abstracted
away from you and our product just seems
like you know so boring and you know
obvious that you'd be able to work with
a television but there's just all these
little bits and pieces and hard problems
that we've solved along the way uh that
make the the high level thing really
work um so my time and my focus is uh
you know spending a lot of time leading
the team to to kind of solve these ux
problems and make the the the product
usable uh in a way to analyze your
problems and find correlations and kind
of build you know like the
observability uh tooling part of our
product that makes uh that makes
reported error in in C
uh easy to dive into find the root cause
and jump back out of our product yeah
yeah as hard as stitching together four
live video streams in a in a reliable
scheduled cued distributed network of
Television sound it's probably still not
the hard part the hard part is making
things usable for users that's right
that's always the hard part it's
JavaScript that's the hardest
part I I'm not saying a word to that you
said it your now record oh
no on that note maybe I should leave you
to go back to presumably figma and keep
working on the ux that's right Dave
thanks very much that's that is
fascinating and one day I'd like to go
and visit the warehouse where all the
televisions are kept we'd love to have
you awesome thanks thank you Dave as
always you'll find links to the things
we discussed in the show notes and if
you've enjoyed this episode please take
a moment to like it share it with a
friend friend or a social network and
make sure you're subscribed because
we'll be back next week with another no
we won't actually we won't be back next
week with another episode because I'll
be taking a break for Christmas so happy
Christmas if you celebrate it and you
know just general happiness from me if
you don't thank you very much for all
your support during this year especially
if you're one of the people that
supports us on patreon or YouTube
memberships and helps keep developer
voices running thank you before we go
I'm going to leave you with a question
Dave mentioned the apples and Netflix's
of this world and it got me wondering
you hear people in this industry
debating what the plural of database
index is so I ask you is the plural of
Netflix Netflix's or
Netflix I shall be spending far too much
time thinking about that over the
holidays so on that note I've been your
host Chris Jenkins this has been
developer voices with Dave Luchia thanks
for listening thank
[Music]